<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Conservation-and-analyses on </title>
    <link>/conservation-and-analysis/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Conservation-and-analyses on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    
	<atom:link href="/conservation-and-analysis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Conservation and Analysis</title>
      <link>/conservation-and-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/conservation-and-analysis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sustainable Conservation of Bronze Artworks</title>
      <link>/conservation-and-analysis/35-casaletto/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/conservation-and-analysis/35-casaletto/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Conservation Science is a field that has been in continuous evolution since the late twentieth century. The study of ancient bronzes has long focused on archaeometry, addressing technological aspects and production concerns. Casting cores, alloys, joins, surface patinas, and corrosion products have been intensively investigated by various analytical techniques in order to improve our knowledge of the original materials, processes, manufacturing techniques, and degradation phenomena. Scientific results provided very useful information to archaeologists, art historians, and conservators about the artistry, craftsmanship, production, conservation, and restoration of ancient bronze artifacts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Investigating Ancient “Bronzes”</title>
      <link>/conservation-and-analysis/36-tykot/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/conservation-and-analysis/36-tykot/</guid>
      <description>X-Ray Fluorescence X-ray fluorescence (XRF) is one of many analytical methods used to determine the composition of copper-based metal objects. When used non-destructively, however, care must be taken to understand the principles of this method and thus the significance of the results. XRF analysis involves primary X-rays striking the sample and creating electron vacancies in an inner shell of the atoms; these vacancies are then filled by lower-energy electrons from an outer shell, while producing secondary X-rays.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Scientific Assessment of the Long-Term Protection of Incralac Coatings on Ancient Bronze Collections in the National Archaeological Museum and the Epigraphic and Numismatic Museum, in Athens, Greece</title>
      <link>/conservation-and-analysis/37-boyatzis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/conservation-and-analysis/37-boyatzis/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Among the main criteria for selecting a coating for cultural heritage metal artifacts are (1) long-term insulation of their surfaces from contaminants due to environmental pollutants and handling; (2) the filtration of light through absorption of radiation; (3) considerable adhesion to the metal surface and elasticity; and finally (4) chemical stability. Ease of application and reversibility are also among the highly sought requirements.
Incralac was introduced by INCRA (International Copper Research Association) in 1964 as a metal protective coating based on the acrylic resin Paraloid B44 (an ethylacrylate –methylmethacrylate copolymer) with benzotriazole (BTA) as a main additive.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Approaches in Stabilizing Chloride-Contaminated Ancient Bronzes Using Corrosion Inhibitors and/or Electrochemical Methods to Preserve Information in the Patinas</title>
      <link>/conservation-and-analysis/38-argyropoulos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/conservation-and-analysis/38-argyropoulos/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Ancient bronzes often contain surface decoration in the corrosion layers or show evidence of tinning, niello, gilding, paint, or organic materials in the corrosion layers. Depending on the quantity of chlorides in their surfaces, traditional conservation methods to stabilize bronze disease are either used locally to treat the artifact with Ag2O particles or zinc dust, with complete immersion in sodium sesquicarbonate (pH 10) solutions with or without electrolysis to convert cupreous chloride to more stable corrosion product(s);1 and/or incorporate the use of corrosion inhibitors, such as benzotriazole.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conservation Treatments and Archaeometallurgical Insights on the Medici Riccardi Horse Head</title>
      <link>/conservation-and-analysis/39-salvioli/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/conservation-and-analysis/39-salvioli/</guid>
      <description>History of the Artifact The equine bronze protome known as the Medici Riccardi horse head in the Museo Archeologico Nazionale of Florence is likely a surviving part of a Hellenistic life-size equestrian sculptural group, which has been dated around the second half of the fourth century BC.1 The sculpture entered the antiquarian collections of the Medici in the fifteenth century and was cited for the first time in 1495 as part of Lorenzo il Magnifico’s antiquarian collection,2 although it had certainly been found well before that.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Cleveland *Apollo*</title>
      <link>/conservation-and-analysis/40-northover/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/conservation-and-analysis/40-northover/</guid>
      <description>Introduction and Pre-accession Investigation The only life-size bronze version of the sculptural type traditionally known as Apollo Sauroktonos (Apollo the Lizard-Slayer), now renamed Apollo the Python-Slayer and attributed to Praxiteles, is part of the permanent collection of the Cleveland Museum of Art (inv. 2004.30; fig. 40.1a–d).1 There are approximately twenty other known sculptures of this type that exist, all in marble with one reduced-scale bronze copy.2
 Figure 40.1a. Apollo the Python-Slayer, ca.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Getty Herm of Dionysos</title>
      <link>/conservation-and-analysis/41-maish/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/conservation-and-analysis/41-maish/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Ancient Athenians are reported to have been the first to erect herms that served as boundary markers in both urban and rural settings and also stood in the entrances of private homes and temples; at one location herms became so numerous that one structure near the Agora was named the Stoa of the Herms. This proliferation and high demand perhaps led to the development of copying and serial reproduction methods, and the Getty Herm of Dionysos (J.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Technological Reexamination of the Piombino Apollo</title>
      <link>/conservation-and-analysis/42-mille-descamps/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/conservation-and-analysis/42-mille-descamps/</guid>
      <description>Epigraphic and Stylistic Reevaluation of the Piombino Apollo The Piombino Apollo (fig. 42.1) was among the statues gathered for the exhibition Power and Pathos: Bronze Sculpture of the Hellenistic World at the J. Paul Getty Museum and the accompanying symposium.1 It is an Archaizing work, as was already suggested by Jean Letronne in 1834, just two years after the bronze was discovered in the sea off the west coast of Piombino, Italy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Results on the Alloys of the Croatian Apoxyomenos</title>
      <link>/conservation-and-analysis/43-vidovic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/conservation-and-analysis/43-vidovic/</guid>
      <description>Introduction The statue of an Apoxyomenos (fig. 43.1), raised from the Adriatic Sea off Croatia in 1999, has been thoroughly restored and investigated at the Croatian Conservation Institute (HRZ). It has been exhibited in Zagreb, Osijek, Rijeka, Split, and Zadar in Croatia, as well as in Florence, Ljubljana, Paris, London, and Los Angeles. Results of conservation-restoration works and investigations have been published and presented at several conferences, including international congresses on ancient bronzes in Bucharest (2003) and Zurich (2013).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Bronze Sculpture of Alexander the Great on Horseback</title>
      <link>/conservation-and-analysis/44-siano/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/conservation-and-analysis/44-siano/</guid>
      <description>The equestrian bronze group of Alexander on horseback in the National Archaeological Museum of Naples (inv. 4996), which is dated around the first century BC, was found in Herculaneum during the Bourbon excavation campaigns of the second half of the eighteenth century (fig. 44.1a–b). According to the sources, the statuette, whose restored height is 49 centimeters, was mostly excavated on October 22, 1761, within a tunnel at the Theater under the Casa dei Colli Mozzi.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Auloi from Meroë</title>
      <link>/conservation-and-analysis/45-gansicke/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/conservation-and-analysis/45-gansicke/</guid>
      <description>Discovery and Introduction In 1921, Harvard Egyptologist George A. Reisner excavated Pyramid N 6 (also called Beg. N. 6), the burial of Queen Amanishakheto, in Meroë, Sudan.1 This pyramid had been discovered in the early nineteenth century by the Italian physician and explorer Giuseppe Ferlini. While investigating the pyramid, much of which was destroyed during the process, Ferlini came upon a rich trove of gold jewelry.2
A few objects however remained in the tomb, to be discovered only when excavations were undertaken in the stairway leading to the underground burial chamber.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Defined Protocol for In Situ Micro-XRF Compositional Analysis of Bronze Figurines from the National Museum of Damascus, Syria</title>
      <link>/conservation-and-analysis/46-kantarelou/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/conservation-and-analysis/46-kantarelou/</guid>
      <description>Introduction During the PROMET European FP6 project, a micro-XRF mobile spectrometer was transported to the National Museum of Damascus, Syria, where it was applied and validated for the quantitative noninvasive analysis of unique museum metal collections across the Mediterranean region, successfully addressing archaeological and conservation questions. Given the value of these collections, transport of objects or sampling for analysis is generally not permitted. Thus, the development and validation of a reliable portable technology is critical for comparisons of analytical compositional results, especially for similar museum collections or objects housed around the world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is There an Ultimate Authority in Authenticity?</title>
      <link>/conservation-and-analysis/47-anderson-eremin-lie-bewer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/conservation-and-analysis/47-anderson-eremin-lie-bewer/</guid>
      <description>On display in the Harvard Art Museums is a statuette of Alexander the Great, sometimes referred to as the Alexander Nelidow after its first known owner.1 The statuette first appeared in the Istanbul bazaar sometime before 1897.2 The original condition of the surface when excavated can only be guessed at: the surface had already been cleaned of any unsightly burial accretions by the time the first images appear.3 Alexander is depicted as a nude youth, standing with his left arm raised, probably to grasp a spear.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Riace Bronze Statues</title>
      <link>/conservation-and-analysis/abstract-angelini-et-al/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/conservation-and-analysis/abstract-angelini-et-al/</guid>
      <description> Bibliography  Alpine Archaeocopper Project http://geo.geoscienze.unipd.it/aacp/welcome.html Arias 1986 Arias, P. E. 1986. “Analisi critica delle statue [The Critical Analysis of the Statues].” In Gli Eroi venuti dal mare, ed. L. M. Lombardi Satriani, et al. 39–64. Università della Calabria, Studi e Ricerche 19. Gangemi: Università della Calabria. BRETTSCAIFE.net http://brettscaife.net/lead/data/index.html OXALID http://oxalid.arch.ox.ac.uk/  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Balancing Artifacts</title>
      <link>/conservation-and-analysis/abstract-azema-mille-descamps-lequime/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/conservation-and-analysis/abstract-azema-mille-descamps-lequime/</guid>
      <description>Bibliography  Boube-Piccot 1969 Boube-Piccot, C. 1969. Les bronzes antiques du Maroc. Vol. 1: La statuaire. Etudes et Travaux d’Archeologie Marocaine 4. Rabat: Royaume du Maroc. Hemingway 2015 Hemingway, S. “Statue of Eros Sleeping.” In Power and Pathos: Bronze Sculpture of the Hellenistic World, ed. J. M. Daehner and K. Lapatin, no. 20, 228–29. Los Angeles: J. Paul Getty Museum. Mattusch 1996 Mattusch, C. C. 1996. Classical Bronzes: The Art and Craft of Greek and Roman Statuary.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Copper, War, and Art in Ancient Greece</title>
      <link>/conservation-and-analysis/abstract-diaz/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/conservation-and-analysis/abstract-diaz/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modern and Ancient Metal Fakes</title>
      <link>/conservation-and-analysis/abstract-giumlia-mair/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/conservation-and-analysis/abstract-giumlia-mair/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Examination, Conservation, and Analysis of a Composed Egyptian Ibis Statue</title>
      <link>/conservation-and-analysis/abstract-mahmoud-matsuda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/conservation-and-analysis/abstract-mahmoud-matsuda/</guid>
      <description> Bibliography  Janssens et al. 2000 Janssens, K., et al. 2000. “The Use of Microscopic XRF for Non-destructive Analysis in Art and Archaeometry.” X-Ray Spectrum 29: 73–91.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Technical Examinations on the Parthian Bronze Coffin from Chubtarash Archaeological Site, Khorramabad, Western Iran</title>
      <link>/conservation-and-analysis/abstract-oudbashi-hassari-hassanpour/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/conservation-and-analysis/abstract-oudbashi-hassari-hassanpour/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Material Interpretation of Ancient Large Bronzes</title>
      <link>/conservation-and-analysis/abstract-siano/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/conservation-and-analysis/abstract-siano/</guid>
      <description>Bibliography  Cygielman 2008 Cygielman, M., ed. 2008. La Minerva di Arezzo. Exh. cat. Florence, Soprintendenza per i Beni Archeologici della Toscana. Iozzo 1998 Iozzo M., ed. 1998 “&amp;hellip; qual era tutto rotto”: L’enigma dell’idolino di Pesaro: Indagini per un restauro. Exh. cat. Florence, Museo Archeologico Nazionale. Siano et al. 2012 Siano, S., M. Miccio, M. Giamello, S. Mugnaini, and J. Agresti. 2012. “Journey through the Material Layers of the Chimaera from Arezzo.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Abstracts</title>
      <link>/conservation-and-analysis/abstracts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/conservation-and-analysis/abstracts/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>