<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/</link>
    <description>Recent content on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    
	<atom:link href="https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Cover</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contents</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/contents/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/contents/</guid>
      <description> Cover List of Previous Bronze Congresses, Proceedings, and Related Exhibitions Directors’ Foreword — Timothy Potts and Tim Whalen Introduction — Jens M. Daehner, Kenneth Lapatin, Ambra Spinelli   Large-Scale Bronzes The Artist Statuettes The Hellenistic East Vessels Artifacts Conservation and Analysis   About   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>International Bronze Congresses and Associated Publications and Exhibitions</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/congresses/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/congresses/</guid>
      <description>1970 NIJMEGEN
Ist International Congress on Ancient Bronzes, April 20–23, 1970. Rijksmuseum G. M. Kam, Nijmegen, Netherlands.
Acta: 1970. “Tagung über römische Bronzegefäße im Rijksmuseum G. M. Kam in Nijmegen von 20. bis einschließlich 23. April 1970.” Hektogr. Niederschrift (Nijmegen).
 1972 MAINZ
IInd International Congress on Ancient Bronzes, May 23–26, 1972. Mainz, Germany.
Acta: H. Menzel, ed. 1973. “Bericht über die Tagung &amp;lsquo;Römische Toreutik’ vom 23–26. Mai 1972 in Mainz.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Directors’ Foreword</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/foreword/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/foreword/</guid>
      <description>The Getty has long been committed to the appreciation, study, and conservation of ancient bronzes. Much like Cicero and others who valued these works for their history, beauty, and craftsmanship, J. Paul Getty himself greatly admired bronze sculpture. Among the early purchases that pleased him most were statuettes of gods and heroes. When he passed away in 1976, he was negotiating for the purchase of the rare life-size image of a victorious athlete that has come to be known as the Getty Bronze.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/introduction/</guid>
      <description>Building on a distinguished tradition, the 19th International Congress on Ancient Bronzes convened in Los Angeles between October 13 and 17, 2015. Organized by the J. Paul Getty Museum in conjunction with the Getty Conservation Institute, this meeting of more than 150 attendees was held at the Getty Center in Brentwood and the Getty Villa in Malibu. Over 5 days, 116 presenters from 24 countries participated in 11 sessions, delivering 49 papers, 3 keynote addresses, and 1 public lecture, as well as 19 posters discussing diverse aspects of ancient bronze production and its modern reception.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Large-Scale Bronzes</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Bronze Athlete from Ephesos</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/1-plattner-gschwantler-vak/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/1-plattner-gschwantler-vak/</guid>
      <description>1. Archaeological Background and History of the Bronze’s Classification Among the few preserved bronze statues from antiquity, the Athlete from Ephesos is an outstanding case in several respects (fig. 1.1): (1) discovered in the late nineteenth century (1896), it comes from a clear context within its ancient surrounding; (2) to this day it ranks among the most complex conservation projects ever undertaken, requiring the reassembly of more than 200 fragments; (3) with the discovery of a “twin” statue in the sea near the coast of Croatia exactly 100 years later, it has recently become part of an intriguing case study and an issue for archaeology and art history.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Was the Colossus of Rhodes Cast in Courses or in Large Sections?</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/2-vedder/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/2-vedder/</guid>
      <description>In the argument over where the monumental statue known as the Colossus of Rhodes was located, its casting has hitherto seldom been considered. The statue—made of cast bronze with a height of 70 cubits (30–35 meters, or 98–114 feet)—must have left at least some remnants of its production. Furthermore, these remnants must be discoverable in the city of Rhodes. However, a requirement for recognizing these remnants is knowledge of the casting technique that was used.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bronzes from the Aegean Sea</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/3-koutsouflakis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/3-koutsouflakis/</guid>
      <description>“Thank God for Vesuvius; thank God for shipwrecks.” Bondo Wyszpolski’s comment1 on the exhibition Power and Pathos: Bronze Sculpture of the Hellenistic World at the Getty Museum accurately sums up an art-historical reality: bronze artwork of antiquity rarely survived the vicissitudes of history, except by mere chance. The contribution of Pompeii together with a handful of other sites is well known and recognized; the Villa dei Papiri at Herculaneum, for example, with its exquisite bronze portraiture “catapulted the study of bronzes from antiquarian pastime to art-historical discipline,”2 presenting an excellent archaeological context in which the Hellenistic art of portraiture could be well appreciated and understood.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Royal Macedonian Portrait Head from the Sea off Kalymnos</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/4-palagia/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/4-palagia/</guid>
      <description>The fine bronze portrait head of a man wearing a kausia (figs. 4.1–3) which was on display in the exhibitions Power and Pathos in Florence, Los Angeles, and Washington, D.C., and Pergamon and the Hellenistic Kingdoms of the Ancient World at the Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York, is one of four over-life-size bronze statues of the Hellenistic period that were recovered from the sea near Kalymnos.1 Another colossal bronze is a female portrait statue of very fine quality, dating from the late third century BC.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Bronze Head of Arsinoë III in Mantua and the Typology of Ptolemaic Divinization of the Archelaos Relief</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/5-butz/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/5-butz/</guid>
      <description>Ὑπὲρ Πτολεμαίου ἐμοῦ τοῦ Ἐπιφανεστάτου
  Figure 5.1. Northwest corner of the Courtyard of Honor, Palazzo Te, Mantua, looking up at the gallery windows of the Acerbi Collection. Architect Giulio Romano (1524–1534). Photo: author  The bronze head of Arsinoë III is one of the most important pieces in the Giuseppe Acerbi Collection of the Museo Civico di Palazzo Te in Mantua, a collection assembled when Acerbi was the Austrian consul general in Alexandria between 1826 and 1834 and later given to his hometown of Mantua (fig.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Apollo from Salerno</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/6-pacifico/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/6-pacifico/</guid>
      <description>The bronze head of Apollo found in the waters of the Gulf of Salerno in 1930 still offers an opportunity to discuss the date, casting and production, place of manufacture, and function of the work of art in antiquity.
Laboratory analysis shows that the bronze has percentages of copper (81%), lead (11%), and tin (5.5%) that can be associated with alloys found in the Roman Imperial period.1 The presence of copper was higher in the oldest bronzes (84–92%).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tiberius from Herculaneum</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/7-risser/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/7-risser/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Building on a collaboration to conserve the bronze Apollo from Pompeii,1 the J. Paul Getty Museum partnered with the Museo Archeologico Nazionale di Napoli between 2012 and 2013 to return the larger-than-life-size portrait of Emperor Tiberius (42 BC‒AD 37) from Herculaneum for display (fig. 7.1).2 The statue, which measured 2.4 meters (8 feet) in height, had been off view for some twenty years, owing to weaknesses in the legs and base.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When a Statue is Not a Statue</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/8-mattusch/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/8-mattusch/</guid>
      <description>The Piombino Apollo has recently undergone new studies of its production, measurements, alloy, and associated inscriptions (fig. 8.1, left). That statue and the similar Apollo from Pompeii (fig. 8.1, right) were installed side-by-side for the first time in the exhibition Power and Pathos, which made it possible to compare and contrast the two figures and to raise new questions about their similarities and differences.The Piombino Apollo was discovered underwater and sold at Livorno in 1832; in 1834 it was acquired by the Louvre.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Second-Century Large Bronze Workshop at Gerasa (Jerash, Jordan)</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/abstract-khalil-seigne-weber/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/abstract-khalil-seigne-weber/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Apoxyomenos</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/abstract-mesic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/abstract-mesic/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Bronze Statue of Germanicus from Ameria (Amelia)</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/abstract-pollini/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/abstract-pollini/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Doryphoros in Bronze</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/abstract-schneider/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/abstract-schneider/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Influence of Ancient Bronzes in Cuban Large-Scale Sculptures</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/abstract-toledo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/abstract-toledo/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Artist</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-artist/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-artist/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More Than Holes!</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-artist/9-adornato/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-artist/9-adornato/</guid>
      <description>1. Defining the Severe-style Period The artistic revolution in Greek sculpture is generally associated with one fundamental historical event, the Persian Wars; with two of the most important sculptors of the late sixth–early fifth century BC, Kritios and Nesiotes; and with a sculptural group: the Tyrannicides. The chronological span between the end of the Persian Wars—marked by the destruction of the monuments on the Athenian Acropolis (480/79 BC)—and the beginning of the construction of the Parthenon (448/7 BC) is commonly labelled as the “Severe style period” in archaeological literature.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Polykleitos at Work</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-artist/10-haga-et-al/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-artist/10-haga-et-al/</guid>
      <description>Introduction For more than a century, arguments have been made both for and against the identification of the Doryphoros with the “Canon” of Polykleitos without a definitive conclusion being reached. Although the most important information is Pliny’s famous phrase, it also is the cause of controversy. He writes: “Polyclitus &amp;hellip; et doryphorum viriliter puerum fecit. quem canona artifices vocant, liniamenta artis ex eo petentes veluti a lege quadam &amp;hellip;” [“Polykleitos made &amp;hellip; and a Doryphoros, a virile-looking boy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Looking at the Bronze of Lost Sculptures</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-artist/11-falaschi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-artist/11-falaschi/</guid>
      <description>At the beginning of his writing On the Pythian Responses (De Pythiae oraculis), Plutarch dedicates several chapters (395b–396c) to the blue patina that characterized bronze Delphian votive offerings. Several studies have tried to give a scientific explanation for this patina and to identify it in artworks brought to light during excavations.1 This contribution focuses on a different aspect, strictly linked to the reception and perception of art in the Imperial age.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mobility and Migration</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-artist/12-horne/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-artist/12-horne/</guid>
      <description>Our understanding of the ancient sculptor’s profession, like so much of ancient sculpture itself, is fragmentary. The particulars of ephemeral facets such as training and organization come primarily from literary sources, supplemented by meager evidence found at sites of bronze and marble sculpture production. As a result, the clearest picture forms around the major figures of antiquity such as Praxiteles and Pheidias, who, according to ancient accounts, were sought out to complete major works across the Aegean.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Praxiteles’ Bronze Sculpture at Delphi</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-artist/abstract-ajootian/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-artist/abstract-ajootian/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statuettes</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/statuettes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/statuettes/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Assertions by the Portable</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/statuettes/13-barr-sharrar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/statuettes/13-barr-sharrar/</guid>
      <description>Discussing Polykleitos’s Doryphoros in his landmark Masterpieces of Greek Sculpture (1895), Adolf Furtwängler included a few bronze statuettes pertinent to his subject. The largest and most important known to him was a statuette from Fins d’Annecy now in the Musée du Petit Palais in Paris (fig. 13.1).1 Suggestive of Roman marble copies of the Doryphoros with the movement of the arms reversed, Furtwängler said it had previously been identified by Adolf Michaelis and other late nineteenth-century scholars as a copy of the Hermes by Polykleitos mentioned by Pliny as “once in Lysimachea” (Naturalis historia 34.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Use of Inlays in Early Greek Bronzes</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/statuettes/14-hemingway-abramitis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/statuettes/14-hemingway-abramitis/</guid>
      <description>Ancient Greek bronze-smiths used a variety of techniques to enhance the appearance of their creations. Due to their often fragmentary state of preservation, the modern observer tends to think of early Greek bronzes as monochromatic, but it is clear that the practice of inlaying other materials into bronze started early in ancient Greece. This paper looks at the evidence for the Geometric (ca. 900–700 BC) and Archaic (ca. 700–480 BC) periods from many different regions, with particular reference to artworks in the collection of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, where a variety of nondestructive scientific analyses were conducted in the Museum’s conservation and scientific laboratories.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Poet as Artisan</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/statuettes/15-mcgowan/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/statuettes/15-mcgowan/</guid>
      <description>Figure 15.1   Figure 15.2   Figure 15.3   Bronze statuette of an artisan. New York, Metropolitan Museum of Art inv. 1972.11.1. Rogers Fund, 1972. Photo: OASC © The Metropolitan Museum of Art  Many of the papers in this volume deal with the technical aspects of bronze manufacture and analysis of fabric and technique. But what of the artisans themselves? A large, relatively well-preserved Hellenistic bronze statuette in the Metropolitan Museum of Art, said to have been found off the coast of North Africa, appears to be an image of an artisan (fig.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Paramythia Bronzes</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/statuettes/16-sharpe/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/statuettes/16-sharpe/</guid>
      <description>Introduction This paper will focus on a hoard of bronze statuettes found near Paramythia (Epirus) at the end of the eighteenth century (fig. 16.1–14).1 It is appropriate to review these bronzes in light of recent scholarship on Roman Greece and current discussions regarding aspects of Roman identity.2 A reappraisal of the Paramythia material can contribute to recent deliberations concerning how material culture, in particular personal items, might reflect and reinforce the patron’s social and cultural identity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roman Bronze Figurines of Deities in the National Archaeological Museum of the Marche (Ancona)</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/statuettes/17-frapiccini/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/statuettes/17-frapiccini/</guid>
      <description>The collection of Roman bronze statuettes in the National Archaeological Museum of the Marche at Ancona includes numerous representations of deities. The majority of these statuettes are probably from domestic lararia in the territory, which in ancient times belonged to the regiones of Umbria and Piceno. This paper analyzes some of the most interesting statuettes including the bronze figurines from Sentinum, where a foundry is known to have existed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Function and Use of Roman Medium-Sized Statuettes in the Northwestern Provinces</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/statuettes/18-kaufmann/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/statuettes/18-kaufmann/</guid>
      <description>When we think of figural bronzes from the northwestern provinces of the Roman world, a considerable number of small statuettes and some impressive fragments of life-size statues come to mind. Medium-sized statuettes, between approximately 40 and 100 cm (16 to 39 in.) high, however, are less well documented, as they seem to have had less chance of surviving either intact, as did small bronzes, or as fragments, as did large statues.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Through Celts and Romans</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/statuettes/19-grossi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/statuettes/19-grossi/</guid>
      <description>Introduction The symbology characterizing the Roman world, as much as its artistic production, often manifests a beautiful syncretism: there are many cases in which a theme, a figure, or a meaning is re-arranged and presented in a different way, and it is often possible to see that their roots are planted far away. From this point of view the Celts were very important, because their myths, rites, and interpretations influenced Roman ones over a long span of time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Representations of Zeus/Jupiter in the Small-Scale Bronze</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/statuettes/20-veseli/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/statuettes/20-veseli/</guid>
      <description>Zeus/Jupiter was one of the most venerated gods in ancient Albania, a country situated on one of the crossroads of the Mediterranean. The area was heavily influenced culturally by the Graeco-Roman world. The eclectic religious life of this Graeco-Roman civilization ensured that the indigenous Illyrian pantheon was very similar to the Greek, and that most of the Olympian gods were venerated, as were Roman deities in a later era. Zeus/Jupiter, one of the most important gods, is represented in the small-scale bronze sculpture found in Albania, and in particular by the four examples discussed here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roman-Age Casting Techniques of Small Bronzes from Marche</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/statuettes/abstract-fazzini/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/statuettes/abstract-fazzini/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Figural Bronze Statuettes in the Ashmolean Collection and the Aesthetics of Replication</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/statuettes/abstract-west/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/statuettes/abstract-west/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Hellenistic East</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-hellenistic-east/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-hellenistic-east/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Influence of East and West on Bronze Objects Found in Central Anatolia</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-hellenistic-east/21-paterakis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-hellenistic-east/21-paterakis/</guid>
      <description>Introduction This paper reviews the influences from the East and West on bronzes (copper-tin alloys) found in Anatolia while focusing on the archaeological finds from the site of Kaman-Kalehöyük. Given its location along ancient trade routes, Kaman-Kalehöyük may have served as a conduit for the intraregional exchange of materials and manufacturing technologies. We examine some of these influences and movements as they relate to ancient bronze technology in Anatolia.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Portrait of a Hellenistic Ruler in the National Museum of Iran</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-hellenistic-east/22-lindstroem/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-hellenistic-east/22-lindstroem/</guid>
      <description>Discovery in 1935 in Ancient Elymais The portrait head of a Hellenistic ruler (fig. 22.1) was discovered more than eighty years ago in Kal-e Chendar in the valley of Shami, north of Izeh in present-day Khuzistan (ancient Elymais). It is often stated that Sir Aurel Stein (1862–1943), the famous Hungaro-British explorer, excavated the portrait. In fact, it was found accidently in the course of construction work, shortly before Stein arrived at the site.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Influence of Bronze Working on Roman Provincial Stone Sculpture</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-hellenistic-east/23-albertson/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-hellenistic-east/23-albertson/</guid>
      <description>The prosperity experienced by the elite of the ancient Romano-Syrian city of Palmyra from the late first century BC through the middle of the third century AD is perhaps most visible in their monumental family tombs and the funerary sculpture associated within these tombs. Among the types included within the well-known repertoire of Palmyran funerary reliefs are the distinctive loculus plaques: rectangular limestone slabs covering the burial cavity, carved in high-relief with a bust depicting the individual interred and often accompanied by an Aramaic inscription denoting the occupant’s name, family lineage, and sometimes even the date of death.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Transformation of Bronze Sculpture in the Hellenistic East and the Iranian World</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-hellenistic-east/abstract-canepa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-hellenistic-east/abstract-canepa/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Hellenistic Heritage of Termez</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-hellenistic-east/abstract-mirzaev/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-hellenistic-east/abstract-mirzaev/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vessels</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/vessels/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/vessels/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bronze Vessels from the Acropolis and the Definition of the Athenian Production in Archaic and Early Classical Period</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/vessels/24-tarditi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/vessels/24-tarditi/</guid>
      <description>In the study of Greek bronze vessels of the Archaic period, important comparisons are always offered by the fragments found during the excavations carried out on the Athenian Acropolis. Until now, these fragments were known mainly from some incomplete publications of the late nineteenth or early twentieth century.1 To fill this gap, we studied the bronze vessel fragments found on the Acropolis more systematically and completely. The results of this research2 make it possible to draw some conclusions about the extent and features of the Athenian bronze vessel production during the Archaic and Classical periods.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bronze Vessels and Related *Instrumenta* at Delphi</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/vessels/25-meirano/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/vessels/25-meirano/</guid>
      <description>The circumstances under which the École Française d’Athènes conducted the chief excavation of the sanctuary of Delphi are well known: the so-called Grande Fouille (Great Excavation) represents a foundational page in the history of archaeological excavations in Greece during the nineteenth century. Between 1892 and 1903, French archaeologists brought to light the major part of the site (fig. 25.1, unveiling the ruins of the celebrated monuments described in the literary texts and contributing to the understanding of one of the most famous sanctuaries of the ancient world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Toward the Derveni Krater</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/vessels/26-gaunt/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/vessels/26-gaunt/</guid>
      <description>Figure 26.1. Bronze volute-krater from Vix (Burgundy, France). Greek, Laconian, ca. 570 BC. Chatîllon sur Seine, Musée du Pays Chatîllonais, inv. nnn. Photo: TK   Figure 26.2. Volute-krater from Derveni. Bronze with silver and copper. Greek, early fourth century BC. Thessaloniki, Archaeological Museum, inv. B1. Photo: TK   A simple observation provides the point of departure for this paper. The decorative schemes of two Greek bronze volute kraters—the Archaic one found at Vix in Burgundy (fig.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Iconography of the Sea World on Late Hellenistic Bronze Vessels</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/vessels/27-dedecker/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/vessels/27-dedecker/</guid>
      <description>The Mediterranean Sea has always captured the imagination of the Greeks, but at the end of the Hellenistic era, their artistic vision and technical knowledge were transferred to the Italian peninsula, where Roman craftsmen created artifacts that surpassed everything before. These craftsmen portrayed deities such as Poseidon, Amphitrite, Triton, Scylla, and Medusa, who lived in the sea, riding creatures like sea horses (hippocampi), sea wolves (ketos), dolphins, and other real and imaginary marine animals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Anthropomorphic Vessel in the National Museum of Beirut</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/vessels/28-fani/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/vessels/28-fani/</guid>
      <description>A bronze anthropomorphic vessel came onto the art market in Damascus in 1953. It was acquired by the late Émir Maurice Chéhab, then director-general of antiquities in Lebanon, who actively sought artifacts that had been excavated in his country and subsequently smuggled into Syria for sale. The vessel (inv. 25422) currently is on display at the National Museum of Beirut.
The Beirut vessel has been discussed in the writings of Frances F.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hellenistic, Roman and Byzantine Influence in the Consolidation of Fatimid Metalware</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/vessels/29-lester/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/vessels/29-lester/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Until recently, the availability of Early Islamic metal vessels was limited to individual pieces in museums and private collections, and the scholarship were always generalized, with very limited information in regard to typology.1 Metal articles from the early centuries of Islam within the Syrian-Egyptian region are even less common, as Iran and Central Asia attracted the greater portion of attention from researchers.2
The Fatimid dynasty3 is famous for its decorative arts, which have stimulated considerable scholarly interest, and several publications have been dedicated to the subject.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Artifacts</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/artifacts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/artifacts/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Minoan Status Symbols</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/artifacts/30-ferrence-giumlia-mair/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/artifacts/30-ferrence-giumlia-mair/</guid>
      <description>Introduction For our project on Minoan metallurgy, many objects of various sizes, belonging to several classes, and made of different metals were analyzed by X-ray fluorescence (XRF). The items come from different sites in eastern Crete, one of which is the Minoan town of Gournia, which was excavated in the early twentieth century.1 With the support of the University of Pennsylvania Museum of Archaeology and Anthropology (hereafter, Penn Museum) in Philadelphia and private donors, Harriet Boyd Hawes and her collaborators, Richard Seager and Edith Hall, excavated the settlement of Gournia in three campaigns in 1901, 1903, and 1904 and published the discoveries in 1908.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bronze Trees from the Greek to the Roman World</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/artifacts/31-castoldi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/artifacts/31-castoldi/</guid>
      <description>It is well known that trees, gardens, and landscapes are not commonly represented in Greek art until the Hellenistic period. In vase painting, the focus is on men, gods, and heroes; war, hunting, labor, rituals, weddings, death, and festivals offer the opportunity to represent humans, who are at the center of philosophy and art in ancient Greece. Nature and landscapes, by contrast, rarely appear in vase painting; floral patterns, tendrils, and leaves only appear as subsidiary decoration.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bronze Medical and Writing Cases in Classical and Hellenistic Macedonia</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/artifacts/32-ignatiadou/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/artifacts/32-ignatiadou/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Parexodos is the name ascribed in the Hippocratic Corpus to the portable medical case that a doctor must own, to facilitate work outside his premises. In it, he could store prepared medicaments and also his tools: “ἔστω δέ σοι ἑτέρη παρέξοδος ἡ λιτοτέρη πρὸς τὰς ἀποδημίας ἡ διὰ χειρῶν &amp;hellip; [Be sure to possess another portable case, simpler and hand-held for travels &amp;hellip;]” (De decente habitu 8.10–11).1
We are familiar with the medical cases of the Roman period, which are rectangular boxes with sliding lids and rectangular compartments,2 but our knowledge of the medical cases of the Classical and Hellenistic periods remains limited.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Group of Items from the Campana Collection as an Example of Nineteenth-Century Restoration</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/artifacts/33-gulyaeva/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/artifacts/33-gulyaeva/</guid>
      <description>The major part of Marquis Giovanni Pietro Campana’s famous collection came into the Department of Classical Antiquities at the Hermitage Museum in 1861. Among the items were three “shields.” There were no detailed descriptions of them, but they were included in a short list of the objects in a special catalogue.1
Two of the three were similar: round basins with wide flat rims. The first one was described in Campana’s catalogue as “Scudo rotondo con figura di Arpia in mezzo di bello stile”;2 the second one was described as “Scudo rotondo con chimera a basso rilievo nel mezzo.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roman Silhouette Figures</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/artifacts/34-franken/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/artifacts/34-franken/</guid>
      <description>The question of original function is of great importance in our attempts to understand any archaeological object. For many ancient bronzes, this question is not easy to answer. Technical features, context of the discovery, or figural parallels can often provide valuable information. First of all, however, one must search for comparable bronzes. Only when one expands one’s view from the individual object to all similar artifacts does it become possible to better understand and assess their shared characteristics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Balancing Artifacts</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/artifacts/abstract-de-angelis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/artifacts/abstract-de-angelis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Figures on Fire</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/artifacts/abstract-bielfeldt/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/artifacts/abstract-bielfeldt/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Standspiegel, Figured Appliqués, and Other Bronze Items at Locri Epizefiri (Magna Graecia)</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/artifacts/abstract-elia-meriano/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/artifacts/abstract-elia-meriano/</guid>
      <description> Bibliography  Cameron 1979 Cameron, F. 1979. Greek Bronze Hand-Mirrors in South Italy. Oxford: British Archaeological Reports. Elia 2010 Elia, D. 2010. Locri Epizefiri 6. Alessandria: Edizioni dell’Orso. Meirano 2002 Meirano, V. 2002. “Utensil Stands da Locri Epizefiri.” In I bronzi antichi: produzione e tecnologia: Atti XV Congresso Internazionale sui Bronzi Antichi, ed. A. Giumlia-Mair, 117–26. Montagnac: Editions Monique Mergoil.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Multidisciplinary Study of Hellenistic and Roman Bronze Mirrors from the Archaeological Collection of Ancient Messene, Greece</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/artifacts/abstract-giannoulaki/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/artifacts/abstract-giannoulaki/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Gréau Mirror and the Phenomenon of Fakes in Nineteenth-Century Paris</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/artifacts/abstract-lee/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/artifacts/abstract-lee/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Ancient Chariot from Serbia</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/artifacts/abstract-milanovic-ratkovic-petelin-colovic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/artifacts/abstract-milanovic-ratkovic-petelin-colovic/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bronze Warfare from the Hellenistic Period</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/artifacts/abstract-tisseyre/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/artifacts/abstract-tisseyre/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conservation and Analysis</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sustainable Conservation of Bronze Artworks</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/35-casaletto/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/35-casaletto/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Conservation Science is a field that has been in continuous evolution since the late twentieth century. The study of ancient bronzes has long focused on archaeometry, addressing technological aspects and production concerns. Casting cores, alloys, joins, surface patinas, and corrosion products have been intensively investigated by various analytical techniques in order to improve our knowledge of the original materials, processes, manufacturing techniques, and degradation phenomena. Scientific results provided very useful information to archaeologists, art historians, and conservators about the artistry, craftsmanship, production, conservation, and restoration of ancient bronze artifacts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Investigating Ancient “Bronzes”</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/36-tykot/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/36-tykot/</guid>
      <description>X-Ray Fluorescence X-ray fluorescence (XRF) is one of many analytical methods used to determine the composition of copper-based metal objects. When used nondestructively, however, care must be taken to understand the principles of this method and thus the significance of the results. XRF analysis involves primary X-rays striking the sample and creating electron vacancies in an inner shell of the atoms; these vacancies are then filled by lower-energy electrons from an outer shell, while producing secondary X-rays.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Scientific Assessment of the Long-Term Protection of Incralac® Coatings on Ancient Bronze Collections in the National Archaeological Museum and the Epigraphic and Numismatic Museum, in Athens, Greece</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/37-boyatzis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/37-boyatzis/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Among the main criteria for selecting a coating for cultural heritage metal artifacts are (1) long-term insulation of their surfaces from contaminants due to environmental pollutants and handling; (2) the filtration of light through absorption of radiation; (3) considerable adhesion to the metal surface and elasticity; and finally (4) chemical stability. Ease of application and reversibility are also among the highly sought requirements.
Incralac® was introduced by INCRA (International Copper Research Association) in 1964 as a metal protective coating based on the acrylic resin Paraloid® B44 (an ethylacrylate –methylmethacrylate copolymer) with benzotriazole (BTA) as a main additive.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Approaches in Stabilizing Chloride-Contaminated Ancient Bronzes Using Corrosion Inhibitors and/or Electrochemical Methods to Preserve Information in the Patinas</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/38-argyropoulos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/38-argyropoulos/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Ancient bronzes often contain surface decoration in the corrosion layers or show evidence of tinning, niello, gilding, paint, or organic materials in the corrosion layers. Depending on the quantity of chlorides in their surfaces, traditional conservation methods to stabilize bronze disease are either (1) locally to treat the artifact with Ag2O particles or zinc dust; followed by complete immersion in sodium sesquicarbonate (pH 10) solutions with or without electrolysis to convert cupreous chloride to more stable corrosion product(s);1 and/or (2) the use of corrosion inhibitors, such as benzotriazole.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conservation Treatments and Archaeometallurgical Insights on the Medici Riccardi Horse Head</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/39-salvioli/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/39-salvioli/</guid>
      <description>History of the Artifact The equine bronze protome known as the Medici Riccardi horse head in the Museo Archeologico Nazionale of Florence is likely a surviving part of a Hellenistic life-size equestrian sculptural group, which has been dated around the second half of the fourth century BC.1 The sculpture entered the antiquarian collections of the Medici in the fifteenth century and was cited for the first time in 1495 as part of Lorenzo il Magnifico’s antiquarian collection,2 although it had certainly been found well before that.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Cleveland *Apollo*</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/40-northover/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/40-northover/</guid>
      <description>Introduction and Pre-accession Investigation The only life-size bronze version of the sculptural type traditionally known as Apollo Sauroktonos (Apollo the Lizard-Slayer), now re-named Apollo the Python-Slayer and attributed to Praxiteles, is part of the permanent collection of the Cleveland Museum of Art (inv. 2004.30; fig. 40.1a–d).1 There are approximately twenty other known sculptures of this type that exist, all in marble with one reduced-scale bronze copy.2
 Figure 40.1a. Apollo the Python-Slayer, ca.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Getty Herm of Dionysos</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/41-maish/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/41-maish/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Ancient Athenians are reported to have been the first to erect herms that served as boundary markers in both urban and rural settings and also stood in the entrances of private homes and temples; at one location herms became so numerous that one structure near the Agora was named the Stoa of the Herms. This proliferation and high demand perhaps led to the development of copying and serial reproduction methods, and the Getty Herm of Dionysos (J.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Technological Re-Examination of the Piombino Apollo</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/42-mille-descamps/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/42-mille-descamps/</guid>
      <description>Epigraphic and Stylistic Re-evaluation of the Piombino Apollo  Figure 42.1. Piombino Apollo, 120–100 BC. H. 115.5 cm. Paris, Musée du Louvre, Département des Antiquités grecques, étrusques et romaines, inv. Br2. Photo: © C2RMF, Anne Maigret  The Piombino Apollo (fig. 42.1) was among the statues gathered for the exhibition Power and Pathos: Bronze Sculpture of the Hellenistic World at the J. Paul Getty Museum and the accompanying symposium.1 It is an Archaizing work, as was already suggested by Jean Letronne in 1834, just two years after the bronze was discovered in the sea off the west coast of Piombino, Italy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Results on the Alloys of the Croatian Apoxyomenos</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/43-vidovic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/43-vidovic/</guid>
      <description>Introduction The statue of an Apoxyomenos (fig. 43.1), raised from the Adriatic Sea off Croatia in 1999, has been thoroughly restored and investigated at the Croatian Conservation Institute (HRZ). It has been exhibited in Zagreb, Osijek, Rijeka, Split, and Zadar in Croatia, as well as in Florence, Ljubljana, Paris, London, and Los Angeles. Results of conservation-restoration works and investigations have been published and presented at several conferences, including international congresses on ancient bronzes in Bucharest (2003) and Zurich (2013).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Bronze Sculpture of Alexander the Great on Horseback</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/44-siano/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/44-siano/</guid>
      <description>The equestrian bronze group of Alexander on horseback in the National Archaeological Museum of Naples (inv. 4996), which is dated around the first century BC, was found in Herculaneum during the Bourbon excavation campaigns of the second half of the eighteenth century (fig. 44.1a–b). According to the sources, the statuette, whose restored height is 49 centimeters, was mostly excavated on October 22, 1761, within a tunnel at the Theater under the Casa dei Colli Mozzi.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Auloi from Meroë</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/45-gansicke/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/45-gansicke/</guid>
      <description>Discovery and Introduction In 1921, Harvard Egyptologist George A. Reisner excavated Pyramid N 6 (also called Beg. N. 6), the burial of Queen Amanishakheto, in Meroë, Sudan.1 This pyramid had been discovered in the early nineteenth century by the Italian physician and explorer Giuseppe Ferlini. While investigating the pyramid, much of which was destroyed during the process, Ferlini came upon a rich trove of gold jewelry.2
A few objects however remained in the tomb, to be discovered only when excavations were undertaken in the stairway leading to the underground burial chamber.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Defined Protocol for *In-situ* Micro-XRF Compositional Analysis of Bronze Figurines from the National Museum of Damascus, Syria</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/46-kantarelou/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/46-kantarelou/</guid>
      <description>Introduction During the PROMET European FP6 project, a micro-XRF mobile spectrometer was transported to the National Museum of Damascus, Syria, where it was applied to and validated for the quantitative noninvasive analysis of unique museum metal collections across the Mediterranean region, successfully addressing archaeological and conservation questions. Given the value of these collections, transport of objects or sampling for analysis is generally not permitted. Thus, the development and validation of a reliable portable technology is critical for comparisons of analytical compositional results, especially for similar museum collections or objects housed around the world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is There an Ultimate Authority in Authenticity?</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/47-anderson-eremin-lie-bewer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/47-anderson-eremin-lie-bewer/</guid>
      <description>On display in the Harvard Art Museums is a statuette of Alexander the Great, sometimes referred to as the Alexander Nelidow after its first known owner.1 The statuette first appeared in the Istanbul bazaar sometime before 1897.2 The original condition of the surface when excavated can only be guessed at: the surface had already been cleaned of any unsightly burial accretions by the time the first images appear.3 Alexander is depicted as a nude youth, standing with his left arm raised, probably to grasp a spear.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Riace Bronze Statues</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/abstract-angelini-et-al/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/abstract-angelini-et-al/</guid>
      <description> Bibliography  Alpine Archaeocopper Project http://geo.geoscienze.unipd.it/aacp/welcome.html Arias 1986 Arias, P. E. 1986. “Analisi critica delle statue [The Critical Analysis of the Statues].” In Gli Eroi venuti dal mare, ed. L. M. Lombardi Satriani, et al. 39–64. Università della Calabria, Studi e Ricerche 19. Gangemi: Università della Calabria. BRETTSCAIFE.net http://brettscaife.net/lead/data/index.html OXALID http://oxalid.arch.ox.ac.uk/  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Balancing Artifacts</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/abstract-azema-mille-descamps-lequime/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/abstract-azema-mille-descamps-lequime/</guid>
      <description>Bibliography  Boube-Piccot 1969 Boube-Piccot, C. 1969. Les bronzes antiques du Maroc. Vol. 1: La statuaire. Etudes et Travaux d’Archeologie Marocaine 4. Rabat: Royaume du Maroc. Hemingway 2015 Hemingway, S. “Statue of Eros Sleeping.” In Power and Pathos: Bronze Sculpture of the Hellenistic World, ed. J. M. Daehner and K. Lapatin, no. 20, 228–29. Los Angeles: J. Paul Getty Museum. Mattusch 1996 Mattusch, C. C. 1996. Classical Bronzes: The Art and Craft of Greek and Roman Statuary.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Copper, War, and Art in Ancient Greece</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/abstract-diaz/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/abstract-diaz/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modern and Ancient Metal Fakes</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/abstract-giumlia-mair/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/abstract-giumlia-mair/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Examination, Conservation, and Analysis of a Composed Egyptian Ibis Statue</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/abstract-mahmoud-matsuda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/abstract-mahmoud-matsuda/</guid>
      <description> Bibliography  Janssens et al. 2000 Janssens, K., et al. 2000. “The Use of Microscopic XRF for Non-destructive Analysis in Art and Archaeometry.” X-Ray Spectrum 29: 73–91.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Technical Examinations on the Parthian Bronze Coffin from Chubtarash Archaeological Site, Khorramabad, Western Iran</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/abstract-oudbashi-hassari-hassanpour/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/abstract-oudbashi-hassari-hassanpour/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Material Interpretation of Ancient Large Bronzes</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/abstract-siano/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/conservation-and-analysis/abstract-siano/</guid>
      <description>Bibliography  Cygielman 2008 Cygielman, M., ed. 2008. La Minerva di Arezzo. Exh. cat. Florence, Soprintendenza per i Beni Archeologici della Toscana. Iozzo 1998 Iozzo M., ed. 1998 “&amp;hellip; qual era tutto rotto”: L’enigma dell’idolino di Pesaro: Indagini per un restauro. Exh. cat. Florence, Museo Archeologico Nazionale. Siano et al. 2012 Siano, S., M. Miccio, M. Giamello, S. Mugnaini, and J. Agresti. 2012. “Journey through the Material Layers of the Chimaera from Arezzo.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/about/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/search.json</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/search.json</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>