<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Vessels on </title>
    <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/vessels/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Vessels on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <atom:link href="https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/vessels/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Bronze Vessels from the Acropolis and the Definition of the Athenian Production in Archaic and Early Classical Period</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/vessels/24-tarditi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/vessels/24-tarditi/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;In the study of Greek bronze vessels of the Archaic period, important comparisons are always offered by the fragments found during the excavations carried out on the Athenian Acropolis. Until now, these fragments were known mainly from some incomplete publications of the late nineteenth or early twentieth century.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; To fill this gap, we studied the bronze vessel fragments found on the Acropolis more systematically and completely. The results of this research&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; make it possible to draw some conclusions about the extent and features of the Athenian bronze vessel production during the Archaic and Classical periods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to a fruitful collaboration with the National Archaeological Museum at Athens, it was possible to examine the previously published pieces and to widen the research to include many other fragments housed in the Museum storerooms. In all, 1,135 pieces were cataloged. Most of them are solid fragments such as handles (852) and feet (144), while just a few are complete or at least partially preserved vessels (3 basins).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the examined pieces were catalogued according to a new typological scheme for each group of objects, highlighting the presence of basic forms and many formal and decorative variations, allowing for more nuanced observations on the style and recurrence of certain elements. For many pieces, formal characteristics made it possible to attribute them to specific shapes: basins (425 fragments), tripod ring bases (100), kraters (3), hydriai (23), &lt;em&gt;kalpides&lt;/em&gt; (31), &lt;em&gt;lebetes&lt;/em&gt; (16), oinochoai (19), paterae (38), plates or lids (17), and situlae (4). For many of the fragments (460 handles in the shape of mobile rings, handle attachments, and feet), the original shape remains undetermined; they could have belonged to any of a variety of vessels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Referring to the full publication (Tarditi 2016) for comments on individual pieces and on the numerous typological variants that were identified, we prefer here to present our conclusions about the pieces attributed to local Athenian workshops, discussing the features, chronology, and diffusion of this production of bronze vessels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bronze-vessels-of-athenian-production&#34;&gt;Bronze Vessels of Athenian Production&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the group of examined fragments from the Athenian acropolis, more than six hundred pieces (631) have been recognized as Athenian products.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; For those with decorative elements, this attribution is based on several formal and stylistic features, while for the great quantity of plain fragments or those with basic and easily reproducible decorative motifs, the attribution to a local Athenian production is justified simply by noting the large number of specimens of a given type attested among the materials of the acropolis, significantly more than in any other Greek context or in areas within the Greek cultural sphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stylistic or formal characteristics recognized as typical of the Athenian bronzes have been recognized on several pieces found in other sites (32 from Athenian demes or Attica; 167 from other areas) or of unknown provenience (40).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In all, including pieces from the acropolis and those found in other areas, today we can attribute to Athenian workshops at least 870 pieces, enough to get a better definition of the chronology and diffusion of this high-level production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;style-shapes-and-decoration&#34;&gt;Style, Shapes, and Decoration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Athenian bronze vessel production seems to have the same mix of high quality and innovation that characterizes all the handicrafts at Athens in Archaic and Early Classical times. Common traits seem to be the high level of workmanship, outstanding originality, and freedom in the re-interpretation of the usual decorative repertoire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basin and the related ring base, usually a tripod, is the most prevalent form, reflecting the importance of this shape in the furniture of Greek sanctuaries and in domestic life, as they were used for many different functions. Peculiar to the Athenian production are some variants in the shape of the handles: extremely numerous are those made from a simple rod, bent at the top to make a triangular form, generally with plain attachments, simply splayed or with a pentagonal section (fig. 24.1).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:6&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This variant is only sporadically attested in other areas, while the many centuries of examples found on the acropolis clearly indicate its local origin.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:7&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Other variants of handles also seem to be typical of Athens: the tracery-worked type (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 24.2&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:8&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; or those shaped like plain rectangular plaques (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 24.3&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:9&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Yet another type shows a characteristic attachment to the basin, with arched side extensions ending with many variants of the flower or “rosette” motif (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 24.4&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:10&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very numerous too are feet in shape of lion’s paws: these are either high and decorated at the top with palmettes (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 24.5&lt;/strong&gt;), or low and decorated with Ionic capitals. Found always alone, they could have been joined to a variety of objects, such as basins, plates, or wooden boxes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A notable feature of the Athenian bronze vessels seems to be the taste for figured decoration, which recurs on many different shapes. Examples include basin handles in shape of animals (lions, snakes, and lizards);&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:11&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; patera handles in the shape of a kouros or lion (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 24.6&lt;/strong&gt;);&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:12&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and oinochoai with a female bust on the upper attachment of the handle.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:13&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of these decorations were also used on bronze vessels made in other regions at this time, but those from Athens have their own stylistic character, which made it possible to attribute pieces found elsewhere to Athenian production. Very interesting, for example, is the frequent use of the lion motif. Well attested on Archaic Laconian vessels, it also had great success at Athens.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:14&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It was used generally on attachments of mobile ring handles and on some handles of paterae&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; Particularly interesting are some basin handles of the &lt;em&gt;podanipter&lt;/em&gt; type in the shape of lions attacking deer or of lions lying opposite a central flower (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 24.7&lt;/strong&gt;);&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:15&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; these are stylistically distinctive and have a wide geographical spread, from southern Italy to southern Russia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A generally accepted opinion&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:16&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; attributes to Athens the production of hydriai with a surmounting vertical handle decorated with a lion’s head on the upper end and a siren on the lower attachment, made from the end of the sixth century or beginning of the fifth down to the fourth century BC. The study of the bronze vessel fragments from the Athenian acropolis was an opportunity to verify this hypothesis, but only one pair of horizontal handles, probably from the same vessel, can be attributed to this kind of hydria, calling into question the attribution to Athens of the entire group. A subset of this hydria group,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:17&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; stylistically very homogeneous, is characterized by the presence of a lion’s head also at the lower attachment of the vertical handle: the significant similarities of this smaller group with some of the lions’ heads attributed to Athenian production&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:18&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; allow us to propose the same artisanal context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Gorgon is another typical motif in figured decorations on Greek Archaic bronze vessels, well attested on Laconian and Corinthian pieces from the late seventh to early sixth century BC.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:19&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; As already noted,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:20&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:20&#34;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; many aspects of the production of bronze vessels in Archaic Athens derive from Laconia and Corinth, often mixing stylistic details from both areas. Such is the case with the Gorgoneion, whose Athenian interpretation presents a mix of Laconian (tusks and one fold in the middle of the forehead) and Corinthian traits (hairstyle with short braids ending with an upturned strand and hexagonal face), creating from the middle of the sixth century pieces that are always elegant and organically composed. Examples thereof are the Gorgoneion on a lion’s paw foot from the Athenian acropolis;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:21&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:21&#34;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; one that appears on the lower attachments of the handles of a &lt;em&gt;kados&lt;/em&gt; in the Steinhardt Collection;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:22&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:22&#34;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; one on the handles of a krater in Munich;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:23&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:23&#34;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and one, slightly later, on a situla-krater from Stavroupolis.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:24&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:24&#34;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The Gorgoneion on an amphora-situla in New York;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:25&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:25&#34;&gt;25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; one on two &lt;em&gt;lebes&lt;/em&gt; attachments; and one on two basin handles from the Athenian acropolis decorated with raised lizards&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:26&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:26&#34;&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; seem more recent, with more humanized faces: they are so similar in style that it is possible they came from the same Attic workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;chronology&#34;&gt;Chronology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fragments of bronze vessels found on the Athenian acropolis and attributed to local workshops are not very useful in defining the chronology of the Athenian bronze vessels production, as we lack of any information about their find contexts. The only thing known is that they were discovered during archaeological excavations carried out on the acropolis plateau from the first half of nineteenth century; the fragments were simply collected and stored, sometimes carelessly, in the Acropolis Museum.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:27&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:27&#34;&gt;27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Stylistic analysis suggests that they are mainly from the Late Archaic or Early Classical period (late sixth and the first half of the fifth century BC); we could not with certainty ascribe any pieces to the late fifth or even the fourth century. As already proposed by André De Ridder,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:28&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:28&#34;&gt;28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; the &lt;em&gt;terminus ante quem&lt;/em&gt; for the bronze vessels from the excavations of the acropolis could be the mid-fifth century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The continuity of the Athenian production through the fifth century is well attested by pieces thought to be Athenian that were found in other areas and in different contexts, including in southern Italian tombs.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:29&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:29&#34;&gt;29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Far less common are finds from stratigraphic contexts: we have just one from Olympia, for which individual finds can be tied to precise excavation data,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:30&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:30&#34;&gt;30&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and a couple of handles from Halae, in Boeotia, of the late sixth–early fifth century.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:31&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:31&#34;&gt;31&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quality and development of the Athenian bronze vessel production has been well defined by the recent work of Beryl Barr-Sharrar. She attributes to Athens the production of the famous Derveni krater (now in the Archaeological Museum of Thessaloniki) and the important series of Type-“A” kraters dating from the beginning of the fifth to the fourth century.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:32&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:32&#34;&gt;32&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The continuity of the Athenian production during the late fifth and fourth centuries is also attested by inventory inscriptions of the Acropolis treasure, made from the second half of the fifth century down to the end of the fourth, which mention many silver and even gold vessels belonging to the goddess.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:33&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:33&#34;&gt;33&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The production of high quality bronze vessels continued into the fourth century and the Hellenistic period, when it reached a particularly high level of artistry within the refined stylistic &lt;em&gt;koinè&lt;/em&gt; common to all the cultural centers of the Mediterranean. While it is very difficult to attribute individual pieces to a defined artistic area, it is nonetheless evident that the “Athenian” stylistic influence was felt on every figured decoration in the broader region, reflecting the circulation of styles, iconography, and probably also highly specialized craftsmen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-diffusion-area&#34;&gt;The Diffusion Area&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Athenian bronze vessels were fairly numerous in some Greek sanctuaries, mainly in the Peloponnese: the greatest quantity comes from Olympia (26 pieces), but they are also well attested in finds from Perachora (17). There were far fewer in Argos (5) and Isthmia (4), which is surprising given their location on the road linking the Peloponnese to Attica (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 24.8&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:34&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:34&#34;&gt;34&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Athenian bronze vessels have a relatively small spread in mainland Greece, with the exception of the sanctuary of Dodona (8 pieces). Given the close relation between Athens and Delphi in the Archaic period, the lack of finds from this sanctuary is quite unexpected. However, the study of the bronze vessels fragments is still ongoing and it is possible that some change will occur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the northern Greece, the most interesting locations in the Archaic period are those in the northern Balkans, as attested by finds from some centers in Macedonia,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:35&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:35&#34;&gt;35&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; the northern Aegean,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:36&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:36&#34;&gt;36&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and the interior of the Balkans.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:37&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:37&#34;&gt;37&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In the Peloponnese, Athenian bronze vessels are found only in sanctuaries and are connected with the attendance there of Athenians pilgrims, who were offering choice products from their city. In the northern regions, by contrast, the vessels are found only in burial contexts affiliated with land and sea routes followed by Greek goods, which were distributed and redistributed within trade networks since the sixth century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The objects found in Macedonia and in the northern Aegean are more recent than those from the sites in the inner Balkans, dating from the beginning of the fifth century. This later chronology seems to revive the hypothesis that already in Archaic times goods were traveling by sea up to Chalkidiki, from whence they were transported overland on long routes to the interior regions,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:38&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:38&#34;&gt;38&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; anticipating the future Via Egnatia. Judging from the chronology of the materials, it seems likely that during the Archaic period there was an established trade route by sea from the Peloponnese to Euboea, from there continuing by land: the route toward Chalkidiki must have developed only from the end of the sixth century. The Athenian commercial presence in the area became more intense after the conquest of Lemnos in 510 BC, establishing an outpost for further development of trade to the Black Sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Particularly interesting is the presence of a small but significant number of pieces attributable to Athenian production found in several towns along the coast of the Black Sea or just inland: there are two basins with handles in the shape of rectangular plaques—one from Solokha&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:39&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:39&#34;&gt;39&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and one from Semibratnye&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:40&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:40&#34;&gt;40&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;—and at least two amphorae from Peschanoe,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:41&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:41&#34;&gt;41&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; but probably also other vases, such as three &lt;em&gt;kalpides&lt;/em&gt; and a basin on a tripod base.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:42&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:42&#34;&gt;42&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The presence of these objects is certainly related to Athenian interests around the Black Sea, the city’s main source of grain. The conquest of Thracian Chersonese in the mid-sixth century contributed significantly to the development of Athenian trade in this region and to the spread of valuable materials, which were used as articles of exchange particularly among the rich elites of the indigenous communities.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:43&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:43&#34;&gt;43&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The objects found in these regions appear to be contemporary with the Athenian pieces from Macedonian sites and Lemnos: it is likely that their distribution is linked to the presence of the same maritime trade-routes—running from Attica to the northern Aegean and from there up to the Black Sea—which ensured the circulation of high-quality products from Athenian workshops in those countries politically related to or dependent upon Athens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking west, a significant presence of Athenian vessels is confirmed along the Adriatic coast, especially in the Apulian area, with more than twenty pieces. It seems evident that the distribution of Attic vessels (both bronze and ceramic) mainly follows the Adriatic route. In exchange for grain and other foodstuffs, Greek merchants traded their famous figured pottery and valuable bronze banquet furnishings, which were appreciated by the indigenous elites as a symbols of their full adherence to the model of the Greek-type symposium. The only difference between the two classes of materials is that bronze vessels stop at the Piceno, while the pottery travels on to the emporia at the mouth of the Po. Beyond the Marche region, further to the north, there are no finds of Greek bronze vessels, either from Attica or from other centers; they were probably “filtered out” by the Etruscans to protect their own well-established bronze vessel production.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:44&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:44&#34;&gt;44&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trade route from the Ionian Gulf to the interior of Basilicata is well attested. Athenian articles have been found at Metaponto and at indigenous settlements such as Botromagno, Braida di Vaglio, and Miglionico.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:45&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:45&#34;&gt;45&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Greek traders in Metaponto appreciated and distributed not only Attic figured pottery but also some fine examples of bronze vessels, not just Attic: from Metaponto, these pieces were distributed up the Bradano River.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fewer examples are found along the Tyrrhenian coast of southern Italy and Sicily, from which we have just a few pieces of relatively modest quality: some paterae with handles in shape of kouroi; a handful of precious pieces, such as the krater from Agrigento&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:46&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:46&#34;&gt;46&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and from Locri;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:47&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:47&#34;&gt;47&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;podanipter&lt;/em&gt; handle in the shape of lions attacking an animal, a fragment of which was found in Locri.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:48&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:48&#34;&gt;48&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; We may suppose that, here too, the Etruscans exercised a “monopoly” on fine bronze production, especially from the end of the sixth century. At that time, the spread of Laconian and Corinthian bronze vessels was interrupted&amp;ndash; after they had been well attested during the middle decades of the sixth century&amp;ndash;and Athenian production began to diminish. The distribution of Athenians pieces in southern Italy seems to stop altogether in the second half of the fifth century, probably reflecting a change in trade routes. However, exports of Athenian bronze vessels continued to reach the northern Aegean and Black Sea area, following in the wake of Athenian military and colonial activity and the onset of business relationships that could also ensure vital supplies of grain to Athens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bibliography&#34;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Barone 2007&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Barone, L. 2007. “Un tesoro riemerso dal Dnepr.” In &lt;em&gt;Ori dei cavalieri delle steppe:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Collezioni dai musei dell’Ucraina&lt;/em&gt;, ed. G. L. Bonora and F. Marzatico, 278–81. Exh. cat. Trento, Castello del Buonconsiglio, Monumenti e collezione provincials. Milan: Silvano.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Barr-Sharrar 2008&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Barr-Sharrar, B. 2008. &lt;em&gt;The Derveni Krater:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Masterpiece of Classical Greek Metalwork&lt;/em&gt;. Ancient Art and Architecture in Context 1. Princeton: American School of Classical Studies at Athens.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Bilimovitch 1970&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Bilimovitch, Z. A. 1970. “Deux cuvettes de bronze de provenence des tumulus dits Sémibratniye.” &lt;em&gt;Sov. Arkheol&lt;/em&gt;. 1970/73: 128–35 (in Russian).&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Boltrik, Fialko, and Treister 2011&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Boltrik, Y. V., E. F. Fialko, and M. Treister. 2011. “Imported Bronze Vessels from the East Catacomb in the Berdyansk Barrow.” &lt;em&gt;Ancient Civilizations from Scythia to Siberia&lt;/em&gt; 17: 255–78.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Bosi 2007&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Bosi, F. 2007. “Sulle rive del Mar Nero: incontri di civiltà.” In &lt;em&gt;Ori dei cavalieri delle steppe: Collezioni dai musei dell’Ucraina&lt;/em&gt;, ed. G. L. Bonora and F. Marzatico, 272–77. Exh. cat. Trento, Castello del Buonconsiglio, Monumenti e collezione provincials. Milan: Cinisello Balsamo.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Carapanos 1878&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Carapanos, C. 1878. &lt;em&gt;Dodone et ses ruines&lt;/em&gt;. Paris: Hachette.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Filow 1927&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Filow, B. D. 1927. &lt;em&gt;Die archaische Nekropole von Trebenischte am Ochrida See&lt;/em&gt;. Berlin and Leipzig: de Gruyter.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Galanakis 2011&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Galanakis, Y., and D. McCarthy, eds. 2011. &lt;em&gt;Heracles to Alexander the Great: Treasures from the Royal Capital of Macedon, a Hellenic Kingdom in the Age of Democracy&lt;/em&gt;. Exh. cat. Oxford, Ashmolean Museum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Gauer 1981&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Gauer, W. 1981. “Ein spätarchaischer Beckengriff mit Tierkampfgruppe.” &lt;em&gt;Olympiabericht&lt;/em&gt; 10: 111–65.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Gauer 1991&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Gauer, W. 1991. &lt;em&gt;Die Bronzegefäße von Olympia&lt;/em&gt;, vol. 1. Olympische Forschungen 20. Berlin: de Gruyter.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Goldman 1940&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Goldman, H. 1940. “The Acropolis of Halae.” &lt;em&gt;Hesperia&lt;/em&gt; 9: 381–514.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Harris 1995&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Harris, D. 1995. &lt;em&gt;The Treasures of the Parthenon and Erechtheion&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford: Clarendon.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Keramopoullos 1915&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Keramopoullos, A. 1915. “Μουσεῖα*.*” &lt;em&gt;ArchDelt&lt;/em&gt; 1: 19–34.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Marchiandi 2012&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Marchiandi, D. 2012. “Le consuetudini funerarie dell&amp;rsquo;élite ateniese: i lebeti bronzei di Myrina (Lemnos).” In &lt;em&gt;Gli Ateniesi fuori dall&amp;rsquo;attica: modi d&amp;rsquo;intervento e di controllo del territorio&lt;/em&gt;, Proceedings of the Congress at Torino, 2010 (ASAtene 88), ed. E. Culasso Gastaldi and D. Marchiandi, 221–36. Athens: Scuola archeologica italiana di Atene.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Reeder 2000&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Reeder, E. D., ed. 2000. &lt;em&gt;Scythian Gold: Treasures from Ancient Ukraine&lt;/em&gt;. Exh. cat. Baltimore, Walters Art Gallery. New York: Harry Abrams.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;De Ridder 1896&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Ridder, A. de. 1896. &lt;em&gt;Catalogue des bronzes trouvés sur l’Acropole d’Athènes&lt;/em&gt;. Paris: A. Fontemoing.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Robinson 1941&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Robinson, D. M. 1941. &lt;em&gt;Excavations at Olynthus X: Metal and Miscellaneous Finds, an Original Contribution to Greek Life&lt;/em&gt;. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Stibbe 2000&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Stibbe, C. M. 2000. &lt;em&gt;The Sons of Hephaistos: Aspects of the Archaic Greek Bronze Industry&lt;/em&gt;. Rome: L’Erma di Bretschneider.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Stibbe 2003&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Stibbe, C. M. 2003. &lt;em&gt;Trebenishte: The Fortunes of an Unusual Excavation&lt;/em&gt;. Studia archeologica 121. Rome: L’Erma di Bretschneider.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Stibbe 2006&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Stibbe, C. M. 2006. &lt;em&gt;Agalmata: Studien zur griechisch-archaischen Bronzekunst&lt;/em&gt;. Dudley (MA): Peeters.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Stibbe 2008&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Stibbe, C. M. 2008. “Laconian Bronzes from the Sanctuary of Apollo Hyperteleatas near Phoiniki (Laconia) and the Acropolis of Athens.” &lt;em&gt;BaBesch&lt;/em&gt; 2008: 17–45.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Tarditi 2007&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Tarditi, C. 2007. “La diffusione del vasellame bronzeo greco in Italia e in Europa: modalità e limiti.” In &lt;em&gt;Dalla Grecia all’Europa: la circolazione di beni di lusso e di modelli culturali nel VI e V sec. a.C&lt;/em&gt;., ed. C. Tarditi, 23–52. Milan: V&amp;amp;P.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Tarditi 2014&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Tarditi, C. 2014. “Il motivo del leone nell’atene arcaica: diffusione e stile nella produzione ateniese di vasellame in bronzo.” &lt;em&gt;Erga-Logoi&lt;/em&gt; 2.2: 31–63.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Tarditi 2016&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Tarditi, C. 2016. &lt;em&gt;Bronze Vessels from the Acropolis: Style and Decoration in Athenian Production between the Sixth and Fifth Centuries BC&lt;/em&gt;. Rome: Edizioni Quasar.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Treister 2010&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Treister, M. 2010. “Bronze and Silver Greek, Macedonian and Etruscan Vessels in Scythia*.*” &lt;em&gt;Bollettino di Archeologia On&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Line&lt;/em&gt;, vol. speciale, 17th International Congress of Classical Archaeology (Rome, 2008): 9–26.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Trofimova 2007&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Trofimova, A. A., ed. 2007. &lt;em&gt;Greeks on the Black Sea: Ancient Art from the Hermitage&lt;/em&gt;. Exh. cat. Los Angeles: J. Paul Getty Museum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Vasić 2003&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Vasić, R. 2003. “To the North of Trebenishte.” In Stibbe 2003, 111–35.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Vokotopoulou 1996&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Vokotopoulou, I. 1996. &lt;em&gt;Führer durch das Archäologische Museum Thessaloniki&lt;/em&gt;. Athens: Kapon Editions.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Vokotopoulou 1997&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Vokotopoulou, I. 1997. &lt;em&gt;Αργυρά και χάλκινα έργα τέχνης&lt;/em&gt;. Athens: Ekdotikē Athenōn.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Vulić 1930&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Vulić, N. 1930. “Das neue Grab von Trebenischte.” &lt;em&gt;AA&lt;/em&gt;: 276–299.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;De Ridder 1896; Keramopoullos 1915; more recently Gauer 1981; Stibbe 2008.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;Tarditi 2016.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;For a complete list with inventory numbers, see Tarditi 2016, appendix 1.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;Tarditi 2016, appendix 2.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;For a complete list see Tarditi 2016, appendixes 3 and 4.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;Tarditi 2016, Type Bh.2.I.A–B.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;Tarditi 2016, 243–45.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;Tarditi 2016, Type Bh.4.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;Tarditi 2016, Type Bh.5.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;Tarditi 2016, Type Bh.3.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;Tarditi 2016, Type Bh.3.II.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;Tarditi 2016, Type PA.2.III–IV; see also Tarditi 2014.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;Tarditi 2016, Type Oh.1.A.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;Tarditi 2014.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;Tarditi 2016, Type Bh.3.II.C.a–b.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34;&gt;Gauer 1981; Vokotopoulou 1997, nos. 149–50; Tarditi 2007.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34;&gt;Dodona, Athens, Archaeological Museum, Carapanos Collection inv. 22 (Carapanos 1878, 48, no. 22; tab. XVI, no. 4); Paris, Louvre, inv. Br 4643, catalogue on line; New York, Metropolitan Museum, inv. 1981.11.23, catalogue on line; Toledo (OH), Toledo Museum of Art, inv. 1964.125, catalogue on line.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:18&#34;&gt;I.e., inv. 7099, 7103, 7104, 7105, and 19997 from the Acropolis (Tarditi 2016, catalogue).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:18&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:19&#34;&gt;Stibbe 2000, 62-64; Tarditi 2016, 313–14.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:19&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:20&#34;&gt;Stibbe 2000, 57–99; Stibbe 2006, 312.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:20&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:21&#34;&gt;Tarditi 2016, catalogue, inv. 7080.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:21&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:22&#34;&gt;Stibbe 2000, 153–55.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:22&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:23&#34;&gt;Munich, Antikensammlung, inv. 4262.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:23&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:24&#34;&gt;Thessaloniki, Archaeological Museum inv. 5124.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:24&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:25&#34;&gt;Metropolitan Museum of Art inv. 60.11.2a–b, thought also by Stibbe to be Attic. Stibbe 2006, 312.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:25&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:26&#34;&gt;Tarditi 2016, type La.3 (inv. 7107 and 7116) and type Bh.3.II.D (inv. 7128 and 21463).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:26&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:27&#34;&gt;Tarditi 2016, chapter 1, 2.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:27&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:28&#34;&gt;De Ridder 1896, xxiii.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:28&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:29&#34;&gt;For example, the Princely Tomb at Sala Consilina and the tombs from the Rutigliano necropolis, of the late sixth to early fifth century BC, and those from Cavallino, Ginosa, Valenzano, Miglionico, Padula, and Botromagno, all dated mainly to the fifth century BC: for bibliography Tarditi 2016, 317.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:29&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:30&#34;&gt;Athens, Archaeological Museum, inv. 6402; Olympia, Archaeological Museum, inv. Br 12120, both from Late Archaic contexts (Gauer 1991, 203: nos. Le 216 and Le 217); inv. B 10416 and two pieces without number (Gauer 1991, 203: nos. Le 215 and Le 218, both from Late Archaic contexts); inv. B 5934 and B 5792, both Early Archaic (Gauer 1991, 270–71: nos. E 26 and E 27); Olympia, Archaeological Museum, inv. Br. 13417 (Gauer 1991, 243: no. P47) from a Classical context; inv. B 5286, found together with Archaic sherds (Gauer 1991, 238: no. P9, tab. 58); inv. Br 5129 (Athens Archaeological Museum, inv. 6403) (Gauer 1991, 51 and 206: no. Le 244, thought to be Early Archaic); inv. Br 3481 and B 154, from a well that was closed in the last quarter of the sixth century (Gauer 1991, 54; 208: no. Le 262; 212: no. Le 297); inv. Br. 13044 and Br. 14418 (Gauer 1991, 20: nos. Le 229 and Le 230, dated around 530–520 BC).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:30&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:31&#34;&gt;Goldman 1940, 415.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:31&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:32&#34;&gt;Barr-Sharrar 2008, 56.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:32&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:33&#34;&gt;Harris 1995, 1–8.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:33&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:34&#34;&gt;For complete references (museum, inventory number) about the mentioned pieces, see Tarditi 2016, appendix 4.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:34&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:35&#34;&gt;Pella: handle of a krater (Barr-Sharrar 2008, 54); Olinthus, a basin handle (Robinson 1941, no. 816, pl. LXIV); Derveni: probably two kraters, one amphora-situla (Barr-Sharrar 2008, 54) and one patera (Galanakis 2011, 244); Stavroupolis: a situla-krater (Vokotopoulou 1996, 187).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:35&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:36&#34;&gt;Myrina on the island of Lemnos: nine handles and reel for &lt;em&gt;lebetes&lt;/em&gt; (Marchiandi 2010).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:36&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:37&#34;&gt;Trebeništa: three tripod bases (Filow 1927, 69, nos. 83 and 84; Vulić 1930, fig. 14; Novi Pazar: one &lt;em&gt;podanipter&lt;/em&gt; (Vasić 2003, 132, figs. 92–94); Stobi: a basin handle (Stibbe 2003, 118, fig. 76).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:37&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:38&#34;&gt;Stibbe 2003, 89–110.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:38&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:39&#34;&gt;Boltrik, Fialko, and Treister 2011, fig. 7.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:39&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:40&#34;&gt;Bilimovitch 1970, 132–35.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:40&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:41&#34;&gt;Reeder 2000, 193–204; Barone 2007; Treister 2010.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:41&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:42&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kalpides&lt;/em&gt; and basin on tripod base: Reeder 2000, 192–93; 195, no. 93; Treister 2010, 12.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:42&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:43&#34;&gt;See articles in Trofinova 2007; Bosi 2007.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:43&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:44&#34;&gt;Tarditi 2007.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:44&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:45&#34;&gt;Tarditi 2016, 316–17.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:45&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:46&#34;&gt;Krater from Contrada Mosè: Agrigento, inv. NM 20733 (Barr-Sharrar 2008, 54).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:46&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:47&#34;&gt;London, British Museum, inv. 1865,0103.43 (Bronze 258) (Barr-Sharrar 2008, 54).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:47&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:48&#34;&gt;Reggio Calabria, inv. NM 7375 (Gauer 1981).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:48&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bronze Vessels and Related *Instrumenta* at Delphi</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/vessels/25-meirano/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/vessels/25-meirano/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The circumstances under which the École Française d’Athènes conducted the chief excavation of the sanctuary of Delphi are well known: the so-called Grande Fouille (Great Excavation) represents a foundational page in the history of archaeological excavations in Greece during the nineteenth century. Between 1892 and 1903, French archaeologists brought to light the major part of the site (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 25.1&lt;/strong&gt;), unveiling the ruins of the celebrated monuments described in the literary texts and contributing to the understanding of one of the most famous sanctuaries of the ancient world.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Topography, architecture, and sculpture were of course the main objectives, while the remaining evidence received far less attention during the excavations and in the subsequent studies. The &lt;em&gt;Journal de la Grande Fouille&lt;/em&gt;, written during the decade of archaeological work, is proof of this attitude. Some pages, like the ones by Paul Perdrizet dealing with ceramics and small bronzes (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 25.2&lt;/strong&gt;), represent exceptions in the general picture one gets from browsing the excavation journal.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach toward exploration and the recording of data—aiming for the grand sweep of history and emphasizing rare treasures while discounting or ignoring smaller, more common artifacts—was widespread at the time and absolutely the norm in the nineteenth century. It inevitably caused the loss of a considerable number of pieces and of a wide body of information regarding the specific, original contexts and depositional conditions from which objects were retrieved. This paucity of information also applies to *anathemata*—items dedicated in the sanctuary for the purpose of denunciation or curse. It has hampered our understanding of various aspects related to the presence and use of these items in the sanctuary—for example, the crucial distinction between offerings and ritual devices—and made it difficult to identify assemblages of objects related to specific religious practices performed in the sacred area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the Grande Fouille, a consistent publication program started, including the small finds, which were published by Perdrizet himself in 1908.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In this volume, which is still a fundamental work, a first selection of bronzes was documented. In the following decades, finds from new excavations were presented in preliminary reports in the &lt;em&gt;Bulletin de Correspondence Hellénique&lt;/em&gt; (BCH)&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; while the majority of the contributions concerning the bronzes at Delphi were left to Claude Rolley. He was responsible for the systematic publication of the statuettes and the geometric tripods,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; the synthesis in the &lt;em&gt;Guide de Delphes&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:6&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and numerous articles published mainly in the BCH.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:7&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last few years, some specific categories of objects have seen systematic or at least partial publication, for example the helmets by Heide Freilinghaus,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:8&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and the seventh-century bronzes by Hélène Aurigny.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:9&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The publication of a recent excavation in &lt;em&gt;L’aire du pilier des Rhodiens&lt;/em&gt; by Jean Marc Luce (2008)&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:10&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; provided fresh evidence concerning bronzes and their contextualization, an issue that previous documentation had made it difficult to approach at Delphi.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:11&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite this progress, the vessels and the related instruments dating from Archaic to Roman times remained mostly unpublished, apart from some selective or preliminary studies. The aim of my work, which is still ongoing, is to put these &lt;em&gt;disiecta membra&lt;/em&gt; and unpublished pieces in a wider perspective and to contribute to the understanding of offering choices, ritual practices performed in the sacred place, and the circulation of the metal objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the space constraints of this volume, I will expand only on some aspects of this broad topic. In light of the recent systematic survey, it is noteworthy that the dossier concerning the bronze vessels is meager compared with evidence coming from other contexts, for example Olympia and the Athenian acropolis, which is now the subject of reappraisal.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:12&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The melting down of artifacts and the poor preservation of bronze due to the soil conditions at Delphi&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:13&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; surely played a role in conservation (or lack thereof) and in determining the selection of the pieces to retrieve from the ground during past excavations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to try to reestablish a reliable picture of the occurrence of bronze vases and &lt;em&gt;instrumenta&lt;/em&gt; in the sanctuary, we should also take into account the data coming from epigraphic evidence and from literary sources, even on precious vessels. Herodotus mentions the six gold kraters offered by Gyges; the monumental silver krater on an iron stand by Glaukos of Chios, offered by Alyattes; and the golden cups and the two kraters offered by Croesus—one of silver and one of gold, attributed to Theodoros of Samos–which were positioned before the temple of Apollo.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:14&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Bronze vases, even monumental ones, must have been a very common sight among the offerings in the sacred area and even among the furniture and ritual tools: bronze tripods, for example, are less numerous than expected among the unearthed objects; nevertheless they play a crucial role in the imagery related to the sanctuary and are often evoked in allusions to the sacred place, long after the Geometric period. The presence of bronze &lt;em&gt;phialai mesomphaloi&lt;/em&gt; as divine attributes and their use as ritual instruments is also widely reflected in official monuments and iconographies.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:15&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though it is not possible to present it in detail here, a general picture of the occurrence, morphology, and chronology of bronze vessels recovered from Delphi is now available. The quantitative indications are provisional and subject to change as the study progresses; in addition, a range of factors have yet to be taken into account in statistical analysis.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:16&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Notwithstanding these difficulties, a quantitative approach is crucial and offers a fresh means of investigating the realm of offerings—and their meaning—in the sacred context.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:17&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As previously stated, contextualization is problematic at Delphi, but nevertheless it rewards study. Although the majority of the finds of known provenance come from the sanctuaries of Apollo and Athena at Marmaria, some evidence was retrieved from funerary and domestic contexts as well. In general, the number of bronze vases and instruments dramatically decreases starting from the fourth century BC. Among the pieces of known provenance, the Hellenistic and later ones mainly come from profane contexts, a sign of the progressive change in ritual practice and offering strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open shapes are predominant. Among them we find the *phialai mesomphaloi*—the drinking vessels and the libation vases *par excellence*—both in the “plain” and in the “lotus-bowl” versions together with large, deep bowls (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 25.3&lt;/strong&gt;). Kantharoi, kylikes and other handled cups, skyphoi, and mugs are far less attested, while handles are the only surviving parts of paterae.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Various types of large and medium-size basins are widely documented, as well as &lt;em&gt;deinoi&lt;/em&gt; (spherical mixing vessels) with their characteristic profile. I could identify the presence of at least two fragments pertaining to basins with embossed rims, a shape that was not attested previously at Delphi.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:18&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; These vessels provide clues to the attendance at the sanctuary, or rather to the circulation of bronze objects. The shape of the basins is of certain Etruscan origin and the majority of the specimens known so far come from the Tyrrhenian area and from the central Italian peninsula. Nevertheless, the vessel type is widely documented, from the barbarian contexts of central-western Europe to central-eastern Mediterranean. In Greece, these basins are definitely rare and occur in only a few sites, namely sanctuaries, including Olympia.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:19&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In the last few decades, the version bearing a single row of bosses—like the specimens attested at Delphi—has been noticed in eastern Sicily, where these vessels mainly occur in graves as funerary receptacles:&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:20&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:20&#34;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; the proposal of local production has been advanced, based on technical and morphological features. In Southern Italy as well, the discovery of a homogeneous group of basins of this type—mostly coming from the sanctuary of Scrimbia at Hipponion in southern Calabria&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:21&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:21&#34;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;—showing close affinities with the Sicilian group, corroborates the hypothesis of a western Greek manufacture inspired by Etruscan prototypes. Technical details would in some cases support the Greek colonial provenance of some of the basins found in Greece. In the case of the fragments from Delphi, which do not preserve their entire profile, it would be difficult to ascertain their origin, apart from their western provenance: a south Italian or Sicilian production remains conjectural, though highly probable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kraters are attested by a few ascertained fragments, a pale echo of the presence of this shape in the sanctuary as recorded by the ancient sources. Among them, some can be ascribed to volute specimens, which are notoriously rare.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:22&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:22&#34;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few pieces attest to the presence of small forms like pyxides, &lt;em&gt;bombylioi&lt;/em&gt;, bottles, and aryballoi, among which are also bronze disk rims that attached to small vases of perishable material, and one rare figured specimen in the shape of a tortoise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Large closed shapes, which can be recognized as hydriai&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; olpai, and oinochoai&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; are mainly documented by fragments or miniature versions, with some exceptions. One is the known hydria dating to the mid-fifth century BC, which served as a cinerary urn in a tomb unearthed during the excavations for the building of the new museum.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:23&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:23&#34;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Another example is a small, refined trefoil oinochoe, which can be compared with Macedonian specimens of the fourth century BC.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:24&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:24&#34;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As expected, the number of handles is large. Some are figured specimens with stylistic features that significantly contribute to the identification of production areas and to the definition of circulation dynamics of bronze objects. The various types of attested vertical handles suggest a wider range of closed shapes in comparison to what is documented by other morphologies (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 25.4&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Refined horizontal handles, sometimes with decorative elements, as well as figured appliqués, support the presence of large vases like &lt;em&gt;podanipteres&lt;/em&gt; or kraters, which are also possibly echoed by fragments of stands with lion paws.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:25&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:25&#34;&gt;25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Some small tripods were connected to &lt;em&gt;exaleiptra&lt;/em&gt; and to other small or miniature shapes (&lt;strong&gt;figs. 25.5–6&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the &lt;em&gt;instrumenta&lt;/em&gt;, lamps are attested especially in the late Hellenistic and Roman times, when we find some figured specimens, like one in the shape of a grotesque figure (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 25.7&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:26&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:26&#34;&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we find a group of “vertical” instruments, namely candelabra, &lt;em&gt;kottaboi&lt;/em&gt; (stands used in the drinking game &lt;em&gt;kottabos&lt;/em&gt;), and other such articles. Some pieces—in particular a few curved arms with decorated finials showing serpent heads or floral motifs—are probably to be interpreted as parts of utensil stands, a rare class that is better known in western Greece, thanks to some specimens from Epizephyrian Lokroi (Locri, in Calabria).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:27&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:27&#34;&gt;27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research on Delphic bronze vessels and instruments also seeks to record and explain the detectable traces of actions made during the sacred rituals and the consecrations of offerings, in order to better understand the behaviors performed by devotees and priests in the sacred precinct. The “partial” offering of metal objects has already been demonstrated in various Greek sacred contexts, especially regarding vases and weapons.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:28&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:28&#34;&gt;28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Modifications of and deliberate damage to bronze objects by breaking, bending, piercing, mutilating, and so on are known at many necropoleis and sanctuaries, including Delphi, where this practice is attested on some helmet cheek-pieces.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:29&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:29&#34;&gt;29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;acknowledgments&#34;&gt;Acknowledgments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The research on metal vessels and related &lt;em&gt;instrumenta&lt;/em&gt; at Delphi is conducted in the frame of the Contrat Quinquennal of the École Française d’Athènes under the auspices of the local Ephoria. I would also like to acknowledge the Alexander S. Onassis Public Benefit Foundation in Athens and the Scuola Archeologica Italiana di Atene for their support and the research facilities provided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bibliography&#34;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Albanese 1979&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Albanese, R. M. 1979. “Bacini bronzei con orlo perlato del Museo Archeologico di Siracusa.” &lt;em&gt;BdA&lt;/em&gt;: 1–20.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Albanese Procelli 1980–81&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Albanese Procelli, R. M. 1980–81. “Intervento.” &lt;em&gt;Kokalos&lt;/em&gt; 26–27: 139–48.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Albanese Procelli 1985&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Albanese Procelli, R. M. 1985. “Considerazioni sulla distribuzione dei bacini bronzei in area tirrenica e in Sicilia.” In &lt;em&gt;Il commercio etrusco arcaico: Atti dell’incontro di studio, Salerno 5–7 dicembre 1983&lt;/em&gt; (QArchEtr 9), 179–206. Rome: CNR.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Aurigny 2010&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Aurigny, H. 2010. “Delphes au VIIe siècle.” In &lt;em&gt;La Méditerranée au VIIe siècle av. J.-C.: Essais d’analyses archéologiques&lt;/em&gt; (Travaux de la maison René Ginouvès 7), ed. R. Etienne, 234–49. Paris: de Boccard.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Aurigny 2011&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Aurigny, H. 2011. “Le sanctuaire de Delphes et ses relations extérieures au VIIème siècle av J.-C.: le témoignage des offrandes.” In &lt;em&gt;Delphes, sa cité, sa région, ses relations internationales: Actes de la Table Ronde organisée les 24 et 25 septembre 2010&lt;/em&gt; (Pallas: Revue d’études antiques 87), ed. J. M. Luce, 151–68. Toulouse: Presses Universitaire du Mirail.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Baitinger 2013&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Baitinger, H. 2013. &lt;em&gt;Sizilisch-Unteritalische Funde in Griechischen Heiligtümern: Ein Beitrag zu den Votivsitten in Griechenland in spätgeometrischer und archaïscher Zeit&lt;/em&gt;. Mainz: Verlag des Römisch-Germanischen Zentralmuseums.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;École Française d’Athènes 1991&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;École Française d’Athènes. 1991. &lt;em&gt;Guide de Delphes: Le Musée&lt;/em&gt;. Paris: de Boccard.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;École Française d’Athènes 1992&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;École Française d’Athènes. 1992. &lt;em&gt;La redécouverte de Delphes&lt;/em&gt;. Paris: de Boccard.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Frielinghaus 2006&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Frielinghaus, H. 2006. “Deliberate Damage to Bronze Votives in Olympia during Archaic and Early Classical Times.” In &lt;em&gt;Common Ground: Archaeology, Art, Science and Humanities, Proceedings of the XVIth International Congress of Classical Archaeology, Boston, August 23–26, 2003&lt;/em&gt;, ed. C. C. Mattusch, A. A. Donohue, and A. Brauer, 36–38. Oxford: Oxbow Books.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Frielinghaus 2007&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Frielinghaus, H. 2007. “Die Helme von Delphi.” &lt;em&gt;BCH&lt;/em&gt; 131: 139–85.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Frielinghaus 2011&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Frielinghaus, H. 2011. &lt;em&gt;Die Helme von Olympia: Ein Beitrag zu Waffenweihungen in Griechischen Heiligtümern&lt;/em&gt;. Olympische Forschungen 33. Berlin and New York: de Gruyter.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Graells i Fabregat 2016&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Graells i Fabregat, R. 2016. “Destruction of Votive Offerings in Greek Sanctuaries: The Case of the Cuirasses of Olympia.” In &lt;em&gt;Materielle Kultur und Identität im Spannungsfeld zwischen mediterraner Welt und Mitteleuropa: Akten der Internationalen Tagung am Römisch-Germanischen Zentralmuseum, Mainz, 22.–24. Oktober 2014&lt;/em&gt;, ed. H. Baitinger, 149–60. Mainz: Verlag des Römisch-Germanischen Zentralmuseums.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Hansen 1960&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Hansen, E. 1960. “Les abords du trésor de Siphnos à Delphes.” &lt;em&gt;BCH&lt;/em&gt; 84: 387–433.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Jacquemin 1992&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Jacquemin, A. 1992. “En feuilletant le Journal de la Grande Fouille.” In École Française d’Athènes 1992, 149–79.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;La Genière 2014&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;La Genière, J. de, ed. 2014. &lt;em&gt;Le cratère à volutes: Destinations d’un vase de prestige entre Grecs et non-Grecs: Actes du Colloque international du Corpus Vasorum Antiquorum, Paris, 26–27 octobre 2012&lt;/em&gt;. Cahiers du Corpus vasorum antiquorum (France) 2. Paris: de Boccard.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Luce 2008&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Luce, J.-M., ed. 2008. &lt;em&gt;L’aire du Pilier des Rhodiens (fouille 1990–1992) à la frontière du profane et du sacré&lt;/em&gt;. Fouilles de Delphes 2; Topographie et architecture 13&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; Athènes-Paris: de Boccard.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Magou et al. 1991&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Magou, E., M. Pernot, and C. Rolley. 1991. “Bronzes orientaux et orientalisants: Analyses complémentaires.” &lt;em&gt;BCH&lt;/em&gt; 115: 560–77.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Masson and Rolley 1971&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Masson, O., and C. Rolley. 1971. “Un bronze de Delphes à inscription chypriote syllabique.” &lt;em&gt;BCH&lt;/em&gt; 95: 295–304.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Meirano 2002&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Meirano, V. 2002. “&lt;em&gt;Utensil stands&lt;/em&gt; da Locri Epizefiri: Nuovi dati dalla necropoli di Lucifero e dal santuario di Mannella.” In &lt;em&gt;I Bronzi antichi: produzione e tecnologia: Atti del XV Congresso Internazionale sui Bronzi Antichi, Grado-Aquileia 22–26 maggio 2001&lt;/em&gt;, ed. A. Giumlia Mair, 117–26. Montagnac: Éditions Monique Mergoil.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Meirano 2004&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Meirano,V. 2004. “Bacili ad orlo perlinato: nuovi dati dai contesti sacri della Calabria meridionale.” In &lt;em&gt;The Antique Bronzes: Typology, Chronology and Authenticity:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Acta of the 16th International Congress on Antique Bronzes, Bucharest, May 26th–31st, 2003&lt;/em&gt;, ed. C. Muşeteanu, 305–17. Bucarest: Editura Cetatea de Scaun.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Meirano 2005&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Meirano, V. 2005. “Vasellame ed &lt;em&gt;instrumentum&lt;/em&gt; metallico nei santuari di Locri/Mannella, Hipponion/Scrimbia e Medma/Calderazzo.” In &lt;em&gt;Lo spazio del rito: Santuari e culti in Italia meridionale tra indigeni e Greci: Atti delle giornate di studio, Matera 28–29/6/2002&lt;/em&gt;, ed. M. L. Nava and M. Osanna (Siris: Studi e ricerche della Scuola di Specializzaizone in Beni archeologici di Matera, Suppl. 1), 43–53.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Meirano 2012&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Meirano V. 2012. “Contributo alla conoscenza del vasellame bronzeo di età arcaica in Calabria meridionale: i bacili ad orlo perlinato.” In &lt;em&gt;Vincenzo Nusdeo sulle tracce della storia: Studi in onore di Vincenzo Nusdeo nel decennale della scomparsa&lt;/em&gt;, ed. M. D’Andrea, 93–107. Vibo Valentia: AdHoc Edizioni.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Meirano 2014&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Meirano, V. 2014. “Vasi, strumenti e altri oggetti: Offerte in metallo e pratiche rituali nei santuari greci della Calabria meridionale.” In &lt;em&gt;Le spose e gli eroi: Offerte in bronzo e in ferro dai santuari e dalle necropoli della Calabria greca&lt;/em&gt;, ed. M. T. Iannelli and C. Sabbione, 32–38. Vibo Valentia: AdHoc Edizioni.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Meirano 2015­–2016&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Meirano, V. 2015–2016. “Étude des vases en métal et des instruments apparentés de Delphes, du VIème s. av. n. è. à l’époque romaine: Rapport 2014–2015.” &lt;em&gt;BCH&lt;/em&gt; 139–40.2.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Meirano 2016&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Meirano, V. 2016. “Bronze &lt;em&gt;phialai mesomphaloi&lt;/em&gt; in context: Some Recent and Older (Revisited) Case-studies.” In &lt;em&gt;Greek and Roman Bronzes from the Eastern Mediterranean:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Acta of the XVIIth International Congress on Ancient Bronzes, Izmir (Turkey) 2016&lt;/em&gt;, ed. A. Giumlia Mair and C. C. Mattusch, 79–86. Autun: Editions Mergoil.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Meirano forthcoming&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Meirano, V. Forthcoming. “Bassins à rebord perlé à Delphes.” In preparation.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Perdrizet 1908&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Perdrizet, P. 1908. &lt;em&gt;Monuments figurés, petits bronzes, terres cuites, antiquités diverses&lt;/em&gt;. Fouilles de Delphes 5; Monuments figurés 1. Paris: Albert Fontemoing.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Rolley 1969&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Rolley, C. 1969. &lt;em&gt;Le statuettes de bronze&lt;/em&gt;. Fouilles de Delphes 5; Monuments figurés 2. Paris: de Boccard.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Rolley 1977&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Rolley, C. 1977. &lt;em&gt;Les trépieds à cuve clouée&lt;/em&gt;. Fouilles de Delphes 5; Monuments figurés 3. Paris: de Boccard.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Rolley 1991a&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Rolley, C. 1991a. “Les bronzes: Statuettes et objets divers.” In &lt;em&gt;Guide
de Delphes: Le Musée&lt;/em&gt;, 139-79. Paris: École Française d’Athènes.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Rolley 1991b&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Rolley, C. 1991b. “Statues de bronze: fragments divers.” In &lt;em&gt;Guide de Delphes: Le Musée&lt;/em&gt;, 187–89. Paris: École Française d’Athènes.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Rolley 1999&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Rolley, C. 1999. “Delphes: Les bronzes.” &lt;em&gt;BCH&lt;/em&gt; 123: 465–67.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Rolley 2002&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Rolley, C. 2002. “Le travail du bronze à Delphes.” &lt;em&gt;BCH&lt;/em&gt; 126: 41–54.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Rolley 2003&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Rolley, C., ed. 2003. &lt;em&gt;La tombe princière de Vix&lt;/em&gt;. Paris: Picard.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Rolley and Rougemont 1973&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Rolley, C., and G. Rougemont. 1973. “Sondage à l’Est du sanctuaire d’Apollon: Catalogue des objets en métal.” &lt;em&gt;BCH&lt;/em&gt; 97: 512–25.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Siganidou 1979&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Siganidou, M. 1979. “Western Macedonia.” In &lt;em&gt;Treasures of Ancient Macedonia&lt;/em&gt;, ed. K. Ninou, 38–47. Athens: Archaeological Museum of Thessalonike.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Tarditi 2016a&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Tarditi, C. 2016. “The Athenian Archaic Bronze Vessel Production: New Evidence from Old Excavations.” In &lt;em&gt;Greek and Roman Bronzes from the Eastern Mediterranean:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Acta of the XVIIth International Congress on Ancient Bronzes, Izmir&lt;/em&gt;, ed. A. Giumlia Mair and C. C. Mattusch, 49–58. Autun: Editions Mergoil.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Tarditi 2016b&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Tarditi, C. 2016. &lt;em&gt;Bronze Vessels from the Acropolis: Style and Decoration in Athenian Production between the sixth and fifth centuries BC.&lt;/em&gt; Rome: Edizioni Quasar.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;For the Grande Fouille and its scientific and political implications, see École Française d’Athènes 1992.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;For the degree of scrutiny by Perdrizet in observing and documenting the small finds, see Jacquemin 1992, 156–57; Meirano 2016.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;Perdrizet 1908.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;Hansen 1960; Rolley and Rougemont 1973; Rolley 1999.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;Rolley 1969 and 1977.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;Rolley 1991a.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;Masson and Rolley 1971; Rolley 2002; for the archaeometric program on geometric, oriental, and orientalizing bronzes, including samples taken from objects from Delphi, see Magou et al. 1991 and previous contributions in the BCH.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;Freilinghaus 2007.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;Aurigny 2010 and 2011.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;Luce 2008.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;Meirano 2015–2016 and Meirano 2016.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;Tarditi 2016a; Tarditi 2016b; and her paper in this volume.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;Rolley 1991b, 187.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;Herodotus 1.14, 1.25, 1.51.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;Meirano 2016.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34;&gt;The bronze objects are particularly fragmentary at Delphi; they are often badly preserved and in some cases in need of conservation. These circumstances do not facilitate the identification of the “minimum number of individuals”: see Meirano 2015–2016.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34;&gt;See, for example, the remarks about the occurrence of various kinds of weapons in the sanctuary of Olympia—and their implications—recently made by Graells i Fabregat (2016, 149 and fig. 1).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:18&#34;&gt;Meirano forthcoming.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:18&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:19&#34;&gt;For a review of the find contexts of embossed rim basins in Greece, with further bibliography, see Meirano 2004, 306; Meirano 2012, 96; Baitinger 2013, 251–52.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:19&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:20&#34;&gt;Among the numerous contributions devoted to this topic, see Albanese 1979; Albanese Procelli 1980–81 and 1985.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:20&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:21&#34;&gt;Meirano 2004; 2005, 47–48; 2012, 97–102; 2014. In the same region, a few specimens come from the Greek colonies of Lokroi, Rhegion, and Kroton: see Meirano 2004, 306.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:21&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:22&#34;&gt;See Rolley 2003, 102–103, n. 15, figs. 59–61. For the particular status of the volute krater as a “prestige vase,” especially in the metal version, also see: de La Genière 2014.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:22&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:23&#34;&gt;Rolley 1991a, 175, n. 43.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:23&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:24&#34;&gt;For example, see Siganidou 1979, 40, n. 35, plate 9 (from grave 1 of the Kozani necropolis).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:24&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:25&#34;&gt;Rolley and Rougemont 1973, 515–16, n. 5, figs. 21–22; Rolley 1991a, 165, n. 32.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:25&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:26&#34;&gt;Rolley 1991a, 179, n. 49.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:26&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:27&#34;&gt;Meirano 2002.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:27&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:28&#34;&gt;For the practice of selective or partial dedication of metal vessels in western Greek sacred contexts, see Meirano 2014, 34; see also Meirano 2016. Concerning the separated offering of cuirass breastplates and back-plates at Olympia and in other Greek sanctuaries, see Graells i Fabregat 2016, 152–53.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:28&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:29&#34;&gt;Frielinghaus 2007, 147. See Meirano 2015–2016 and Meirano 2016 for further bibliography on this practice, also regarding mirrors, vases, and other types of weapons in Greek sanctuaries of southern Italy. For the deliberate damage to bronze objects at Olympia, see Frielinghaus 2006; Frielinghaus 2011, 185–200; about this practice regarding bronze cuirasses at Olympia, the destruction steps, and possible meanings, see Graells i Fabregat 2016.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:29&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Toward the Derveni Krater</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/vessels/26-gaunt/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/vessels/26-gaunt/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;A simple observation provides the point of departure for this paper. The decorative schemes of two Greek bronze volute kraters—the Archaic one found at Vix in Burgundy (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 26.1&lt;/strong&gt;) and the Late Classical one from Derveni near Thessaloniki (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 26.2&lt;/strong&gt;)—differ radically.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The critical distinction lies in the prominent Dionysian frieze in high relief on the body of the latter. It is most unusual to find figural decoration at a large scale on the bodies of substantial Greek bronze vessels of the Archaic and Classical periods. The figural decoration on the body of the Derveni krater, too, was well outside the usual canon even at the time of manufacture, far removed from the generally austere appearance of Archaic and Classical bronze vessels—acknowledging, however, some important fifth-century developments in surface treatments, notably reeding. The restrained decoration of most Greek bronze vessels was a deliberate aesthetic choice, as suggested by comparison with contemporary pieces of armor: these are often much more elaborately embellished. Contemporary representations of these objects show that this difference is not simply a function of chance survival. This comparison inspires a generalizing rule: plain vessels, but elaborate armor. The contrast, I propose, goes back to the Homeric poems, which clearly articulate such a distinction. The underlying reasons for these profound differences, I will argue, may well have been economic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In stark contrast to the opulence of the Derveni krater, the surviving large Greek bronze vessels of the Archaic and Classical periods (kraters, amphorae, hydriai, and so forth) are, to a remarkable degree, homogenous in the restraint of their decoration. Three archaeological contexts are especially illuminating: the series of graves of Balkan chieftains at Trebenishte; the so-called heroon at Paestum; and the finds at Pischane, Ukraine.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Collectively, they account for over one hundred completely preserved bronze vessels. Leaving aside restricted pattern-work like shoulder tongues, every one of these vessels has a plain body. The decoration was confined primarily to the cast elements that served utilitarian functions—handles, feet, and bases—while on larger vases appliqués were sometimes also attached to the shoulder or neck. Well-known examples include the volute-krater from Trebenishte, now in Belgrade, and the hydria with a lion peering over the rim from Paestum.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This general scheme of decoration is also familiar from other shapes, such as the oinochoe in Budapest whose handle is modeled in the form of an equestrian astride the spout; or the pointed amphora at the Metropolitan Museum in New York (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 26.3&lt;/strong&gt;), whose body is relatively elaborately decorated with shoulder tongues above a guilloche band.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Many more examples could easily be found, especially on hydriai.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This subdued decoration on larger vessels should, I believe, be respected as the considered choice of Greek metalsmiths and their customers, rather than reflecting any technical limitation. The craftsmen who made the Vix and Derveni kraters, for example, could surely have made anything they chose. Walls of vessels with figural decoration in repoussé like the Derveni krater were prone to crack, thereby causing leaks; but, as Beryl Barr-Sharrar has discovered, that krater was lined after completion with a protective layer of beeswax and a film of clay.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:6&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Furthermore, the concept of a double-walled vessel—the outer elaborately decorated, the inner a plain liner (familiar from small-scale Hellenistic and Roman silver cups)—is actually already present in the Archaic series of black- and red-figured psykter-amphorai and kraters that were made in Athens and Rhegium. These appear in the mid-sixth century with, for example, the Lydos amphora in London and continue until the Troilos Painter’s column krater of around 470 BC, now in New York.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:7&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Earlier still is a series of Phoenician bowls with double walls, some of which found their ways into Greek contexts.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:8&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the practice of decorating large areas of metalwork, whether through engraving, casting, repoussé, or a combination of techniques, is familiar from contemporary Greek armor. The famous breastplate from Olympia, with Zeus and Apollo between deities, exemplifies engraved work.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:9&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The magnificent shield devices document repoussé at a large scale: from the Archaic griffin suckling her young or the “composite Gorgon” from Olympia to a Late Classical rampant lion in Mougins (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 26.4&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:10&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The shield bands offer a view into small-scale work using the same techniques; one in the J. Paul Getty Museum gives us the earliest of all signatures for metalsmiths, Aristodamos of Argos.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:11&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Other pieces of armor, notably helmets and their cheekpieces but also greaves, sometimes reveal astonishing decorative metalwork.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:12&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; While a great deal of plain armor does of course survive, other examples were perhaps more for parade than for battle; the helmet in St. Louis&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fig-26-5&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:fig-26-5&#34;&gt;0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, for example, was evidently made for a figure of elevated importance, perhaps the same class of persons that commissioned the vessels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The restrained decoration accorded Archaic and Classical Greek bronze vessels stands in marked contrast not only to contemporary Greek armor but also to products of workshops outside Greece making similar vessels. The magnificent Orientalizing cauldrons from North Syria and elsewhere, with figures in high relief on the stands, were familiar enough in Greek sanctuaries.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:14&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; They were also popular in Etruria, where they engendered elaborate local responses, such as the tripod cauldron from the Barberini Tomb in Palestrina.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:15&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; From Italy and central-northern Europe comes a series of bronze situlae whose walls are decorated all over with figural registers.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:16&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; These were surely known in Greece given that their elite Italic and Celtic owners supplied Greek aristocrats with the thoroughbred horses from the Veneto, of which the lyric poet Alkman wrote.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:17&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The objection may be raised that, because so few Greek bronze vessels survive, any observations concerning their appearance are largely speculative. To counter this objection, we turn to traditions of representations of these vessels in four different media: coins, gems, terracottas, and back- and red-figured vases. Of these four, two—coins and gems—are interrelated, while images on terracottas and black- and red-figure vases stand apart. All four types, however, suggest independently that metal vessels with major figural decoration were extremely uncommon. Furthermore, the ceramic dinoid krater in the J. Paul Getty Museum (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 26.6&lt;/strong&gt;) demonstrates that surviving examples do indeed correspond closely with their representations.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:18&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Just this sort of vessel is depicted on contemporary volute-krater fragments attributed to near the Pronomos and Talos Painters, now in Würzburg, while a neo-Attic marble version in a private collection evidently derives from the very same models (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 26.7&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:19&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On coins and gems, scale alone does not explain why figural decoration on vessels is not shown: these same objects record minute details of ornate hoplite equipment, particularly in the wake of Pheidias’s chryselephantine Athena Parthenos.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:20&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:20&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Perhaps the most detailed glyptic example is the rather later intaglio in Rome signed by Aspasios that conscientiously reproduces the helmet of the Parthenos, but similar detail occurs on an earlier carnelian cameo of Perseus of Macedon, now in Paris, in which a centauromachy decorates his helmet.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:21&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:21&#34;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; On coins, helmets with elaborate figural decoration first appear on late fifth-century staters of Heraclea (continuing through the fourth century), and on gold twenty-litra coins of Camarina; and, through the fourth century, on staters of Thurium, distaters of Metapontum, and later didrachms of Hyele.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:22&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:22&#34;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Representations of shield devices are encountered on staters minted in late fourth-century Taranto (depicting Pegasos) and Opuntian Locris (griffin); and on didrachms in early third-century Epirus under Pyrrhus (Gorgoneion).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:23&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:23&#34;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This wealth of figurally decorated armor recorded on gems and coins contrasts markedly with contemporary representations of metal vessels in the same media. Archaic and Classical glyptic representations of kantharoi clearly depict metal rather than ceramic vessels, as we know from the treatment of the handles but also from the aristocratic clientele that is depicted.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:24&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:24&#34;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Nevertheless, almost all of these vessels are represented as entirely plain. Just occasionally, as on the beaded rim of the kantharos held by a satyr and the krater that stands beside it on a famous scarab in London, some understated surface elaboration is suggested.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:25&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:25&#34;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; An Archaic glyptic representation of a hydria with reeding or tongues on the shoulder, and a Classical version of a calyx-krater with reeded body are preserved; but not, to my knowledge, vessels with figural decoration.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:26&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:26&#34;&gt;25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A similar picture emerges in numismatics. The amphorai on Archaic coins from Athens, Chios, Terone, and of unknown Macedonian mint are naturally plain, being “transport” amphorai.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:27&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:27&#34;&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Yet so too are the many kantharoi depicted, most famously on early fifth-century staters of Naxos.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:28&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:28&#34;&gt;27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; As with the gems, the only decoration accorded to vessels on coins is reeding, as for example on the shoulders of volute-kraters on fourth-century hemidrachms minted in Lamia and staters minted in Thebes.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:29&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:29&#34;&gt;28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; As Barr-Sharrar has noted, these compare well with the shoulder tongues on the Derveni krater and those of an early Apulian volute-krater by the Painter of the Birth of Dionysos in Ruvo.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:30&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:30&#34;&gt;29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Images on coins and gems, therefore, suggest that metal vessels were either plain or only partially decorated with pattern-work such as reeding. The terracotta plaques from Locri would tend to confirm this.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:31&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:31&#34;&gt;30&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Three types depict a variety of vessels together. On one, in which Persephone returns folded cloth to a chest, a plain lekythos and kantharos are shown hanging from pegs.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:32&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:32&#34;&gt;31&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; A second type shows a table or cupboard on which stand four vessels: two plain alabastra, a plain pointed oinochoe, and a larger oinochoe with beaded rim, shoulder tongues, and tongues or rays at the foot.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:33&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:33&#34;&gt;32&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; A third type, with two women, one enthroned, depicts two phialai and a hydria hanging from pegs, while the seated woman holds a deep bowl. The bodies of all are reeded or, for the phialai, articulated with lobes.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:34&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:34&#34;&gt;33&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evidence for the appearance of major figural decoration on metal vessels from representations on vase paintings is more complex, but it, too, strongly suggests its rarity.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:35&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:35&#34;&gt;34&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Plentiful representations of vessels, sometimes washed in dilute glaze to approximate the appearance of polished metal, clearly depict these vases. The bail-handled amphora drawn in the tondo of a cup by Douris in New York (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 26.8&lt;/strong&gt;) is clearly metal because the mechanism for the swinging handle is carefully drawn.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:36&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:36&#34;&gt;35&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The hydriai carried as part of the Ransom of Hektor on the Brygos Painter’s skyphos in Vienna furnishes another example.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:37&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:37&#34;&gt;36&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Like surviving examples, the ones drawn are plain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also, however, an important series of images of vases on vases that do bear figural decoration. These are essentially confined in the sixth and fifth centuries to Attic black- and red-figured vases, and proliferate during the fourth century in Apulia. Dirk Oenbrink has compiled a list of around forty Attic examples, a number that, by comparison with the representations of plain vases, is almost insignificant.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:38&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:38&#34;&gt;37&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Among many observations possible, two are pertinent. First, most such images appear in the late fifth and fourth centuries, a time when evidence exists for greater decorative elaboration on works of art in general. Second, while each example is unto itself, nevertheless several of them clearly reference ceramic rather than metal vases. Heading the list are the magnificent mid-sixth-century column-krater fragments in New York with the Return of Hephaistos, where maenads and satyrs fill two volute-kraters with wine.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:39&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:39&#34;&gt;38&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Mary Moore has rightly argued that the ivy on the handles, the rays at the base, and the animal fight on one of them that compares so well with other black-figured kraters, all suggest the artist had ceramic rather than metal vases in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The practice of reeding for toreutic vessels must, by contrast, have been widespread. We have already encountered it on the shoulder tongues of the Derveni krater, and in representations of vessels on coins, gems, terracottas, and even vase paintings. The technique spread to black-glazed pottery during the second quarter of the fifth century.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:40&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:40&#34;&gt;39&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Although most common on small mugs, it is also found on larger vessels, especially hydriai but also on volute-kraters, not only black-glazed but also red-figured.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:41&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:41&#34;&gt;40&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The Parthenon inventories record a golden oinochoe in this technique.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:42&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:42&#34;&gt;41&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Brian Shefton rightly observed that the rising popularity of reeding may reflect emulation of Achaemenid metalwork,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:43&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:43&#34;&gt;42&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; but the practice may also follow natural diversification of pattern-work accorded to that most sacred of shapes, the phiale, which can be traced back into the seventh century.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:44&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:44&#34;&gt;43&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The limited evidence for surviving vessels similarly conceived with major relief friezes, like the Derveni krater, begins with the famous fragment of a late fifth-century cast calyx-krater with maenads in Berlin published by Wolfgang Züchner.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:45&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:45&#34;&gt;44&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; To this may be added a few cast statuettes of seated figures that may once have formed parts of kraters like that from Derveni, and an ancient plaster cast from something similar found at the Athenian Agora,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:46&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:46&#34;&gt;45&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; with the important proviso that they may or may not have been quite as elaborate.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:47&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:47&#34;&gt;46&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Doubtless more common, because much smaller, were decorated situlae.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:48&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:48&#34;&gt;47&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Yet even here the preponderance of surviving examples suggests that, in general, only small areas of the body at the handles were decorated, whether with figures or simply with palmettes associated with handle attachments. Situlae with larger friezes wrapping around the (upper) body would appear to have been much less common.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:49&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:49&#34;&gt;48&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; More recently, a spectacular bronze neck-amphora has come to light at Parion in the Troad. The body is decorated in relief with a Dionysiac &lt;em&gt;thiasos&lt;/em&gt;, while large plaques below the handles (their placement recalling hydriai) show Eros.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:50&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:50&#34;&gt;49&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major source of late fifth- and fourth-century evidence must finally be acknowledged: the ceramic vases with figural decoration in relief spread over large surfaces of the body, made in Athenian workshops of the late fifth and fourth centuries. One such is the hydria by the Painter of the Wedding Procession depicting the struggle between Athena and Poseidon for Attica, familiar most recently from Beth Cohen’s marvelous exhibition at the Hermitage in St. Petersburg, &lt;em&gt;The Colors of Clay&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:51&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:51&#34;&gt;50&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In light of the evidence for the rarity of what these ceramic versions appear to be emulating, perhaps we should think of them in terms that include elements of wishful fantasy as well as actual imitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper has argued for a conscious distinction between the generally restrained appearance of Archaic and Classical Greek bronze tableware and the exuberant decoration of contemporary armor. The symposiast and the hoplite are, of course, cultural extremes of one and the same person: a sort of ancient commonplace for Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde. It remains to advance some explanation for this phenomenon. Elaborate armor, I suggest, would seem consciously to emulate the legendary examples starting with the most famous of all, the set made by Hephaistos at the request of Thetis for Achilles in the &lt;em&gt;Iliad&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:52&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:52&#34;&gt;51&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Such literary descriptions continue via the Shield of Herakles described by Pseudo-Hesiod, to those Aeschylus bestowed upon the shield devices carried by the Seven who fought against Thebes.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:53&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:53&#34;&gt;52&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; With these literary descriptions go both surviving examples and representations or derivations of others, not least the Pheidian Shield of Athena Parthenos, that are nothing less than spectacular.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:54&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:54&#34;&gt;53&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Taken together, they make it clear that the Homeric (heroic) vision for going into battle armed with glorious metalwork was very much alive in Archaic and Classical Greece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast to the epic taste for supremely elaborate armor, the Homeric vision for tableware is notably plain. Many vessels are mentioned in the two epics, but only one is described at any length, the Cup of Nestor.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:55&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:55&#34;&gt;54&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Of that cup’s decoration, we learn only that it was beautifully wrought, that it was set with golden nails (rivets), that it had four handles, and that around these handles were fashioned two doves of gold, feeding. In other words, the vessel had a plain body, the decoration was confined to the handles, or near them, and the parts were assembled with rivets. This is precisely the character of bronze vessels of the Archaic and Classical periods that we have seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Archaic and Classical bronze vessels circulated in an intellectual climate in which the act of conferring a highly polished surface to the metal was probably more prized than its elaboration: the very gleam of polished metal rendered it intrinsically godlike. In the end, however, it was perhaps not a simple aesthetic preference for plain bronze vessels that was the driving force among Greek bronze smiths and their customers, nor yet a desire to distinguish the appearance of armor from that of tableware, but rather the forces of raw economic reality. As Demaratus is quoted as saying to Xerxes, it was poverty that was native to Greece: “τῇ Ἑλλάδι πενίη αἰει κοτε συντροφός ἐστι.”&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:56&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:56&#34;&gt;55&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; An Athenian inscription, concerned with commissioning cult statues of Athena and Hephaistos for the Hephaisteion in 421/420 BC, records the price of tin and copper as 230 and 35 drachmae per talent (a talent weighing 25.86 kg or 57 lb.).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:57&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:57&#34;&gt;56&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Put another way, a silver tetradrachm would purchase 448 grams of tin or 2,956 grams of copper. Very approximately, therefore, the cost of the raw materials—i.e., the bullion value—of the Derveni krater, which weighs 40 kilograms (88 lb.) and contains 12 percent tin, would be 45.85 drachmae for the tin and 47.63 for the copper. To this must be added provision for silver elements like the wreaths (possibly as much as 40 drachmae?), for a total of more than 133 drachmae for the materials alone. A second inscription, recording accounts for the Erechtheum, indicates that craftsmen in Late Classical Athens were paid one drachma per day.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:58&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:58&#34;&gt;57&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The estimate reported by Barr-Sharrar that the Derveni krater “could well have taken five or six artisans, working together, more than eighteen months to produce,” &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:59&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:59&#34;&gt;58&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; implies potentially staggering costs for the actual workmanship, something conceivably in the order of 3,000 drachmae. Although this estimate to my mind is greatly exaggerated, it presupposes that the labor costs alone for the Derveni krater could have purchased sufficient silver to make three full-size hydriai of the types mentioned in the Parthenon inventories.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:60&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:60&#34;&gt;59&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Since these labor costs were completely unrecoverable in the frequent emergency situations that precipitated the melting down of metal plate, they must have struck many Greeks as an irresponsible and even profligate use of precious resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The impression that the sheer opulence of the Derveni krater is in some ways conceptually un-Greek may be refined by considering the findspots of the most elaborately decorated bronze vessels of the time. The Berlin krater with maenads was found in the northern Caucasus as part of the “Maikop Treasure.” The Athenian red-figured vases with relief were made largely for export to the Black Sea or Italy; the situlae for the most part come from northern Greece and Thrace, the new neck-amphora came from the Troad, while the Derveni krater itself was inscribed for one Aristouneios who came from Larisa. Common to these regions is a greater depth of wealth than one would find in Greece itself. In such places, the resources could be found to expend enormous, irrevocable sums on tableware for the purpose of display.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;acknowledgments&#34;&gt;Acknowledgments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My warmest thanks to the congress organizers, Jens Daehner, Kenneth Lapatin, and Ambra Spinelli, as well as Jeffrey Spier and Paige-Marie Ketner. For valuable discussions, I thank Günter Kopcke and Andrew Stewart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bibliography&#34;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Aitken 1982&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Aitken, B.T. 1982. “A New Cheekpiece.” &lt;em&gt;AntK&lt;/em&gt; 25, 58–61.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Barr-Sharrar 1982&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Barr-Sharrar, B. 1982. “Macedonian Metal Vases in Perspective: Some Observations on Context and Tradition.” In &lt;em&gt;Macedonia and Greece in Late Classical and Early Hellenistic Times&lt;/em&gt;, edited by B. Barr-Sharrar and E.N. Borza, 123–40. Washington, DC: The National Gallery of Art.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Barr-Sharrar 2000&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Barr-Sharrar, B. 2000. “Some Observations on the Cast Bronze Ovoid Situla.” In &lt;em&gt;Antike Bronzen, Werkstattkreise: Figuren und Geräte. Akten des 14. Internationalen Kongresses für antiken Bronzen&lt;/em&gt;, edited by. R. Thomas, 277–90. Berlin: Gebr. Mann Verlag.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Barr-Sharrar 2008&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Barr-Sharrar, B. 2008. &lt;em&gt;The Derveni Krater: Masterpiece of Classical Greek Metalwork&lt;/em&gt;. Princeton: Princeton University Press.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Basaran 2015&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Basaran, C. 2015. &lt;em&gt;Parion, The Flourishing City of Ancient Troad&lt;/em&gt;. Istanbul: Ege Yayınları.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Bennett et al. 2002&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Bennett, M., A. J. Paul, and M. Iozzo. 2002. &lt;em&gt;Magna Graecia: Greek Art from South Italy and Sicily&lt;/em&gt;. Exh. cat. Cleveland, Cleveland Museum of Art. New York: Hudson Hills Press.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Boardman 2001&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Boardman, J. 2001. &lt;em&gt;Greek Gems and Finger Rings: Early Bronze Age to Late Classical&lt;/em&gt;. New expanded edition. London: Thames and Hudson.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Bol 1989&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Bol, P. C. 1989. &lt;em&gt;Argivische Schilde&lt;/em&gt;. Berlin: Walter de Gruyter.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;von Bothmer 1979&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;von Bothmer, D. 1979. “A Bronze Oinochoe in New York.” In &lt;em&gt;Studies in Classical Art and Archaeology: A Tribute to Peter Heinrich von Blanckenhagen&lt;/em&gt;, ed. G. Kopcke and M. B. Moore, 63–67. Locust Valley (NY): J. J. Augustin.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Buitron-Oliver 1995&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Buitron-Oliver, D. 1995. &lt;em&gt;Douris: A Master-painter of Athenian Red-figure Vases&lt;/em&gt;. Mainz: Philipp von Zabern.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Burn 1991&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Burn, L. 1991. “A Dinoid Volute-Krater by the Meleager Painter: An Attic Vase in the South Italian Manner.” In &lt;em&gt;Greek Vases in the J. Paul Getty Museum, vol. 5,&lt;/em&gt; 107–30. Malibu (CA): J. Paul Getty Museum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Campbell 1988&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Campbell, D. A. 1988. &lt;em&gt;Greek Lyric&lt;/em&gt;, vol. 2. Loeb Classical Library 476. Cambridge (MA): Harvard University Press.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Cohen 2006&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Cohen, B. 2006. &lt;em&gt;The Colors of Clay: Special Techniques in Athenian Vases&lt;/em&gt;. Exh. cat. Los Angeles, J. Paul Getty Museum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Comstock and Vermeule 1971&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Comstock, M. B., and C. Vermeule. 1971. &lt;em&gt;Greek, Etruscan and Roman Bronzes in the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston&lt;/em&gt;. Boston: Museum of Fine Arts.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Filow 1927&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Filow, B. 1927. &lt;em&gt;Die archaische Nekropole von Trebenischte am Ochrida-See&lt;/em&gt;. Berlin: Walter de Gruyter.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Gaunt 2002&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Gaunt, J. 2002. “The Attic Volute-krater.” Ph.D. diss. New York University, Institute of Fine Arts.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Gericke 1970&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Gericke, H. 1970. &lt;em&gt;Gefäßdarstellungen auf griechischen Vasen&lt;/em&gt;. Berlin: Hessling.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Godart 2010&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Godart, L. 2010&lt;em&gt;. L’Italia e il restauro del Magnifico Cratere: Capolavori del Museo Nazionale di Belgrado&lt;/em&gt;. Rome: Presidenza della Repubblica.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Hampe and Simon 1981&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Hampe, R., and E. Simon. 1981. &lt;em&gt;The Birth of Greek Art, from the Mycenaean to the Archaic Period&lt;/em&gt;. New York: Oxford University Press.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Hanina 1970&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Hanina, O. D. 1970. &lt;em&gt;Antychni bronzy z Pishchanoho&lt;/em&gt;. Kiev: Mystetstvo.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Harris 1995&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Harris, D. 1995. &lt;em&gt;Treasures of the Parthenon and Erechtheion&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford: Clarendon Press.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Harrison 1981&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Harrison, E. B. 1981. “Motifs of the City Siege on the Shield of Athena Parthenos.” &lt;em&gt;AJA&lt;/em&gt; 85: 281–317.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Herrmann 1966–79&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Herrmann, H.-V. 1966–79. &lt;em&gt;Die Kessel der orientalisierenden Zeit&lt;/em&gt;. 2 vols. Berlin: Walter de Gruyter.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Hoffmann and Raubitschek 1972&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Hoffmann, H., and A. E. Raubitschek. 1972. &lt;em&gt;Early Cretan Armorers&lt;/em&gt;. Mainz: Philipp von Zabern.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Kopcke 1964&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Kopcke, G. 1964. “Golddekorierte attische Schwarzfirniskeramik des vierten Jahrhunderts v. Chr.” &lt;em&gt;AM&lt;/em&gt; 79: 22–84.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Kraay and Hirmer 1966&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Kraay, C., and M. Hirmer. 1966. &lt;em&gt;Greek Coins&lt;/em&gt;. New York: Harry N. Abrams.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Kunze 1950&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Kunze, E. 1950. &lt;em&gt;Archaische Schildbänder: Ein Beitrag zur frühgriechischen Bildgeschichte und Sagenüberlieferung&lt;/em&gt;. Berlin: Walter de Gruyter.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Lapatin 2001&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Lapatin, K. D. S. 2001. &lt;em&gt;Chryselephantine Statuary in the Ancient Mediterranean World&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford: Oxford University Press.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Lapatin 2015&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Lapatin, K. D. S. 2015. &lt;em&gt;Luxus: The Sumptuous Arts of Greece and Rome&lt;/em&gt;. Los Angeles: J. Paul Getty Museum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Lissi Caronna et al. 1999–2007&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Lissi Caronna, E., C. Sabbione, and L. V. Borrelli, eds. 1999–2007. &lt;em&gt;I pinakes di Locri Epizefiri&lt;/em&gt;. Rome: Società Magna Grecia.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Luschey 1939&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Luschey, H. 1939. &lt;em&gt;Die Phiale.&lt;/em&gt; Bleicherode am Harz: Nieft.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Markoe 1985&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Markoe, G. 1985. &lt;em&gt;Phoenician Bronze and Silver Bowls from Cyprus and the Mediterranean&lt;/em&gt;. Los Angeles and Berkeley: University of California Press.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Mattusch 2014&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Mattusch, C. C. 2014. &lt;em&gt;Enduring Bronze: Ancient Art, Modern Views&lt;/em&gt;. Los Angeles: J. Paul Getty Museum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Merrony 2011&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Merrony, M. 2011. &lt;em&gt;Musée d’art classique de Mougins: la collection famille Levett&lt;/em&gt;. Mougins: Musée d’art classique de Mougins.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Moore 2010&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Moore, M. B. 2010. “Hephaistos Goes Home: An Attic Black-figured Column-krater in the Metropolitan Museum.” &lt;em&gt;MMJ&lt;/em&gt; 45: 21–54.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Neils 1995&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Neils, J. 1995. “The Euthymides Krater from Morgantina,” &lt;em&gt;AJA&lt;/em&gt; 99: 427–44.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Oenbrink 1996&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Oenbrink, W. 1996.“Ein ‘Bild im Bild’-Phänomen: Zur Darstellung figürlich dekorierter Vasen auf bemalten attischen Tongefässen.” &lt;em&gt;Hephaistos&lt;/em&gt; 14: 81–134.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Padgett 2002&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Padgett, J. M. 2002. “A Unique Vase in the Metropolitan Museum of Art.” In &lt;em&gt;Essays in Honor of Dietrich von Bothmer&lt;/em&gt;, eds. A. J. Clark and J. Gaunt, 249–66. Amsterdam: Allard Pierson Museum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Page 1951&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Page, D. L. 1951. &lt;em&gt;The Partheneion, Alcman&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford: Clarendon Press.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pasquier 1999 : Pasquier, A. 1999. “Un cratere-rafraichissoir au Musée du Louvre: du vin frais pour un banquet de luxe.” &lt;em&gt;MonPiot&lt;/em&gt; 78: 5–51.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Pflug 1989&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Pflug, H. 1989. &lt;em&gt;Antike Helme: Antikenmuseum Berlin, Staatliche Museen Preussischer Kulturbesitz zu Gast im Rheinischen Landesmuseum&lt;/em&gt;. Bonn: Römisch-Germanisches Zentralmuseum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Picón et al. 2007&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Picón, C., et al. 2007. &lt;em&gt;Art of the Classical World in the Metropolitan Museum of Art&lt;/em&gt;. New York: Metropolitan Museum of Art; New Haven: Yale University Press.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pruckner 1968 : Pruckner, H. 1968. &lt;em&gt;Die lokrischen Tonreliefs: Beitrag zur Kultgeschichte von Lokroi Epizephyrioi.&lt;/em&gt; Mainz: Philipp von Zabern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Reeder 1976&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Reeder, E. D. 1976. “Ancient Clay Impressions from Greek Metalwork.” &lt;em&gt;Hesperia&lt;/em&gt; 45: 41–66.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Reeder 1999&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Reeder, E. D. 1999. &lt;em&gt;Scythian Gold: Treasures from Ancient Ukraine&lt;/em&gt;. New York: Harry N. Abrams.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Rolley 1982&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Rolley, C. 1982. &lt;em&gt;Les vases de bronze de l’archaïsme recent en Grande-Grèce&lt;/em&gt;. Naples: Centre Jean Bérard.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Rolley 1986&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Rolley, C. 1986. &lt;em&gt;Greek Bronzes&lt;/em&gt;. London: Sotheby’s Publications.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Rolley 2003&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Rolley, C. 2003&lt;em&gt;. La tombe princière de Vix&lt;/em&gt;. Paris: Picard.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Rumpf 1927&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Rumpf, A. 1927. &lt;em&gt;Chalkidische Vasen&lt;/em&gt;. Berlin: Walter de Gruyter.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Shefton 1971&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Shefton, B. 1971. “Persian Gold and Attic Black Glaze: Achaemenid Influences on Attic Pottery of the 5th and 4th Centuries BC.” &lt;em&gt;AAS&lt;/em&gt; 21: 109–11.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Shefton 1994&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Shefton, B. 1994. “The Waldalgesheim Situla: Where Was It Made?” In &lt;em&gt;Festschrift für Otto-Herman Frey zum 65 Geburtstag&lt;/em&gt;, ed. C. Dobiat, 583–93. Marburg: Hitzeroth.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Sichtermann 1966&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Sichtermann, H. 1966. &lt;em&gt;Griechische Vasen in Unteritalien: Aus der Sammlung Jatta in Ruvo&lt;/em&gt;. Tübingen: Wasmuth.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Simon and Hirmer 1976&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Simon, E., and M. Hirmer. 1976. &lt;em&gt;Die griechischen Vasen&lt;/em&gt;. Munich: Hirmer.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Sowder 2009&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Sowder, A. A. 2009. “Greek Bronze Hydriai.” Ph.D. diss. Emory University.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Sparkes and Talcott 1970&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Sparkes, B. A., and L. Talcott. 1970. &lt;em&gt;Black and Plain Pottery of the 6th, 5th, and 4th Centuries B.C&lt;/em&gt;. Athenian Agora 12. Princeton: Princeton University Press.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Sprenger and Bartoloni 1977&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Sprenger, M. and G. Bartoloni. 1977. &lt;em&gt;Die Etrusker: Kunst und Geschichte&lt;/em&gt;. Photography by Max and Albert Hirmer. Munich: Hirmer.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Stibbe 2003&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Stibbe, C. M. 2003. &lt;em&gt;Trebenishte: The Fortunes of an Unusual Excavation&lt;/em&gt;. Rome: L’Erma di Bretschneider.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Vollenweider 1995&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Vollenweider, M.-L. 1995. &lt;em&gt;Camées et Intailles, Les Portraits grecs du Cabinet des médailles&lt;/em&gt;. Catalogue raisonné. Paris: Bibliothèque nationale de France.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Züchner 1938&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Züchner, W. 1938. &lt;em&gt;Der Berliner Mänadenkrater&lt;/em&gt;. Berlin: Walter de Gruyter.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;For the Vix krater, see Rolley 2003, 77–143. For the Derveni krater, see Barr-Sharrar 2008.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;For the tombs at Trebenischte, see Filow 1927; Stibbe 2003. For the “heroon” at Paestum, see Rolley 1982, 26–27. For the finds from Pischane, see Hanina 1970; Reeder 1999, 193–205.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;For the Belgrade krater, see Godart 2010. For the lion hydria from Paestum (Museo Archeologico Nazionale, inv. 49801), see Bennett et al. 2002, 126–29.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;Budapest, Szépmúvészeti Múzeum, inv. LA 18: von Bothmer 1979, plate 21. New York, Metropolitan Museum of Art, inv. 2004.171a–b: Picón et al. 2007, 101, no. 107, 427.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;Sowder 2009.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;Barr-Sharrar 2008, 103.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;London, British Museum, inv. B 148, by Lydos: &lt;em&gt;ABV&lt;/em&gt; 109, no. 29; &lt;em&gt;BAPD&lt;/em&gt; 310175. New York, Metropolitan Museum of Art, inv. 1986.11.12: Padgett 2002; &lt;em&gt;BAPD&lt;/em&gt; 15922. On the series, see also Pasquier 1999. For the Chalcidian examples, see Rumpf 1927, 121–22.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;Markoe 1985, 9.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;Olympia Museum, inv. B 3501: Hampe and Simon 1981, 125–26, figs. 195–96.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;Olympia Museum, inv. B 104: Hampe and Simon 1981, 110, fig. 170b (drawing); and B 4990 (“composite gorgon”): Rolley 1986, 152, fig. 135. Mougins, Musée d’art classique de Mougins, inv. 648: Merrony 2011, 183 and 196, fig. 40.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;J. Paul Getty Museum, inv. 84.AC.11: &lt;em&gt;LIMC&lt;/em&gt; [1992] VI 843, s.v. “Nessos,” no. 97, plate 551; Mattusch 2014, 60–61, fig. 37. For shield bands in general, see Kunze 1950; Bol 1989.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;For elaborately decorated armor, see (for instance) Hoffmann and Raubitschek 1972; Hampe and Simon 1981, 117–28; Pflug 1989 (helmets). For cheekpieces, see Aitken 1982; for a plaster cast in the Akademisches Kunstmuseum, Bonn, see Rolley 1986, 172, fig. 151.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;Herrmann 1966–79.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;Rome, Museo Nazionale di Villa Giulia, from the Barberini tomb, Palestrina: Sprenger and Bartoloni 1977, 81 no. 25 and fig. 25.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34;&gt;For example, Bologna, Museo Civico Archeologico, from the Certosa cemetery: Sprenger and Bartoloni 1977, 125, no. 168 and figs. 168–69.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34;&gt;P Louvre E 3320, line 51. For an edition of this papyrus, see Page 1951; for a translation, Campbell 1988, 360–76.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:18&#34;&gt;Malibu, J. Paul Getty Museum, inv. 87.AE.93: Burn 1991; BAPD 44230.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:18&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:19&#34;&gt;Würzburg, Martin-von-Wagner-Museum, inv. H 4781: *ARV^2^*1338, 1690; Barr-Sharrar 2008, 75, fig. 71; BAPD 217516. Sotheby’s, New York, &lt;em&gt;Antiquities&lt;/em&gt;, June 4, 2009, lot 119.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:19&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:20&#34;&gt;Lapatin 2001, 63–79.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:20&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:21&#34;&gt;Aspasios gem: Rome, Museo Nazionale Romano, Palazzo Massimo alle Terme, inv. 52382: Lapatin 2015, 135, plate 92, 246. Perseus gem: Vollenweider 1995, no. 201.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:21&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:22&#34;&gt;Heraclea: Kraay and Hirmer 1966, 309, nos. 255, 257, 258, plates 88–89. Camarina: Kraay and Hirmer 1966, 294, no. 153, plate 54. Thurium: Kraay and Hirmer 1966, 308–309, nos. 252–54, plates 87–88. Metapontum: Kraay and Hirmer 1966, 307, no. 242, plate 84. Hyele: Kraay and Hirmer 1966, 306, no. 227, plate 80.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:22&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:23&#34;&gt;Taranto: Kraay and Hirmer 1966, 315, no. 313, plate 107. Opuntian Locris: Kraay and Hirmer 1966, 338, no. 465, plate 148. Epirus: Kraay and Hirmer 1966, 339, no. 473, plate 150.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:23&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:24&#34;&gt;These include, Archaic: London, British Museum, inv. 466: Boardman 2001, 181, no. 300 (satyr with kantharos and jug). Ex Ionides: Boardman 2001, 181, no. 302 (youth with jug and kantharos). Athens, Numismatic Museum, Tzivanopoulos Coll. 6: Boardman 2001, 183, no. 340 (satyr with amphora on shoulder, with Cypriot inscription). New York, Metropolitan Museum of Art, inv. 42.11.16 inscribed by Anakles: Boardman 2001, 185, no. 373 (reclining satyr holding out kantharos). Baltimore, Walters Art Museum, inv. 42.461: Boardman 2001, 185, no. 376 (kneeling satyr draws bow, a kantharos beside him). Classical: New York, Metropolitan Museum of Art, inv. 21.88.39: Boardman 2001, 199, fig. 205 and 283, fig. 205 (kantharos between dolphins). St. Petersburg, Hermitage inv. Π.1850-31: Boardman 2001, 288, no. 470 (Chiot amphora). Once Oxford, Arthur Evans: Boardman 2001, 294, no. 613 (calyx krater). Once London market: Boardman 2001, 301, no. 774 (woman with torch and jug).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:24&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:25&#34;&gt;London, British Museum, Gem 465, inv. 1865,0712.106: Boardman 2001, 181, no. 301.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:25&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:26&#34;&gt;Reeded: Berlin, Antikensammlung, Staatliche Museen Preussischer Kulturbesitz, inv. F 159: Boardman 2001, 184, no. 358 (inscribed by Semon; naked girl kneels to fill hydria). Athens, Agora T 3334: Boardman 2001, 286, no. 271, and 235, fig. 271 (clay impression, on one face a calyx-krater).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:26&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:27&#34;&gt;Early Athenian amphora: Kraay and Hirmer 1966, no. 339, plate 114. Chios: Kraay and Hirmer 1966, 357, nos. 605–606, plate 180: Terone: Kraay and Hirmer 1966, 331, no. 401, plate 130. Uncertain Macedonian mint: Kraay and Hirmer 1966, 328, no. 374, plate 123.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:27&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:28&#34;&gt;Kantharoi are commonly depicted on coins, for example: Sicilian Naxos: Kraay and Hirmer 1966, 282, nos. 6, 7, 9, and 12, plates 2–4. Taranto: Kraay and Hirmer 1966, 314–15, nos. 298, 299, and 303, plates 103–105. Mende: Kraay and Hirmer 1966, 331, nos. 403–406, plates 130–31. Maroneia: Kraay and Hirmer 1966, 334, no. 430, plate 139. Thasos: Kraay and Hirmer 1966, 335, no. 438, plate 141. Thebes: Kraay and Hirmer 1966, 337, nos. 449–50, plate 144. Naxos: Kraay and Hirmer 1966, 345–46, nos. 523–24, plate 162.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:28&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:29&#34;&gt;Lamia: Kraay and Hirmer 1966, 339, no. 469, plate 149. Thebes: Kraay and Hirmer 1966, 337, no. 459, plate 145.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:29&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:30&#34;&gt;Ruvo, Museo Jatta, inv. 1494: &lt;em&gt;RVAp&lt;/em&gt;, 35, no. 7; Sichtermann 1966, 35, no. 38, plates 56–59. Barr-Sharrar 2008, 74–100 passim.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:30&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:31&#34;&gt;Prückner 1968; Lissi Caronna 1997–2007.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:31&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:32&#34;&gt;Prückner 1968, plate 4.4.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:32&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:33&#34;&gt;Prückner 1968, plate 31.1.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:33&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:34&#34;&gt;Prückner 1968, plate 7.6.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:34&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:35&#34;&gt;On representations of vases on vases, see Gericke 1970.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:35&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:36&#34;&gt;New York, Metropolitan Museum of Art, inv. 1986.322.1: Buitron-Oliver 1995, plate 11; BAPD 1142.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:36&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:37&#34;&gt;Vienna, Kunsthistorisches Museum, inv. 3710: &lt;em&gt;ARV^2^&lt;/em&gt; 380, 171; Simon and Hirmer 1976, plates 146–47; BAPD 204068.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:37&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:38&#34;&gt;Oenbrink 1996.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:38&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:39&#34;&gt;Metropolitan Museum of Art, inv. 1997.388: Moore 2010.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:39&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:40&#34;&gt;For reeding, see Sparkes and Talcott 1970, 21–22.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:40&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:41&#34;&gt;For black glaze, see Kopcke 1964; for red-figure, notably the volute-krater, New York, Metropolitan Museum of Art, inv. 24.97.25a–b, and discussion, see Gaunt 2002, 305–18; Barr-Sharrar 2008, 92–95 and passim.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:41&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:42&#34;&gt;Harris 1995, 167, no. 293.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:42&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:43&#34;&gt;Shefton 1971.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:43&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:44&#34;&gt;For the shape, see Luschey 1939.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:44&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:45&#34;&gt;Antikensammlung, Staatliche Museen zu Berlin, Preussischer Kulturbesitz, inv. 30622: Züchner 1938; Barr-Sharrar 2008, 140–43, fig. 127 (part).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:45&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:46&#34;&gt;Agora T 2126: Reeder 1976, 52–53, no. 5, plate 6; Barr-Sharrar 2008, 84, fig. 76.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:46&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:47&#34;&gt;Barr-Sharrar 2008, 87–88 and 74–100 passim.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:47&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:48&#34;&gt;On bronze situlae, see Barr-Sharrar 1982, 2000; Shefton 1994.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:48&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:49&#34;&gt;Boston, Museum of Fine Arts, inv. 03.1001: Comstock and Vermeule 1971, 302–303, no. 428.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:49&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:50&#34;&gt;Parion PIC 214 from grave TSM2: Basaran 2015, 163–65 (H. Kasapoglu).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:50&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:51&#34;&gt;St. Petersburg, Hermitage, inv. P 1872.130: Cohen 2006, 339–41, no. 105; BAPD 6988.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:51&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:52&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Iliad&lt;/em&gt; 18.457–616.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:52&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:53&#34;&gt;Hesiod [&lt;em&gt;Scutum&lt;/em&gt;]; Aeschylus, &lt;em&gt;Septem contra Thebas&lt;/em&gt; 375–651.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:53&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:54&#34;&gt;Harrison 1981.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:54&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:55&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Iliad&lt;/em&gt; 11.631–36.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:55&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:56&#34;&gt;Herodotus 7.102.1.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:56&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:57&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;IG&lt;/em&gt; 1^3^ 456–58, no. 457.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:57&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:58&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;IG&lt;/em&gt; 1^3^ 459–76, nos. 474–79.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:58&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:59&#34;&gt;Barr-Sharrar 2008, 103 (quoting conservator Richard Stone and further corroborative conversation with metalworker John Tzelepis).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:59&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:60&#34;&gt;Harris 1995, 153, nos. 215–18, and 158–62, nos. 251–60. Their weights (values) are approximately 1,000 drachmae.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:60&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Iconography of the Sea World on Late Hellenistic Bronze Vessels</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/vessels/27-dedecker/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/vessels/27-dedecker/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The Mediterranean Sea has always captured the imagination of the Greeks, but at the end of the Hellenistic era, their artistic vision and technical knowledge were transferred to the Italian peninsula, where Roman craftsmen created artifacts that surpassed everything before. These craftsmen portrayed deities such as Poseidon, Amphitrite, Triton, Scylla, and Medusa, who lived in the sea, riding creatures like sea horses (hippocampi), sea wolves (&lt;em&gt;ketos&lt;/em&gt;), dolphins, and other real and imaginary marine animals.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Wealthy Romans ate exotic meals off expensive tableware, in solemn settings;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; some of their dishes were metal vessels decorated with reliefs (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 27.1&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The excavations at Pompeii and Herculaneum have lead to the discovery of close to seventeen hundred bronze vessels, which can be categorized in any number of ways. Our interest here is in the iconography on the vertical part of the vessels’ handles. The subjects can be divided into three main groups:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reliefs depicting only vegetal motifs, such as tendrils, sprouts, and leaves.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reliefs depicting Dionysian objects (&lt;em&gt;tympanon&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;crotalon&lt;/em&gt;, mask, &lt;em&gt;thyrsos&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;narthex&lt;/em&gt;), plants (ivy, grapes, poppies, and pomegranates), or animals (panthers, lions, and goats).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reliefs depicting sea life, such as hippocampi, fish, and sea deities.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:6&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sea themes are used particularly to decorate the handles; the lower attachment often ends with a face or figure of Medusa, Skylla, a Tritoness, or Triton, the faces of the latter two usually covered with kelp and seaweed. We will describe several such vessels, followed by a discussion of their significance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-pathetic-triton-7&#34;&gt;A Pathetic Triton&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:7&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first vessel under discussion is a bronze calyx-krater with pedestal in the Museo Archeologico Nazionale, Naples, which was found on May 16, 1873, at Pompeii, in the atrium of the house designated II 2.10 (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 27.2&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:8&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It is high-quality imported ware, dating to the second quarter of the first century BC. Its height is 75.5 centimeters (29 &amp;frac34; in.) including the handles. The krater has two curled handles, decorated at the top with three acanthus leaves. Below, they have oval attachments on each side, with acanthus leaves in low relief covering them. There is an &lt;em&gt;emblema&lt;/em&gt; in between, which is soldered onto the shoulder of the krater. On it, a somber image of Triton can be seen in high relief; one side has black patina, the other side verdigris. A male face with silver-inlaid eyes (now missing) is framed by tousled hair in which are entangled the fishtails of two sea wolves. The ears are shaped like mussels; seaweed trails over the eyebrows; fins stick out behind the jaw. The open lips show copper inlay, displaying teeth inlaid with silver. Under his chin, two sea panthers hold an octopus. Made at the end of the Late Hellenistic period in open-work technique, the handle has several parts soldered on, namely the head of the sea wolf, lips, and fins. On the black-patinated side, one of the two sea wolves is broken.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:9&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-two-faced-triton&#34;&gt;A Two-faced Triton&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The calyx-krater with pedestal, now in Berlin, is from Boscoreale.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:10&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Its height is 64 centimeters (25 &amp;frac14; in.) including the handles. The handle was analyzed in 2001 at the Rathgen Labor using atomic absorption spectrometry; it was found to be 84.7 percent copper, 11.47 percent tin, and less than one percent lead. The alloy was typical for South Italian bronze casting, according to Josef Riederer.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:11&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; These results confirm Andreas Oettel’s earlier supposition that the krater was manufactured in Campania, although Eastern artisans cannot be ruled out.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:12&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Various dates have been proposed for this vessel; Lucia Pirzio Biroli Stefanelli suggested the second half of the first century BC;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:13&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Anna Elisabeth Riz suggested the second quarter of the first century BC;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:14&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Erich Pernice favored a date after the Augustan period.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:15&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The handles of the Boscoreale krater are decorated in low relief, displaying acanthus leaves. It has simple, half-oval attachments. Its uniqueness lies in the fact that Triton is depicted as both male and female on the same vessel in high relief. The male face, unlike the female, is covered with seaweed, like the retreating waves; the female face, by contrast, is smooth and peaceful, like a calm sea. In the wavy hair (which they share), there are several snakes, and the ears are mussel-shaped. Under the chin is an octopus; along the face are two sea wolves with gaping mouths. The high relief is made with the utmost care and skill, its light-and-dark contrasts showing up particularly well among the locks of hair. The whole composition consists of a single block. This artifact shows great technical skill but does not use open-worked surfaces. Because of this, we suggest a date the end of the first century BC to the beginning of the first century AD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-grim-faced-deity&#34;&gt;A Grim-faced Deity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Handle fragments (lower attachment) from a calyx-krater, now in Geneva, were retrieved from Ostia (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 27.3&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:16&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The length of the handle is 9.2 centimeters (3 5/8 in.). It shows a male face in whose tousled hair two serpent heads writhe. The ears are again shaped like mussels, and seaweed clings above the eyebrows; the eyes, once glass or silver, are now lost. The face is covered with kelp; the mouth is slightly open. Two dogs are under his chin, and below that, two dolphins with an octopus between them. As to the iconography, several hypotheses have been advanced. Walther Fol thought it could represent Medusa;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:17&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Waldemar Deonna suggested Scylla;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:18&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and finally Christiane Dunant proposed that it might be a Triton or another sea god.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:19&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The seaweed would be typical for Triton. One is immediately struck by the rather grim expression of the deity. Paired animal figures, like the dog heads and dolphins surrounding an octopus and placed symmetrically, are common motifs (see “The Two-faced Triton” from Boscoreale, above). The workshop was likely in Campania or Capua, or in the East.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:20&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:20&#34;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Our estimated date for this handle fragment is post-Augustan to middle of the first century AD. The three works listed so far are in chronological order, the earliest being the Pompeian krater, followed by the Boscoreale krater, and finally this piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are numerous comparanda for the shape:&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:21&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:21&#34;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; a silver kantharos from the northeast Mediterranean, but without handle, dated between 46 and 15 BC;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:22&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:22&#34;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; a large krater from the Hildesheim treasure (a collection of silver wares of various origins), surely earlier than the middle of the first century AD;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:23&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:23&#34;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and a kantharos from the West Cemetery at Meroë with Greek inscription.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:24&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:24&#34;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Handles formed from two curled rods were common since the Early Hellenistic period.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:25&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:25&#34;&gt;25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tritons-young-and-old&#34;&gt;Tritons, Young and Old&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A silver handle at the J. Paul Getty Museum, which likely once belonged to an askos, shows an older but still very powerful Triton. The length of the handle is 24 centimeters (9 &amp;frac12; in.). His mustache and beard frame his thick-lipped mouth; he has intense large eyes and equine ears.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:26&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:26&#34;&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The pathos in his facial expression is typical of the Hellenistic style. The handle was dated by B. Barr-Sharrar between 100 and 50 BC, the region of production being probably around Tarentum in Magna Graecia.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:27&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:27&#34;&gt;27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our next example, in the Petit Palais, Paris, may have been found near Smyrna. It is of a type similar to the Getty handle, but it has a female torso ending in a long scabrous tail. It wears a double crown of acanthus leaves. Judith Petit considers it a Roman work and connects it to art from Asia Minor.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:28&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:28&#34;&gt;28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting bronze is the Triton and hippocampus statuette group in the Elie Borowski collection.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:29&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:29&#34;&gt;29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Triton is depicted as a muscular youth, with semi-long tousled hair and wearing a loincloth made of three rows of acanthus leaves. The hippocampus is constrained with the crab claws of Triton, his demeanor exuding truculence. The group was made around 180 BC and is considered the work of a Rhodian artist.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:30&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:30&#34;&gt;30&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next significant example of a bronze vessel handle is again in the J. Paul Getty Museum,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:31&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:31&#34;&gt;31&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; formerly part of the Fleischman Collection. It shows a young woman, perhaps a Tritoness or Skylla (depicted without dogs), which lies above an enlarged face of an old Triton. She holds a rudder in her right hand and appears peaceful; her long hair is parted in the middle, and she is wearing a simple crown or a hair band. She is naked save for a skirt made of long acanthus leaves that ends in a curved, hooklike fishtail. Crab claws typical of pereiopods reach out from underneath Triton’s thick hair; his face is covered in seaweed, his mouth is agape, with two dolphins beneath the chin; the eyes and fins along the jaw are made in silver inlay. This is a manifestation of a solemn or philosophical Triton and can be dated from the late first century BC to the early first century AD.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:32&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:32&#34;&gt;32&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another handle belonging to Tassinari’s Pompeian Type B 1222,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:33&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:33&#34;&gt;33&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in the Archaeological Museum in Naples, is from Herculaneum (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 27.4&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:34&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:34&#34;&gt;34&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The length of the handle is decorated in low relief, with a face peering through acanthus leaves, then an unfurling scroll of acanthus leaves from the side, with a bordering bead pattern. The lower attachment, in high relief, bears a mask of a sea god; there are two wings in his tousled hair, with snakes, dogs, and coiled serpents in three sets above. He has mussel ears, silver-encrusted eyes, a seaweed-covered face, an open mouth, inlaid silver teeth, and a chin ending in a knotted serpent’s tail. Below this on the left and right are dolphins holding an octopus in the center with their open mouths.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:35&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:35&#34;&gt;35&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The composition in high relief is an open work and the surface is not continuous; these details are characteristic for the period from the second half of the first century BC to the middle of the first century AD.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:36&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:36&#34;&gt;36&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we have two jugs with large mouths, again Type B 1222 and also in Naples, which were found in Pompeii in 1862.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:37&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:37&#34;&gt;37&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Their height is 41.5 centimeters (16 &amp;frac14; in.). The jugs are of high quality; the body color is verdigris, and the rim has two grooves. The horizontal part of the handle is flanked, left and right, by birds’ heads; in the center of the two attachments is a thumb rest in the form of a curved leaf, originally inlaid with silver. The transverse band consists of three rows of beads, dividing the horizontal and vertical parts. The vertical part of the handle is in low relief with a scroll of twisting leaves on the sides, edged again by a beaded pattern. The lower attachment depicts the face of a sea god; in his tousled hair are two &lt;em&gt;ketoi&lt;/em&gt;, his face is covered with seaweed, and under his chin are two dolphins and an octopus in high relief, with silver inlay in the eyes.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:38&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:38&#34;&gt;38&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The composition of the Triton is entirely closed. This piece comes from the middle of the first century AD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the bigger jugs of Type B 1222 was found in the cubiculum of the Casa dell’Ara Massima in Pompeii; its height is 42.6 centimeters (16 &amp;frac34; in.), including the handles (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 27.5&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:39&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:39&#34;&gt;39&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The jug’s rim has numerous grooves; the body is large, and its bottom consists of several concentric circles in high relief. The top of the handle depicts horizontal bird heads, rather plainly; the thumb rest in the center has thin leaves around it. The transverse band consists of three lines of beaded decoration; as is often the case, the silver inlay is missing. The vertical part of the handle has a cascade of leaves in low relief. The lower attachment is decorated with a vine leaf in the background, and Triton with his free-flowing hair has been placed over it. He has shell ears, but here the ears look more pointy than shell-like. His face is covered with seaweed. The iconographic significance is that the head of Triton now incorporates many Dionysian elements. The craftsmanship is of lower quality in comparison to the previously mentioned works and, again, the silver inlays in the eyes are missing. The composition is entirely closed. The piece looks very much like something mass produced, or made by an apprentice just learning his craft. The date of manufacture is the middle of the first century AD or somewhat later; the piece was probably produced in Alexandria, as indicated by the engraved leaves and the thumb rest with a crown of leaves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still another jug, also belonging to Type B 1222, comes from Pompeii I 9.5, the House of the Orchard (Casa del frutteto).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:40&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:40&#34;&gt;40&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Its height is 37.2 centimeters (14 &amp;frac12; in.) including the handles; the length of the handle alone is 21.5 centimeters (8 &amp;frac12; in.). In line with the previous examples, its transverse band consists of three lines of beads, the silver inlay long ago eroded. The vertical part has a line of leaves in low relief; the surface has lost definition and become quite worn over time. The lower attachment is decorated with a male head in high relief, his wild wavy hair with a &lt;em&gt;taenia&lt;/em&gt; on top with two wings; the forehead is covered with seaweed.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:41&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:41&#34;&gt;41&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The iconographic emphasis here shows once more how Triton appears with Dionysiac elements (e.g., the &lt;em&gt;taenia&lt;/em&gt;), but his expression is severe. The composition is closed. Manufacturing date seems to be the middle of the first century AD or after, probably from a workshop at Alexandria but fashioned after a different model from the previous handle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems hardly coincidental that the sea world that artistically inspired the various maritime themes discussed here reflects the cultural, financial, and political issues affecting the human realm. It tells a story of artisans from the East looking for patrons who could afford what we call Hellenistic craftsmanship (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 27.6&lt;/strong&gt;). Traveling across the Mediterranean to cities like Naples or Capua, artists set up their workshops close to their clients. It is highly probable that these artisans became specialized, becoming what we will now call Triton Masters (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 27.7&lt;/strong&gt;). Most of the more ostentatious pieces were made in the mid-first century BC, like the kraters, in which the deities were shown in their traditional iconographical contexts. Even if we don’t know him by name, the master behind these works is recognizable; take, for instance, the highly detailed mussel-shaped ear of Triton (see figs. 27.2–5, 27.7). Then came a period from the late first century BC, when artifacts are complex open works in high relief, accentuated with silver inlays. This is where the archetypes become more ambiguous. Augustus’s naval victory at Actium in 31 BC became associated with the figure of Triton, and artisans added qualities of Triton to representations of other deities in support of Augustus’s political propaganda (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 27.8&lt;/strong&gt;). This is also the phase when the pathos of Triton is most eloquently expressed. As prosperity increased in the early Imperial period, lifestyles of the upper class became more lavish and elaborate. Higher demand during this phase—around the middle of the first century AD—caused an increased production and combined with the public’s interest in Alexandrian style to stimulate the next notable development in craftsmanship. The masters in charge began making tableware series using standardized techniques.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:42&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:42&#34;&gt;42&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It is also likely that they assigned much of the manufacturing to their apprentices, including many migrants from the East. This would explain why there is such a notable range of quality during this period. The distinctive mussel-ear shape inherited from previous masters devolves into pointed ears; even Triton’s pathos gets lost in the poor execution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, vessels produced during the last quarter of the first century AD feature a union between Triton and Dionysos. In doing so, the Triton Masters take this deity to his next transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;acknowledgments&#34;&gt;Acknowledgments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many thanks are due to S. Tassinari, S. Descamps, C. Pouzadoux, V. Sampaolo, A. Villone, F. Miele, A. Milanesi, G. Albano, D. Salzmann, R. Dylka, and J. Chamay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bibliography&#34;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Andreae 2003&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Andreae, B. 2003. &lt;em&gt;Antike Bildmosaiken.&lt;/em&gt; Mainz: Philipp von Zabern.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Andreae et al. 2002&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Andreae, B., S. Kansteiner, and M. Kunze. 2002. &lt;em&gt;Meeresgott und Seepferd: Ein neuentdecktes Meisterwerk griechischer Bronzekunst aus Jerusalem&lt;/em&gt;. Exh. cat. Stendal, Winckelmann-Museum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Balty 1965&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Balty, J.-Ch. 1965. “Une anse d’aiguière d’époque romaine à incrustation d’argent.” &lt;em&gt;BMusBrux&lt;/em&gt; 37: 13–77.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Barr-Sharrar 1993&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Barr-Sharrar, B. 1993. “A Silver Triton in the Getty Museum.” In &lt;em&gt;Studia Varia from the J. Paul Getty Museum&lt;/em&gt; 1: 99–106. Malibu: J. Paul Getty Museum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Carandini 1977&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Carandini, A. 1977. “Alcune forme bronzee conservate a Pompei e nel Museo Nazionale di Napoli.” In &lt;em&gt;L’Instrumentum domesticum di Ercolano e Pompei nella prima età imperiale&lt;/em&gt;, ed. M. Annecchino et al. (Quaderni di cultura materiale 1), 163–68. Rome: L’Erma di Bretschneider.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Dahy 2005/2006&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Dahy, I. 2005/2006. “La collection de bronzes du Musée de l’Arles et de la Provence antiques: Étude du mobilier issu de découvertes récentes.” Thesis, Université de Provence, Aix–Marseilles III.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;De Decker 2007/2008&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;De Decker, K. 2007/2008. “Une olpé au Musée Hongrois des Beaux-Arts: La cruche de Budapest.” &lt;em&gt;Boreas&lt;/em&gt; 30/31: 73–103.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Deonna 1912&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Deonna, W. 1912. “Bronzes du Musée de Genève.” &lt;em&gt;RA&lt;/em&gt; 1912.2: 32–42.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Di Cresce 1995
Di Cresce, A. 1995. “133 Brocche con imboccatura circolare: B 1240–1260.” Thesis, Università Federico II, Naples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Drexel 1909&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Drexel, F. 1909. “Alexandrinische Silbergefässe der Kaiserzeit.” &lt;em&gt;BJb&lt;/em&gt; 118: 176–235.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Dunant 1967&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Dunant, C. 1967. “Une applique de bronze en relief.” In &lt;em&gt;Gestalt und Geschichte: Festschrift Karl Schefold zu seinem 60. Geburtstag am 26. Januar 1965&lt;/em&gt; (Beihefte zur AK 4), ed. M. Rohde-Liegle, 110–14&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; Bern: Francke.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Dunbabin 2003&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Dunbabin, K. M. D. 2003. &lt;em&gt;The Roman Banquet: Images of Conviviality.&lt;/em&gt; Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Faider-Feytmans 1979&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Faider-Feytmans, G. M. 1979. &lt;em&gt;Les bronzes romains de Belgique&lt;/em&gt;. Mainz: Philipp von Zabern.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Fol 1874&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Fol, W. 1874. &lt;em&gt;Catalogue du Musée Fol: Antiquités&lt;/em&gt;. Vol. 1: &lt;em&gt;Céramique et plastique&lt;/em&gt;. Geneva: H. Georg Cherbulier.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Getty Museum 1994&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;J. Paul Getty Museum. 1994. &lt;em&gt;A Passion for Antiquities: Ancient Art from the Collection of Barbara and Lawrence Fleischman&lt;/em&gt;. Malibu: J. Paul Getty Museum in association with the Cleveland Museum of Art.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Guzzo 1980&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Guzzo, P. G. 1980. “Argenteria da Palmi in ripostiglio del I sec a C.” &lt;em&gt;AttiMGrecia&lt;/em&gt; 18–20 (1977–79): 193–209. Rome: La Società.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Guzzo 2006&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Guzzo, P. G. 2006. &lt;em&gt;Argenti a Pompei&lt;/em&gt;. Verona: Electa Milano.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Mielsch and Niemeyer 2001&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Mielsch, H., and B. Niemeyer. 2001. &lt;em&gt;Römisches Silber aus Ägypten in Berlin&lt;/em&gt;. Winckelmannsprogramm der archäologischen Gesellschaft zu Berlin 139/140. Berlin: Walter de Gruyter.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Nuber 1972&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Nuber, H. U. 1972. &lt;em&gt;Kanne und Griffschale: ihr Gebrauch im täglichen Leben und die Beigabe in Gräbern der römischen Kaiserzeit.&lt;/em&gt; Berlin: de Gruyter.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Oettel, A. 1990&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Oettel, A. 1990. &lt;em&gt;Bronzen aus Boscoreale in Berlin.&lt;/em&gt; Berlin: Antikenmuseum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Oliver 1977&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Oliver, A., Jr. 1977. &lt;em&gt;Silver for the Gods: 800 Years of Greek and Roman Silver&lt;/em&gt; Exh. cat. Toledo (OH), Museum of Art.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Oliver 1980&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Oliver, A., Jr. 1980. “A Set of Ancient Silverware in the Getty Museum.” &lt;em&gt;GettyMusJ&lt;/em&gt; 8: 155–66.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Pernice 1925&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Pernice, E. 1925. &lt;em&gt;Die hellenistische Kunst in Pompeji&lt;/em&gt;. Vol. 4. &lt;em&gt;Gefässe und Geräte aus Bronze.&lt;/em&gt; Berlin and Leipzig: Walter de Gruyter.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Pernice and Winter 1901&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Pernice, E., and F. Winter, eds. 1901. &lt;em&gt;Der Hildesheimer Silberfund.&lt;/em&gt; Berlin: Spemann.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Petit 1980&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Petit, J., 1980. &lt;em&gt;Bronzes antiques de la Collection Dutuit:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Grecs, hellénistiques, romains et de l’Antiquité tardive&lt;/em&gt;. Paris: Musée du Petit Palais.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Pirzio Biroli Stefanelli 1990&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Pirzio Biroli Stefanelli, L. 1990. &lt;em&gt;Il Bronzo dei Romani: Arredo e suppellettile&lt;/em&gt;. Rome: L’Erma di Bretschneider.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Ratković 2005&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Ratković, D. 2005. &lt;em&gt;Roman Bronze Vessels in the Roman Collection of the National Museum in Belgrade&lt;/em&gt;. Belgrade: Narodni Muzej.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Riederer 2001&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Riederer, J. 2001. “Die Berliner Datenbank von Metallanalysen kulturgeschichtlicher Objekte III: Römische Objekte.” &lt;em&gt;Berliner Beiträge zur Archäometrie&lt;/em&gt; 18: 139–259.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Riz 1990&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Riz, A. E. 1990. &lt;em&gt;Bronzegefässe in der römsich-pompejanischen Wandmalerei&lt;/em&gt;. Mainz: Philipp von Zabern.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Sarnataro 1998&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Sarnataro, T. 1998. “138 Paterae.” Thesis, Università Federico II, Naples.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Stefani 2005&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Stefani, G. 2005. &lt;em&gt;Cibi e sapori a Pompei e dintorni&lt;/em&gt;. Exh. cat. Pompei, Antiquarium di Boscoreale. Pompei: Edizioni Flavius.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Tassinari 1975&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Tassinari, S. 1975. “Pot à anse unique: Étude du décor des anses d’un type de récipients en bronze d’Herculanum et de Pompéi.” &lt;em&gt;CronPomp&lt;/em&gt; 1: 160–231.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Tassinari 1993&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Tassinari, S. 1993. &lt;em&gt;Il vasellame bronzeo di Pompei.&lt;/em&gt; 2 vols. Rome: L’Erma di Bretschneider.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Tassinari 2002&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Tassinari, S. 2002. “Observations et propos sur la fabrication des anses de récipients de Pompéi.” In &lt;em&gt;I Bronzi Antichi: Produzione e tecnologia: Atti del XV Congresso Internazionale sui Bronzi Antichi organizzato dall’Università di Udine, sede Gorizia Grado-Aquileia, 22–26 maggio 2001&lt;/em&gt;, ed. A. Giumlia-Mair, 363–69. Montagnac: Monique Mergoil.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Tassinari 2009&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Tassinari, S. 2009. &lt;em&gt;Vasi in bronzo, brocche, askoi, vasi a paniere&lt;/em&gt;. Naples: Electa.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Tassinari 2015&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Tassinari, S. 2015. “De la spécificité typologique du décor des anses: L’exemple de la catégorie des cruches trilobées D.” In &lt;em&gt;New Research on Ancient Bronzes: Acta of the XVIIIth International Congress on Ancient Bronzes&lt;/em&gt;, ed. E. Deschler-Erb and P. Della Casa, 235–39. Zürich: Chronos.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Trofimova 2007&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Trofimova, A., ed. 2007. &lt;em&gt;Greeks on the Black Sea: Ancient Art from the Hermitage&lt;/em&gt;. Exh. cat. J. Paul Getty Museum: Los Angeles.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Andreae 2003,150–53, 270–72.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;Dunbabin 2003, 55, fig. 26.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;De Decker 2007/2008, 93, plate 22.16; Guzzo 2006, 81, no. 8 (Cassetta); 137, no. 168 (Stefani); 140. no. 171 (De Carolis); Stefani 2005, 64, no. 69; Carandini 1977, 166, plate 80.22.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;Tassinari 1975, 175, fig. 7c (Museo Archeologico Nazionale di Napoli [hereafter MANN], inv. 69491).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;Tassinari 1975, 167, fig. 3a (MANN, inv.69488).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;e.g. Balty 1965, 52 no. 25; p. 54, no. 52, plates 6–7; Tassinari 1975, 169, fig. 4d (MANN, inv. 69489); Faider-Feytmans 1979, 177, no. 362; Tassinari 2002, 367, fig. 8; Ratković 2005, 74, no. 21 (MANN, inv. 115565 and 115570).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;LIMC&lt;/em&gt; 8 (1997), 68–85, s.v. “Triton, Tritones” (Icard-Gianolio).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;MANN, inv. 109697. History of the find: MANN Archivio storico, folio 47, no. 1. (I am very grateful for the support I received when using the archive).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;Riz 1990, 38, plate 5.2.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;Berlin, Staatliche Museen, Antikensammlung, inv. Misc. 8850. Boscoreale, K. 23, finding group 1: Oettel 1990, 24.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;Riederer 2001, 177–98. The full results were: Cu 84.7%, Sn 11.47%, Pb 0.8%, Zn 0.002%, Fe 0.13%, Ni 0.11%, Ag 0.08%, Sb 0.02%, As 0,05%, Bi 0.025%, Co 0.005%, Au 0.01%, Cd 0.001%.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;Oettel 1990, 25–26.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;Pirzio Biroli Stefanelli 1990, 253, 284, fig. 240, no. 121.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;Riz 1990, 38, plate 5.2.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;Pernice 1925, 40–41, figs. 50–51, group III.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34;&gt;Geneva, Musée d’Art et d’histoire, inv. MF 1207: Fol 1874, 261, no. 1207.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34;&gt;Fol 1874, 261.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:18&#34;&gt;Deonna 1912, 39.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:18&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:19&#34;&gt;Dunant 1967, 110–14.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:19&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:20&#34;&gt;Riz 1990, 42–48.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:20&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:21&#34;&gt;The typology belongs to Y 1100: see Tassinari 1993, 2: 344–45.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:21&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:22&#34;&gt;Oliver 1980, 159–61, 166, figs. 10–11.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:22&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:23&#34;&gt;Pernice and Winter 1901, 64–65, plate 35.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:23&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:24&#34;&gt;Mielsch and Niemeyer 2001, 3–4, fig. 1.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:24&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:25&#34;&gt;Trofimova 2007, 170–73, nos. 74 and 76, from the Crimea (third century BC). Other comparanda include: Oliver 1977, 48–50, nos. 17–18; Oliver 1977, 64–65, nos. 31–32 (early Hellenistic); Oliver 1977, 100–101, nos. 56–57 (Tivoli hoard, dated mid-first century BC); Oliver 1977, 124–25, nos. 78–79, from a burial at Olbia, dated first century BC; and finally one from Palmi in South Italy, Guzzo 1980, 203, fig. 6, dated first century BC.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:25&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:26&#34;&gt;Los Angeles, J. Paul Getty Museum, inv. 85.AM.163. Barr-Sharrar 1993; cf. Christie’s (New York), &lt;em&gt;Antiquities&lt;/em&gt;, June 16, 2006, lot 158; dated second–first century BC. For an identical pair of Tritons as a vessel handle, see Royal Athena Galleries, &lt;em&gt;Art of the Ancient World&lt;/em&gt; 73 (1997), 10–11, no. 40, from an Alexandrian workshop.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:26&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:27&#34;&gt;Barr-Sharrar 1993, 99–106.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:27&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:28&#34;&gt;Petit 1980, 79–80, no. 25.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:28&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:29&#34;&gt;Andreae et al. 2002&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:29&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:30&#34;&gt;Andreae et al. 2002, 5.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:30&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:31&#34;&gt;Los Angeles, J. Paul Getty Museum, inv. 96.AC.181.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:31&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:32&#34;&gt;Getty Museum 1994, 272–73, no. 138 (Ariel Herrmann).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:32&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:33&#34;&gt;Tassinari 1993, 2:23–39.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:33&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:34&#34;&gt;MANN, inv. 72600.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:34&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:35&#34;&gt;Tassinari 1975, 175, fig. 7g (face); 189, fig. 14c (the upper attachment of the handle).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:35&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:36&#34;&gt;Drexel 1909, 178.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:36&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:37&#34;&gt;MANN, inv. 69492–93, found in Pompeii on September 26, 1862.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:37&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:38&#34;&gt;Tassinari 1975, 175, 224, fig. 7f, fig. 18e (lower attachment); MANN, inv. 69492.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:38&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:39&#34;&gt;Soprintendenza Archeologica di Pompei, inv. 3169, Pompeii VI 16.15 (Casa dell’Ara Massima); Tassinari 1975, 175, figs. 7e and 18b; Tassinari 1993, 1: 179, plate 135.3–4.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:39&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:40&#34;&gt;Soprintendenza Archeologica di Pompei, inv. 8579; Tassinari 1993, 1: 139, plate 135.1–2.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:40&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:41&#34;&gt;Tassinari 1975, 175 figs. 7d and 18c.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:41&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:42&#34;&gt;Nuber 1972.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:42&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Anthropomorphic Vessel in the National Museum of Beirut</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/vessels/28-fani/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/vessels/28-fani/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;A bronze anthropomorphic vessel came onto the art market in Damascus in 1953. It was acquired by the late Émir Maurice Chéhab, then director-general of antiquities in Lebanon, who actively sought artifacts that had been excavated in his country and subsequently smuggled into Syria for sale. The vessel (inv. 25422) currently is on display at the National Museum of Beirut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Beirut vessel has been discussed in the writings of Frances F. Jones and Valérie Marti-Clercx. Jones compares it to a bronze vessel that the Princeton University Museum acquired in the late 1980s. The bust is one of a group of Roman representations of young men, some of whom wear a &lt;em&gt;nebris&lt;/em&gt; (fawn skin) over their shoulders and a few of whom wear a torque with a pendant around their necks.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In her thesis, Marti-Clercx provides a typology of these vessels.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The bust in the National Museum of Beirut was cast from the same mold as three others: one of unknown provenance conserved in the Princeton University Art Museum;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; one in the Louvre;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and one in Sozopol, Bulgaria.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the object’s location was unknown to these scholars, neither of them had access to the vessel’s complete documentation. This paper investigates the crescent pendant motif and the bead molding, which provide clues as to the date and place of casting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;description&#34;&gt;Description&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Bust&lt;/em&gt;. The elongated and narrow face, depicted off-center, possesses rough facial features (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 28.1&lt;/strong&gt;). The prominent nose is rather geometric, with sharp edges, an effect formed by a chisel. The nostrils are subtly incised. The asymmetrical arches of the eyebrows reach the temples. The heavy lids of the small almond-shaped eyes are deeply incised to give them greater emphasis. Lines of incision also mark the eyelashes and eyebrows. The latter seem quite restrained and this accentuates the curved lines of this area of the face. The whites of the eyes show the remains of a different material, probably silver or paste. The thin-lipped mouth seems to have a faint smile and it is the same width as the nose. A gentle rounded curve constitutes the chin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The head of the figure, which is raised slightly to the right, is crowned by a thick cap of hair composed of short, defined locks that hide the forehead, the ears, and the nape of the neck. They frame the face and give it a distinct presence. Although the locks of hair are irregular in direction, they are all pointed, striated, and more or less the same size. The front locks are in two rows. On the left side, the front row is directed back with only one pointing toward the cheek (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 28.2&lt;/strong&gt;); on the right, only two locks fall toward the back (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 28.3&lt;/strong&gt;). One elevated lock is positioned on either side of the round opening at the crown of the head, indicating where the hinges of the handle would have been. Curls of hair in low relief cover the remaining space around the rim opening (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 28.4&lt;/strong&gt;). Below the crown, the strands gain volume and fall in wavy locks at the back of the neck. They are combed in different directions and untangle at the nape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The young man wears a torque around his thick neck. Suspended from the torque is a crescent-shaped pendant. The crescent is open at the bottom and ornamented with three beads, one at each end and another in the middle, just at the level of the ribbed ring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shoulders and chest are roughly modeled, with the lower edge cut straight and delimited by a bead molding. The upper arms of the figure lie flush against the body. They are lightly indicated at the front.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The figure is draped in a &lt;em&gt;nebris&lt;/em&gt;, the diagonal folds of which gather on the left shoulder, baring the right shoulder and nipple. One or two pairs of hooves fall across his chest and back, and rest near one another. The folds at front and back are almost identical and are decorated with hatching suggesting the texture of the fur. The right nipple is defined by an incised circle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Vessel&lt;/em&gt;. The 1980s reproduction of a photo from the 1950s shows not only a circular pedestal foot, but also a spout affixed to the top the head. This hexagonal faceted spout has thick molding at the base and a curved rim decorated with a bead molding at the top (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 28.5&lt;/strong&gt;). A zoomorphic (lion?) handle was attached at the back. The pedestal foot and the spout are now detached from the bust and their present location is unknown. On the vessel currently displayed in the museum, there is no sign of an attachment for a handle; likewise the opening in the head shows no indication of hinges. The external black layer of the vessel is flaking and corrosion is present at the bottom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;making-the-artifact&#34;&gt;Making the Artifact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Technique&lt;/em&gt;. This bronze vessel was fabricated by indirect casting, using the lost-wax method. The bead molding at the lower part of the bust was added in wax to the model. It varies in thickness from 0.5–1 centimeter (1/4–3/8 in.). The interior and exterior surfaces of the head conform to one another (&lt;strong&gt;figs. 28.6–7&lt;/strong&gt;). The outer part was polished after casting; the inner surface remains rough and uneven due to the movement of the wax during the casting process (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 28.8&lt;/strong&gt;). The deeply undercut strands of hair and eyelashes were detailed in the wax working model. Brushstrokes are visible on the interior of the bust, and chaplet holes are present in the interior of the head and bust. In its current state, the vessel measures 18 centimeters high, 17 centimeters long, and 11 centimeters wide (7 x 6 &amp;frac34; x 4 3/8 in.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hatching technique employed to define the eyebrows and the fur, as well as the whitish coloration left in the eyes, are cold work.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:6&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The footed pedestal and the spout were also fixed after the casting. The former is attested on a few known examples,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:7&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; while the faceted shape of the spout is unusual; it was evidently soldered to the vessel. However, there is a group of anthropomorphic vessels that were cast with a short spout and two handles.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:8&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In addition, oinochoai were commonly cast with a neck ending in a spout and a single handle. One anthropomorphic example was found in Banias (Syria) with a zoomorphic handle resembling the Beirut vessel.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:9&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Iconographical Inspirations&lt;/em&gt;. The young man is characterized by his heavy uncombed hair, hiding his forehead as well as his nape, and crowning his head. This style is common to anthropomorphic vessels that represent a certain type of young man, and was inspired by the hairstyle of Antinous, the deified favorite of the emperor Hadrian. The bust and the tilted face are characteristic of Antinous portraits, but not the facial features and the details on this Beirut vessel.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:10&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Antinous was sometimes portrayed with attributes of the wine god Dionysos, particularly the &lt;em&gt;nebris&lt;/em&gt;, which was worn by the god and by his followers. The &lt;em&gt;nebris&lt;/em&gt; shown on some of these vessels is the only meaningful evidence of a Dionysian affiliation.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:11&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It is depicted like the one associated with Antinous, one hoof falling forward from the shoulder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antinous is also sometimes portrayed with an amulet suspended from a torque around his neck;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:12&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; the torque is unknown as a Dionysian attribute. This type of jewelry is most commonly associated with barbarian tribal people,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:13&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; such as the Celts, Goths, and Thracians. The crescent-shaped amulet is found among artifacts of the latter tribe,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:14&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; but it is not exclusive to them. It is also linked to Eastern deities, as we will now see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;eastern-connections&#34;&gt;Eastern Connections?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Crescent Pendant&lt;/em&gt;. The crescent is an ancient Near Eastern and, later, Hellenistic motif.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:15&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It is the acknowledged symbol of two main deities: the Graeco-Roman Selene/Luna and the Anatolian god Men. In addition to the obvious lunar symbolism, the crescent may also represent the sky, especially when associated with a circular motif, which can be interpreted as the sun. It can also be considered a fertility symbol,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:16&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; or the symbol of the Phoenician Goddess Caelestis.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:17&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crescent is attested in both the western and eastern parts of the Roman Empire. In Razgrad (Thrace), a female deity with possible connections to Atargatis or Dea Syria wears the lunar pendant.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:18&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Examples have also been found in the Danube region dating to the second and third centuries AD,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:19&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and in England in a second-century AD hoard.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:20&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:20&#34;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Further east, a goddess in Palmyra wears a prominent crescent;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:21&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:21&#34;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Nabatean deities and humans wear bead necklaces with lunar pendants;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:22&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:22&#34;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and crescents also feature on funerary stelae in South Syria.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:23&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:23&#34;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Crescents appear in the painted portraits of Roman Egypt, where the amulets have ball-shaped terminals like the one here.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:24&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:24&#34;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Lebanon, crescents with ball-shaped terminals have not yet been attested in jewelry, but some examples were discovered in a spring in the city of Baalbek/Heliopolis as votive standards.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:25&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:25&#34;&gt;25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Children wearing torques with other amulets are known from the Beka’a plain.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:26&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:26&#34;&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the anthropomorphic vessels like the one in the Beirut Museum have been found in the western part of the Roman Empire, and especially in the Rheno-Danubian region. Some scholars, however, do not exclude Alexandria (Egypt) as a center of production.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:27&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:27&#34;&gt;27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bead Molding&lt;/em&gt;. The only other example of large bead molding occurring on anthropomorphic bronze vessels is a ewer with silver inlays. It depicts the head of a woman whose brow is adorned by two rows of beads; a third row is strung across her neck.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:28&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:28&#34;&gt;28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It is part of the Esquiline treasure, consisting mainly of silver artifacts, found in Rome in 1793. The bulk of the treasure has been dated to the fourth or early fifth century AD. The ewer has not been given a precise date within the Roman period,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:29&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:29&#34;&gt;29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; but it seems that it cannot be older than the third century AD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bead moldings appeared on silver vessels by the mid-third century AD&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:30&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:30&#34;&gt;30&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and were common during the fourth to the fifth centuries AD.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:31&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:31&#34;&gt;31&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The punch-and-die technique used on these vessels was different from bronze casting.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:32&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:32&#34;&gt;32&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Silver vessels with cast beads have been found in Nubia, in Tomb 37 of Ballana. They were discovered with objects decorated with depictions of Venus and Isis, and they date from the third to the sixth century AD.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:33&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:33&#34;&gt;33&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The date of the Beirut vessel is probably no earlier than the third century AD, the earliest century in which cast bead molding is attested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This anthropomorphic bronze vessel with its footed pedestal reminds us of Roman portrait busts similarly placed.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:34&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:34&#34;&gt;34&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The production of this type of bronze vessel is concentrated in Germania, Bulgaria, and Egypt.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:35&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:35&#34;&gt;35&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It is plausible that this particular vessel was cast in Egypt because of the cast bead molding and the numerous crescent-shaped pendants depicted there, albeit in portraits. However, I would like to propose an alternative hypothesis, namely that it was cast in a Lebanese workshop. Numerous inscriptions found in a bronze workshop active for many generations in Rhodes indicate that it was founded by a family from Tyre.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:36&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:36&#34;&gt;36&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; During the Roman period, the legate of Syria, Petronius, is known to have ordered a bronze portrait of Caligula from a Sidonian workshop.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:37&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:37&#34;&gt;37&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The site of another workshop has been excavated in Beirut.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:38&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:38&#34;&gt;38&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Thus it is quite possible for a local artisan to have cast this vessel, especially if a mold was available. The artisan of the Beirut vessel appears to have been unfamiliar with some aspects of his subject: for example, the fawn’s hooves are not sculpted accurately. He stressed the eyes by outlining the lid, a feature characteristic of Syro-Lebanese portraits.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:39&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:39&#34;&gt;39&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Finally, the young man’s locks of hair can be compared to a bust of Helios found near Sidon.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:40&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:40&#34;&gt;40&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bibliography&#34;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Almasri 2012&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Almasri, E. 2012. “Nabataean Jewellery and Accessories.” &lt;em&gt;Ancient Near Eastern Studies&lt;/em&gt; 49: 150–75.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Badoud, N. 2010&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Badoud, N. 2010. “Une famille de bronziers originaire de Tyr.” &lt;em&gt;ZPE&lt;/em&gt; 172: 125–143.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Baratte and Painter 1989&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Baratte, F., and K. Painter. 1989. &lt;em&gt;Trésors d’orfèvrerie gallo-romains&lt;/em&gt;. Exh. cat. Paris, Musée du Luxembourg, Paris; Lyon, Musée de la civilization gallo-romaine. Paris: Réunion des musées nationaux.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Baratte et al. 2002&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Baratte, F., J. Lang, S. La Niece, and C. Metzger. 2002. &lt;em&gt;Le trésor de Carthage: Contribution à l’étude de l’orfèvrerie de l’Antiquité tardive&lt;/em&gt;. Paris: Centre National de Recherche Scientifique.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Bernier 1994&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Bernier, J.-F. 1994. “Les divinités lunaires et leurs interactions sous l’Empire Romain.” &lt;em&gt;Tranquillitas: Mélanges en l’honneur de Tran Tam Tinh&lt;/em&gt;, ed. M.-O. Jentel and G. Deschênes-Wagner, 53–63. Québec: Université de Laval.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Cahn and Kaufmann-Heinimann 1984&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Cahn, H. A., and A. Kaufmann-Heinimann. 1984. &lt;em&gt;Der spätrömische Silberschatz von Kaiseraugst&lt;/em&gt;. Derendingen: Habegger.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Colledge 1976&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Colledge, M. A. R. 1976. &lt;em&gt;The Art of Palmyra&lt;/em&gt;. London: Thames and Hudson.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;em&gt;Die Thraker&lt;/em&gt; 2004&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;em&gt;Die Thraker: Das goldene Reich des Orpheus&lt;/em&gt;. Exh. cat. Bonn, Kunst- und Ausstellungshalle der Bundesrepublik Deutschland. Mainz am Rhein: Zabern.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;El-Khouri 2002&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;El-Khouri, L. S. 2002. &lt;em&gt;The Nabataean Terracotta Figurines&lt;/em&gt;. BAR International Series 1034.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Elmasri et al. 2012&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Elmasri, E., F. Alawneh, and F. Bala’awi. 2012. “Nabatean Jewellery and Accessories.” &lt;em&gt;Ancient Near Eastern Studies&lt;/em&gt; 49: 150–75.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Emery 1948&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Emery, W. B. 1948. &lt;em&gt;Nubian Treasure: An Account of the Discoveries at Ballana and Qustul&lt;/em&gt;. London: Methuen and Co.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Fani 2016&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Fani, Z. “Les bronzes de Rimat.” In &lt;em&gt;Greek and Roman Bronzes from the Eastern Mediterranean:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Acta of the XVIIth International Congress on Ancient Bronzes, Izmir (Turkey) 2016&lt;/em&gt;, ed. A. Giumlia Mair and C. C. Mattusch, 209–16. Autun: Editions Mergoil.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Hajjar 1977&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Hajjar, Y. 1977. &lt;em&gt;La triade d’Héliopolis-Baalbek:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Son culte et sa diffusion à travers les textes littéraires et les documents iconographiques et épigraphiques&lt;/em&gt;. Leiden: E. J. Brill.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Jones 1987&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Jones, F. F. 1987. “A Bronze Head-Vase.” &lt;em&gt;Record of the Art Museum, Princeton University&lt;/em&gt; 46: 17–23.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Kazanski and Mastykova 2007&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Kazanski, M., and A. Mastykova. 2007. &lt;em&gt;Tsibilium: La nécropole apsile de Tsibilium (VIIe av. J.-C. –VIIe ap.J.-C.) (Abkhazie, Caucase): L’étude du site&lt;/em&gt;. Vol. 2. BAR International Series 1721.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Lang and Holmes 1983&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Lang, J., and R. Holmes. 1983. “Studies on the Technology of Beaded Rims on Late Roman Silver Vessels.” &lt;em&gt;Britannia&lt;/em&gt; 14: 197–205.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Lazarov 1972&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Lazarov, M. 1972. “Tombes romaines de Sozopol.” &lt;em&gt;Bulletin de l’Institut d’Archéologie Bulgare&lt;/em&gt; 33: 153–58.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Mambella 1999&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Mambella, R. 1999. &lt;em&gt;Le memorie di Antinoo. Romanzo: La rivelazione di un antico mistero&lt;/em&gt;. Florence: Firenze Libri.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Mambella 2008&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Mambella, R. 2008. &lt;em&gt;Antinoo: “Un dio malinconico” nella storia e nell’arte&lt;/em&gt;. Rome: Colombo.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Marti 1996&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Marti, V. 1996. “De l’usage des ‘balsamaires’ anthropomorphes en bronze.” &lt;em&gt;MÉFRA&lt;/em&gt; 108: 979–1000.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Marti-Clercx 1999&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Marti-Clercx, V. 1999. “Les vases anthropomorphes en bronze du monde romain: Recherches sur les ‘balsamaires’.” Thèse de 3ème cycle. Université Paris IV-Sorbonne.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Marti-Clercx and Mille 2002&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Marti-Clercx, V., and B. Mille. 2002.“Nouvelles données sur la répartition des ateliers producteurs des vases anthropomorphes d’époque romaine: la nature peut-elle determiner la provenance?” In &lt;em&gt;I Bronzi Antichi: Produzione e tecnologia, Atti del XV Congresso Internazionale sui Bronzi Antichi, Gorizio Grado-Aquileia, 22–26 maggio 2001&lt;/em&gt;, ed. Alessandra Giumlia-Mair, 385–92. Montagnac: M. Mergoil.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Mustata 2010&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Mustata, S. 2010. “The Roman Anthropomorphic Bronze Vessel from Stramba (Turceni, Gorj County): Typological, Functional and Chronological Aspects.” &lt;em&gt;Muzeul Olteniei Craiova: Oltenia: Studii si communicari: Arheologie-Istori&lt;/em&gt; 17: 51–56.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Nenova-Merdjanova 1995&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Nenova-Merdjanova, R. 1995. “Typology and Chronology of the Bronze Vessels Used in the Palaestra and in the Baths from the Roman Provinces Thrace and Moesia.” In &lt;em&gt;Acta of the 12th International Congress on Ancient Bronzes, Nijmegen 1–4 June 1992&lt;/em&gt;, ed. S. T. A. M. Mols, 51–58. Nijmegen: Provincial Museum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Painter 1977&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Painter, K. S. 1977. &lt;em&gt;The Mildenhall Treasure&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Roman Silver from East Anglia&lt;/em&gt;. London: British Museum Publications.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Radnóti 1938&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Radnóti, A. 1938. &lt;em&gt;Die römischen Bronzegefässe von Pannonien&lt;/em&gt;. Budapest: Institut für Münzkunde und Archäologie der P. Pázmány-Universität; Leipzig: Harrassowitz.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;De Ridder 1905&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;De Ridder, A. 1905. &lt;em&gt;Collection de Clercq.&lt;/em&gt; Vol. 3: &lt;em&gt;Les bronzes&lt;/em&gt;. Paris: E. Leroux.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;De Ridder 1915&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;De Ridder, A. 1915. &lt;em&gt;Les bronzes antiques du Louvre.&lt;/em&gt; Vol. 2: &lt;em&gt;Les instruments&lt;/em&gt;. Paris: E. Leroux.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Ronzevalle 1934&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Ronzevalle, S. 1934. “Notes et études d’archéologie orientale: Le prétendu ‘char d’Astarté’ (part 2).” &lt;em&gt;Mélanges de l’Université Saint-Joseph&lt;/em&gt; 18: 109–47.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Ronzevalle 1937–38&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Ronzevalle, S. 1937–38. “Notes et études d’archéologie orientale: Jupiter héliopolitain, &lt;em&gt;nova et vetera&lt;/em&gt;.” &lt;em&gt;Mélanges de l’Université Saint-Joseph&lt;/em&gt; 21: 3–162.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Sapelli Ragni 2012&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Sapelli Ragni, M. 2012. &lt;em&gt;Antinoo: Il Fascino della Bellezza&lt;/em&gt;. Milan: Electa.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Sartre-Fauriat 2001&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Sartre-Fauriat, A. 2001. &lt;em&gt;Des tombeaux et des morts: Monuments funéraires, société et culture en Syrie du sud du 1er s. av. J.-C. au VIIe s. apr. J.C.&lt;/em&gt; Beirut: Institut français du Proche-Orient.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Sawaya 2016&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Sawaya, Z. 2016. &lt;em&gt;Les monnaies de JEM 003, JEM 003 et JEM 004 à Jemmayzeh-Beyrouth&lt;/em&gt;. Bulletin d&amp;rsquo;Archéologie et d&amp;rsquo;Architecture Libanaises, Hors-Série XIII. Beirut: Ministère de la culture. Direction générale des antiquités.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Shelton 1981&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Shelton, K. 1981. &lt;em&gt;The Esquiline Treasures&lt;/em&gt;. London: British Museum Press.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Skupińska-Løvset 1999&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Skupińska-Løvset, I. 1999. &lt;em&gt;Portraiture in Roman Syria: A Study in Social and Regional Differentiation within the Art of Portraiture&lt;/em&gt;. Łódź: Wydawnictwo Universytetu Łódkiego.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Tacheva-Hitova 1983&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Tacheva-Hitova, M. 1983. &lt;em&gt;Eastern Cults in Moesia Inferior and Thracia (5th century BC – 4th century AD)&lt;/em&gt;. Leiden: E. J. Brill.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Walker et al. 1997&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Walker S., M. Bierbrier, P. Roberts, and J. Taylor. 1997. &lt;em&gt;Ancient Faces: Mummy Portraits from Roman Egypt&lt;/em&gt;. London: Trustees of the British Museum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Will 1985&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Will, E. 1985. “La déesse au chien de Palmyre.” &lt;em&gt;Syria&lt;/em&gt; 62: 49–55.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Williams and Ogden 1994&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Williams, D., and J. Ogden 1994. &lt;em&gt;Greek Gold: Jewellery of the Classical World&lt;/em&gt;. New York: Harry N. Abrams.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Jones 1987.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;Marti-Clercx 1999, 71–72, 151.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;Jones 1987, 17–18.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;De Ridder 1915, 130, plate 103, no. 2943.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;Lazarov 1972, 154–55.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;I am grateful to Iskra Karniš Vidovič and Azza Ali Aquil for their useful remarks.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;Marti-Clercx 1999, examples Nebr I.2 and Nebr III.6.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;Radnóti 1938, plate 55, fig. 2; Jones 1987, 23; Marti 1996, 981–82, 988; Marti-Clercx 1999, 172, 192, 194; Marti-Clercx and Mille 2002, 385–86.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;De Ridder 1905, 192, plate 45, no. 278. There are other numerous examples of plastic &lt;em&gt;oinochoai&lt;/em&gt;; see De Ridder 1915, 131–32, plate 104, nos. 2955–56.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;Mambella 2008, 150, 152, 159, 195, figs. 134–35, 139, 184; Sapelli Ragni 2012, 65. However, we cannot systematically identify the young men so depicted as Antinous. Rather, these are elements inspired by his portraits. See Jones 1987, 17; Nenova-Merdjanova 1995, 55; Marti 1996, 992; Marti-Clercx 1999, 62–64, 79–81, 190; Marti-Clercx and Mille 2002, 385; Mustata 2010, 52;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;Mambella 2008, 181, figs. 41, 58, 75; Sapelli Ragni 2012, 69, 75, 116–18.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;Mambella 2008, fig. 139.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;Williams and Ogden 1994, 137.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;Tacheva-Hitova 1983, 253– 54, 257; Kazanski and Mastykova 2007, 22.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;Colledge 1976, 212–13; Bernier 1994; Elmasri et al. 2012, 162.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34;&gt;Ronzevalle 1934, 109–20, 129–32, 136–40; Bernier 1994, 58–59; Walker et al. 1997, 164.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34;&gt;Bernier 1994, 58–59.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:18&#34;&gt;Tacheva-Hitova 1983, 253, 261–63; &lt;em&gt;Die Thraker&lt;/em&gt; 2004, 329, no. 302c (identified with the mother goddess).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:18&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:19&#34;&gt;Kazanski and Mastykova 2007, 22.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:19&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:20&#34;&gt;Walker et al. 1997, 164.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:20&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:21&#34;&gt;Colledge 1976, fig. 38; Will 1985, fig. 1.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:21&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:22&#34;&gt;El-Khouri 2002, 163–65; Elmasri et al. 2012, 154–56, 162, 171, figs. 1–2.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:22&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:23&#34;&gt;Sartre-Fauriat 2001, 247–48, 260–61.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:23&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:24&#34;&gt;Walker et al. 1997, 43–46, nos. 17–19; 87–88, no. 77; 163–65. We can also add: an anthropomorphic vase depicting a boy whose neck is adorned with a lunula (190, no. 257); and a bronze bust-vessel (192–93, no. 262).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:24&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:25&#34;&gt;Ronzevalle 1937–38, 129–32; Hajjar 1977, 131–36, plates 39–40.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:25&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:26&#34;&gt;Ronzevalle 1937–38, 75–76, plates 19, no. 2; 20 no. 3; 23 no. 11.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:26&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:27&#34;&gt;Jones 1987, 18; Marti-Clercx 1999, 158, 165–67, 194; Mustata 2010, 52.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:27&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:28&#34;&gt;Shelton 1981, 84, no. 18, plate 32. I am grateful to François Baratte for this reference as well as for the Nubian one.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:28&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:29&#34;&gt;Shelton 1981, 22, 41, 44, 50, 53–55.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:29&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:30&#34;&gt;Baratte and Painter 1989, 123, 127, 132–33.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:30&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:31&#34;&gt;Painter 1977, 12–14; Cahn and Kaufmann-Heinimann 1984, 190–91, 283; Baratte et al. 2002, 20, 28.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:31&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:32&#34;&gt;Lang and Holmes 1983, 201–205.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:32&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:33&#34;&gt;Emery 1948, 33, 58–60, plates 44, 46.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:33&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:34&#34;&gt;Mambella 2008, fig. 160, no. 15.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:34&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:35&#34;&gt;Marti-Clercx 1999, 164.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:35&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:36&#34;&gt;Badoud 2010.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:36&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:37&#34;&gt;Skupińska-Løvset 1999, 28.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:37&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:38&#34;&gt;Discovered during a rescue excavation, it is still under study. Sawaya 2016, 12.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:38&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:39&#34;&gt;Skupińska-Løvset 1999, 91.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:39&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:40&#34;&gt;Fani 2016, 211.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:40&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hellenistic, Roman and Byzantine Influence in the Consolidation of Fatimid Metalware</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/vessels/29-lester/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/vessels/29-lester/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until recently, the availability of Early Islamic metal vessels was limited to individual pieces in museums and private collections, and the scholarship were always generalized, with very limited information in regard to typology.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Metal articles from the early centuries of Islam within the Syrian-Egyptian region are even less common, as Iran and Central Asia attracted the greater portion of attention from researchers.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fatimid dynasty&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; is famous for its decorative arts, which have stimulated considerable scholarly interest, and several publications have been dedicated to the subject.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Studies of Fatimid metalware, however, were based upon a small number of vessels from a few collections.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The situation has entirely changed over the last twenty years with the discovery in Israel of two major hoards. The first was uncovered in Caesarea in 1995 and included 136 metal articles together with glass and ceramic vessels.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:6&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The second cache was found in 1998 in Tiberias and included 660 metal vessels along with a great deal of production waste.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:7&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hoard from Caesarea was discovered in the southeastern part of the city, in the area of the Temple platform, which was the city’s cultural center from Roman times up to the Crusader period. The hoard was found in a cavity near a staircase leading to the Temple platform area and included 136 metal articles, 15 vessels made of clay, and 13 glass articles. The group of metal vessels was composed of lampstands, saucepans, ladles, basins, ewers, round boxes, buckets, braziers, incense burners, and individual handles and feet used to support other vessels. A few of the vessels are splendidly decorated and very well made, while others are much simpler, testifying to a variety of clients. The hoard probably belonged to a merchant who traded in metal and other vessels originating from Palestine, Syria, and Egypt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cache from Tiberias was found during the salvage excavation of a dwelling area, within a private house. The vessels were hidden in three large pithoi, two of which were buried under the floor, and the third, the largest, was concealed behind a wall built specially for this purpose. The pithoi included about 660 vessels along with about 100 kilograms (220 lb.) of production waste. The vessels were very similar to those found in Caesarea, while also including parts of articles that had been serially produced, such as rims and necks of bell-shaped bottles, handles and hinges of buckets, legs to support trays, handles for bowls and cauldrons, and so forth. Working tools such as scissors, molds for sand-casting, and an anvil were also uncovered. The walls and floors of the building, comprising two rooms and a courtyard, were encrusted with flecks of base metal, resulting from the extended use of a lathe to polish and decorate the vessels. All these facts confirm that the location served as a workshop. It was most probably active between the end of the tenth century and about AD 1072, when Turkoman tribes invaded Palestine, establishing their base near Tiberias.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:8&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper focuses on a few types of vessels—lampstands, saucepans, braziers, and feet and handles of vessels—in order to follow their morphological consolidation up to the Fatimid period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lampstands&#34;&gt;Lampstands&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fatimid lampstands are typically composed of three parts: a tripod base, a shaft, and a tray (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 29.1&lt;/strong&gt;). The shaft is designed to fit into the central socket of the base; the bottom part of the tray was soldered to the shaft. The lampstands are characterized by a stylistic continuity between the base and the shaft; thus a base with a round body was fitted to a round shaft and a polygonal base supported a polygonal shaft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fatimid lampstand is the outcome of a long process of adaption, beginning in the Persian period during the late sixth–fifth century BC. The earliest example is a lampstand with three sharply bent legs with cloven hooves, and a long fluted shaft with a bowl attached on the top. Three palmettes or ivy leafs emerge between the legs.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:9&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This tradition continues to the early Imperial period (first–third century AD), with lampstands characterized by ivy leaf design between the legs, and a krater-shaped top (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 29.2a&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:10&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In parallel, during the first century AD, we find another subtype of lampstand, with a circular plate that rests on the legs (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 29.2b&lt;/strong&gt;). The decoration of the plate consists of ovolo and other moldings.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:11&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; A lampstand of the same type is dated between the second and third centuries AD, however the plate has become convex with engraved decoration.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:12&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, during the fifth and sixth centuries AD, the morphology of the lampstand changes. The round horizontal plate transforms into a tent-shaped canopy, with the protruding leaf motif combined amid the legs. The shaft has two variations. One is a solid, hexagonal form with bulges at the edges;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:13&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; the other is baluster in shape composed of spherical balls soldered together.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:14&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; On the upper part of the lampstand, the bowl was modified into a circular tray, sometimes with a central spike on which a metal lamp was placed.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:15&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These versions of lampstands continue during the Fatimid period, but the tripod base becomes semi-spherical or polygonal in shape; the shaft is massive and heavy; and the small upper tray becomes much larger, being flat with a round rim and, in most cases, without an elevated frame. The base, with a round canopy, extends over the upper part of the feet so that the thigh disappears and the base becomes trapezoidal in shape. The shaft is composed of three parts: two balusters flanking the central main part, which is either round in section decorated on the lathe with pairs of fluted circles, or decorated with patterns of lozenges or other shapes. The stylistic identity between the base and the shaft creates sets of matching round bases with round shafts, and polygonal decorated bases and shafts. The tray, seen in profile, is a thin band: it is usually a single round flat surface soldered to the top of the shaft. It rarely bears compatible decorative ornament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The typological considerations also include the physical perception of sizes, from the largest (diam. 31.3 cm or 12 3/8 in.) and highest (48.2 cm or 19 in.) to a miniature lampstand with a diameter of just 6.8 centimeters (2 &amp;frac34; in.) at the base with a height of 11 centimeters (4 3/8 in.). The miniature lampstand is in line with the stylistic characteristics of the group and has a round base with a round shaft. A prototype for the miniature circular lampstand can be seen in the collection of the British Museum, and is of Egyptian origin, dated from the sixth to the seventh century AD.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:16&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of the morphological differences, the production techniques did not change over the centuries. The base and the shaft were produced using the lost wax technique, and the tray was probably cast in a stone mold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;saucepans-measuring-vessels&#34;&gt;Saucepans/Measuring Vessels&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saucepans of various sizes were found at both Caesarea and Tiberias. They are trapezoidal in section with an everted rim and a long handle with a clover-shaped termination or a loop for suspension (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 29.3&lt;/strong&gt;). They continue a tradition of saucepans from the first century AD, such as vessels found at Pompeii, dated to the first century AD, which have a convex body with a splayed rim and a long handle (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 29.4&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:17&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; They continue to circulate during the second and third centuries, for example in Egypt.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:18&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These vessels have also been identified as ladles for serving food. John W. Hayes defined the vessel as a saucepan (&lt;em&gt;trulla&lt;/em&gt;) and was not certain whether it was Roman or Islamic in origin.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:19&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Géza Fehérvari and Elias Khamis recognized it as a dipper.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:20&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:20&#34;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Some of the vessels are decorated with inscriptions and tendrils. One article from Caesarea bears an inscription on its base لصاحبه برکة (blessing to its owner). Thus, when it was not in use, it was hung on the wall with the inscription praising the owner facing outward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These saucepans were displayed at an exhibition at the Hecht Museum in Haifa, about seventeen years ago, where Palestinian women identified the article as a measuring vessel called a &lt;em&gt;Ṣaʻ&lt;/em&gt; (صاع.). Based upon this correlation, I measured the capacity of the vessels in order to determine if their volume is compatible with traditional Islamic measures. I included all the saucepans from Caesarea and one from Tiberias. Two vessels hold 4 liters, one 3.7 liters, and a smaller one 2.2 liters. These measurements correlate with the religious Islamic term &lt;em&gt;Ṣaʻ&lt;/em&gt; or saa’h (صاع), which was used for a measure for grain of about 4.2 liters. The saa’h is connected with one of the commandments of Islam requiring a person to donate a measure of wheat or barley to the poor. It was issued by the Prophet Muhammad during the second year of the Hijra, as part of the ceremonies of I’d al-Fiter (Eid), the festival following the fast during the month of Ramadan.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:21&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:21&#34;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, S. D. Goitein, in his comprehensive work about the Jewish communities in the Mediterranean basin based upon the documents found at the Geniza of the Ibn-Ezra synagogue at Fustat, discusses the private home and its customs. He mentions that “a small vessel of fixed measurement and durable material such as marble was attached to the jar which enabled the housewife to control the consumption.”&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:22&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:22&#34;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The combination of the vessel, its capacity, and the description by Goitein, together with the identification by contemporary Palestinian women, provide a firm base to confirm that the vessel was used as a measuring cup for grain, rather than as a saucepan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This type of vessel is known in the eastern part of the Islamic world, appearing in miniatures from the sixteenth century. A miniature from an album depicts a nomad’s camp with food cooking in a casserole and a ladle alongside.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:23&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:23&#34;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Another miniature from the manuscript of the &lt;em&gt;Hamsa&lt;/em&gt; of Nizami, shows preparations for a banquet, with a servant holding a ladle and filling a dish from a cauldron.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:24&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:24&#34;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;braziers&#34;&gt;Braziers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Braziers are known in two versions, square and round. Cooking in both types is based upon the heat reflected from the coals inside the vessel. The square type was used for grilling meat on skewers. It consolidated under Roman influence, as seen in a square brazier that originated in Pompeii, dated to the first century AD. (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 29.5a&lt;/strong&gt;). Other examples are dated to the Umayyad period, prior to AD 750, and to the Mamluk period in the second half of the thirteenth century.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:25&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:25&#34;&gt;25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This type of brazier was used during social events such as outings, as can be seen from a miniature in a manuscript of Galen, dated to the middle of the thirteenth century, and a manuscript of the &lt;em&gt;Hamsa&lt;/em&gt; by Nizami, from Tabriz in Persia, dated to the middle of the sixteenth century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second type of brazier is round with a base and an upper concave receptacle for coals. Such ceramic braziers are known from the Etruscan period (seventh–sixth century BC). They are characterized by a round container with a thickened rim, triangular in section, decorated in relief with animals walking in procession. According to Lisa Pieraccini, they were used as offerings to the dead within family tombs.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:26&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:26&#34;&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A related version, made of clay, from the Hellenistic period was found in Palestine. The shape is based on a high cylindrical container in which the coals were kept and an upper bowl with three massive handles to support the vessel on top. It was used in private homes both as a hearth and for cooking.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:27&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:27&#34;&gt;27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; A subtype of it is known from the Fatimid period. It appears in different sizes from the very large to the very small. The largest are supported by four feet with spherical extensions that secure the container in place (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 29.5b&lt;/strong&gt;). Smaller versions maintain the idea of a sunken base for the coals, but the square frame is diminished and only a bowl with a broad rim to support the pot remained. It is raised above the floor by three feet that were soldered to the base. The smallest version has an inner diameter of just 10.5 centimeters (4 in.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems that these braziers continue a tradition that originated in Etruria and appeared again during the Hellenistic period. Such braziers are not known from the Roman and Byzantine periods. It may be that braziers have not been identified as such or that they were not popular during these periods; but the typological concept somehow survived and it reappears during the Fatimid period. A set including four braziers of different sizes is part of the hoard from Caesarea. The largest brazier is 39 centimeters (15 3/8 in.) high with a diameter of 26 centimeters (10 &amp;frac14; in.). A large bag-shaped container of similar size is part of the Caesarea hoard. The cache from Tiberias includes eight braziers. They all have signs of soldered feet on the base. One of them has traces of a cylindrical receptacle in its center, which resulted in researchers misidentifying the group as candlesticks.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:28&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:28&#34;&gt;28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The square brazier was far more popular and, as mentioned above, was used during social events such as outings. The round brazier was used for slow cooking; since it remained in the home, it does not appear in contemporary documents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both types are still in use today. The square brazier, made of simple hammered tin, is very popular for outdoor events in the Middle East. A subtype of the large brazier is found in traditional Eastern cooking. Today it is made of stainless steel and is heated by a gas canister sufficient for the long slow cooking of fava beans. This was probably the function of the large brazier originating from Caesarea. The smaller ones were to cook beans, rice, and sauces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;feet-and-handles&#34;&gt;Feet and Handles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuous typological adaptation affected not just vessels and cooking articles but also minor items such as feet and handles of vessels. Vessel feet from the Greek, Hellenistic, Roman, and Byzantine periods are based upon the paw- or hoof-shaped leg, which continues with variations into the Islamic period (see &lt;strong&gt;fig. 29.5a&lt;/strong&gt;). For example, a bronze throne leg dated from the sixth to the fourth centuries BC is characterized by its lion-paw shape.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:29&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:29&#34;&gt;29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; A box or cista with the figure of Heracles fighting a snake, now in the British Museum, is supported by three cloven hoof–shaped feet; the box is dated to the late fourth to the third centuries BC. A lampstand with lion’s legs dated to the first century AD is also in London.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:30&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:30&#34;&gt;30&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A base of a lampstand, with three hoof-shaped feet with protruding lion paws, is dated to the Roman period.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:31&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:31&#34;&gt;31&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; A lampstand dated to the sixth–seventh century has three feet in the shape of griffon’s heads.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:32&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:32&#34;&gt;32&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; During the Islamic period, the naturalistic shape was transformed into a symbolic pattern that often only insinuates the original shape. The small feet that were used to raise a vessel above the floor have undergone a change. During the Classical period, they bore a motif of a cloven hoof with a recess on which the vessel rested; now they have became entirely stylized (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 29.6&lt;/strong&gt;), sometimes even being identified as a spike rather than a foot.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:33&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:33&#34;&gt;33&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This reflects the religious ban on the use of figural sculpture and exemplifies its effect on the consolidation of Islamic material culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same effect apparently applied to arch-shaped handles. The tips of the handles change into simple almond-shaped terminations, thus becoming functional rather than decorative (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 29.7a&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:34&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:34&#34;&gt;34&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This is a substantial change from earlier handles, which were decorated on the edges with animals, faces of men, ivy leaves, and fruits (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 29.7b&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper has surveyed typological changes of vessels and other artifacts from the Persian, Hellenistic, Roman, and Byzantine periods, up to the Fatimid period during the eleventh and twelfth centuries, over a period of more than 1,700 years. Four different groups of vessels were dealt with: lampstands, saucepans, braziers, and feet and handles. They were continuously in use and maintained their broad typological outlines while undergoing morphological changes over the years. The most prominent difference between Byzantine lampstands and Fatimid ones is the replacement of the round canopy-shaped base and the replacement of the upper pricket with a large tray. Although they were found at Tiberias, metal lamps during the Islamic period are rare in comparison to the huge quantities of clay lamps that were placed on the metal trays. This is clearly shown in a miniature from &lt;em&gt;Kitab al-Diryāq&lt;/em&gt; (Book of Antidotes) by Pseudo-Galen, dated 1199, in which the writer is presented with a lampstand bearing a lamp made of glazed clay, typical of the Ayyubid-Mamluk period.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:35&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:35&#34;&gt;35&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The saucepans, which we suggest are measuring vessels for grain, became trapezoidal in shape and were sometimes decorated with a band of half palmettes, tendrils, and benefactory inscriptions in Arabic. The square brazier subtype continues a Roman tradition. The round subtype has no known prototypes from the Roman and Byzantine periods, but it remained within the typological repertoire and reappeared during the Fatimid era. It should be mentioned that the major influence within the group of metal vessels is from Egypt, during the Roman and Byzantine periods, where there was an established tradition of metal production. The groups of feet and handles exemplify the fundamental consolidation of Islamic material culture. They refrain from any sculpture-like identity and schematize decorative elements into functional shapes that distance themselves from the prototype. This change most likely occurred during the Abbasid period with the establishment of the Islamic regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bibliography&#34;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Ainé 1870&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Ainé, H. R. 1870. &lt;em&gt;Herculanum et Pompéi: Recueil général des peitures, bronzes, mosaiques, etc&lt;/em&gt;. Vol. 12. Paris: Librairie de Firmin-Didot.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Allan 1985&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Allan, J. W. 1985. “Concave or Convex? The Sources of Jaziran and Syrian Metalwork in the 13th Century.” In &lt;em&gt;The Art of Syria and the Jazīra 1100–1250&lt;/em&gt;, ed. J. Raby, 126–40. Oxford and New York: Oxford University Press.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Baer 1983&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Baer, E. 1983. &lt;em&gt;Metalwork in Medieval Islamic Art&lt;/em&gt;. Albany: State University Press of New York.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Bailey 1996&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Bailey, D. M. 1996. &lt;em&gt;A Catalogue of the Lamps in the British Museum.&lt;/em&gt; Vol. 4: &lt;em&gt;Lamps of Metal and Stone and Lampstands&lt;/em&gt;. London: The Trustees of the British Museum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Bel 1995&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Bel, A. 1995. s.v. “Sā‘.” &lt;em&gt;Encyclopaedia of Islam&lt;/em&gt; 7: 654. 2nd ed. Leiden: Brill.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Bénazeth 2008&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Bénazeth, D. 2008. &lt;em&gt;Catalogue général du Musée copte du Caire&lt;/em&gt;. Vol. 1: &lt;em&gt;Objets en metal&lt;/em&gt;. Cairo: Institut français d’archéologique orientale.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Bijovsky and Berman 2008&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Bijovsky, G., and A. Berman. 2008. “The Coins.” In &lt;em&gt;Tiberias: Excavations in the House of the Bronzes.&lt;/em&gt; Vol. 1: &lt;em&gt;Architecture, Stratigraphy, and Small Finds&lt;/em&gt;, ed. Y. Hirschfeld, and O. Gutfeld, 63–105. Qedem 48. Jerusalem: Hebrew University of Jerusalem.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Bloom 2007&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Bloom, J. M. 2007. &lt;em&gt;Arts of the City Victorious: Islamic Art and Architecture in Fatimid North Africa and Egypt.&lt;/em&gt; New Haven and London: Yale University Press.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Bloom and Blair 1997&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Bloom, J. M., and S. Blair. 1997. &lt;em&gt;Islamic Arts&lt;/em&gt;. London: Phaidon.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Brend 1991&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Brend, B. 1991. &lt;em&gt;Islamic Art&lt;/em&gt;. Cambridge (MA): Harvard University Press.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Canard 1965&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Canard, M. 1965. s.v. “Fātimids.” &lt;em&gt;Encyclopaedia of Islam&lt;/em&gt; 2: 850–52. 2nd ed. Leiden: Brill.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Contadini 1998&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Contadini A. 1998. &lt;em&gt;Fatimid Art at the Victoria and Albert Museum&lt;/em&gt;. London: V&amp;amp;A Publications.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Davidson 1952&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Davidson, G. R. 1952. &lt;em&gt;Corinth.&lt;/em&gt; Vol. 12: &lt;em&gt;The Minor Objects&lt;/em&gt;. Princeton (NJ): The American School of Classical Studies at Athens.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Dayagi-Mendels and Rosenberg 2010&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Dayagi-Mendels, M., and S. Rozenberg. 2010. &lt;em&gt;Chronicles of the Land: Archaeology in the Israel Museum Jerusalem&lt;/em&gt;. Jerusalem: The Israel Museum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Dimand 1944&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Dimand, M. S. 1944. &lt;em&gt;A Handbook of Muhammadan Art&lt;/em&gt;. New York: Hartsdale House.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Enderlein 2003&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Enderlein, V. 2003. &lt;em&gt;Museum of Islamic Art: State Museums of Berlin, Prussian Cultural Property.&lt;/em&gt; Translated by R. H. Barnes. Mainz: Philipp von Zabern.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Ettinghausen 1943&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Ettinghausen, R. 1943. “The Bobrinski ‘Kettle’: Patron and Style of an Islamic Bronze.” &lt;em&gt;Gazette des Beaux Arts&lt;/em&gt; 24: 193–208.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Ettinghausen and Grabar 1987&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Ettinghausen, R., and O. Grabar. 1987. &lt;em&gt;The Art and Architecture of Islam, 650–1250&lt;/em&gt;. Pelican History of Art. Harmondsworth, Middlesex (UK) and New York: Penguin.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Ettinghausen, Grabar, and Jenkins-Madina 2001&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Ettinghausen, R., O. Grabar, and M. Jenkins-Madina. 2001. &lt;em&gt;Islamic Art and Architecture, 650–1250&lt;/em&gt;. 2nd ed. New Haven and London: Yale University Press.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Fehérvari 1976&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Fehérvari, G. 1976. &lt;em&gt;Islamic Metalware of the Eighth to the Fifteenth Century in the Keir Collection.&lt;/em&gt; London: Faber and Faber.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Gil 1983&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Gil, M. 1983. &lt;em&gt;Palestine during the First Muslim Period (634–1099)&lt;/em&gt; (in Hebrew). Tel Aviv: Tel Aviv University and the Ministry of Defense.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Goitein 1983&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Goitein, S. D. 1983. &lt;em&gt;A Mediterranean Society: The Jewish Communities of the Arab World as Portrayed in the Documents of the Cairo Geniza&lt;/em&gt;. Vol. 4, &lt;em&gt;Daily Life&lt;/em&gt;. Berkeley (CA): University of California Press.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Hayes 1984&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Hayes, J. W. 1984. &lt;em&gt;Greek, Roman, and Related Metalware in the Royal Ontario Museum: A Catalogue&lt;/em&gt;. Toronto: Royal Ontario Museum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Hillenbrand, R. 1999&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Hillenbrand, R. 1999. &lt;em&gt;Islamic Art and Architecture.&lt;/em&gt; London: Thames and Hudson.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Institut du monde arabe 1998&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Institut du monde arabe. 1998. &lt;em&gt;Trésors fātimides du Caire.&lt;/em&gt; Exh. cat. Paris: Institut du monde arabe.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Irwin 1997&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Irwin, R. 1997. &lt;em&gt;Islamic Art&lt;/em&gt;. London: Laurence King.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Jones and Mitchell 1976&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Jones, D., and G. Mitchell, eds. 1976. &lt;em&gt;The Arts of Islam&lt;/em&gt;. Exh. cat. London, Hayward Gallery. London: Arts Council of Great Britain.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Khamis 2013&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Khamis, E. 2013. &lt;em&gt;Tiberias: Excavations in the House of the Bronzes&lt;/em&gt;. Vol. 2: &lt;em&gt;The Fatimid Metalwork Hoard from Tiberias&lt;/em&gt;. Qedem 55. Jerusalem: Hebrew University of Jerusalem.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Lester 2011&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Lester, A. 2011. “Typological and Stylistic Aspects of Metalware of the Fatimid Period” (Hebrew with an abstract in English). 2 vols. Ph.D. thesis. University of Haifa.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Lester 2014&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Lester, A. 2014. “Reconsidering Fatimid Metalware.” &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the 8th International Congress on the Archaeology of the Ancient Near East, Warsaw 2012&lt;/em&gt;, ed. Piotr Bieliński et al., 437–54. Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Melikian-Chirvani 1982&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Melikian-Chirvani, A. S. 1982. &lt;em&gt;Islamic Metalwork from the Iranian World: 8th–18th Centuries&lt;/em&gt;. Victoria and Albert Museum Catalogue. London: HMSO.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Pieraccini 2003&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Pieraccini, L. C. 2003. &lt;em&gt;Around the Hearth: Caeretan Cylinder-stamped Braziers&lt;/em&gt;. Rome: L’Erma di Bretschneider.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Rosenthal-Heginbottom 1981&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Rosenthal-Heginbottom, R. 1981. “Notes on Hellenistic Braziers from Tel-Dor.” &lt;em&gt;Qadmoniot&lt;/em&gt; 55/56: 110–11.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Ross 1962&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Ross, M. C. 1962. &lt;em&gt;Catalogue of the Byzantine and Early Medieval Antiquities in the Dumbarton Oaks Collection.&lt;/em&gt; Vol. 1: &lt;em&gt;Metalwork, Ceramics, Glyptics, Painting&lt;/em&gt;. Washington, DC: Dumberton Oaks Research Library and Collection.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Seipel 1998&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Seipel W. 1998. &lt;em&gt;Schätze der Kalifen: Islamische Kunst zur Fatimidenzeit&lt;/em&gt;. Exh. cat. Vienna, Kunsthistorisches Museum&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Tassinari 1993&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Tassinari, S. 1993. &lt;em&gt;Il vasellame bronzeo di Pompei&lt;/em&gt;. 2 vols. Rome: L’Erma di Bretschneider.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Ward 1993&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Ward, R. 1993. &lt;em&gt;Islamic Metalwork&lt;/em&gt;. London: British Museum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Weitzmann and Frazer 1979&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Weitzmann, K., and M. E. Frazer. 1979. &lt;em&gt;Age of Spirituality: Late Antique and Early Christian Art, Third to Seventh Century&lt;/em&gt;. Exh. cat. New York, Metropolitan Museum of Art.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Wulff 1909&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Wulff, O. 1909. &lt;em&gt;Altchristliche und mittelalterliche byzantinische und italienische Bildwerke&lt;/em&gt;. Part 1: &lt;em&gt;Altchristliche Bildwerke&lt;/em&gt;. 2 vols. Berlin: Reimer.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Ettinghausen 1943, fig. 2; Jones and Mitchell 1976, nos. 157, 166; Fehérvari 1976, plates 2, 2a; Brend 1991, fig. 16; Enderlein 2003, 27–28.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;Bloom and Blair 1997, nos. 65–67; Melikian-Chirvani 1982, 7–22; Allan 1983.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;The Fatimid dynasty emerged from North Africa in 909, conquered Egypt in 969, and founded Cairo as its capital. It took its name from Fatima, the daughter of Muhammad, from whom they claimed decent and adopted the Ismaili branch of Shi’ite belief. They subdued and ruled Sicily, Syria, Palestine, Hejaz, and Yemen. The Fatimid rulers established a strong administrative and financial apparatus with extensive revenues arising from taxes, trade, and an influx of gold from the Nubian mines; see Canard 1965.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;Ettinghausen and Grabar 1987, 167–208; Contadini 1998; Institut du monde arab 1998; Ettinghausen, Grabar, and Jenkins-Madina 2001, 187–215; Bloom 2007.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;Fehérvari 1976, 39–54; Baer 1983, 13, fig. 5; Allan 1985; Ward 1993, 60–69; Seipel 1998, 65–72.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;Lester 2011; Lester 2014.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;Khamis 2013.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;Gil 1983, 338; Bijovsky and Berman 2008.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;Bailey 1996, nos. Q3863, Q3864.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;Bailey 1996, nos. Q3873, Q3874, fig. 2a.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;Bailey 1996, nos. Q3870, Q3876.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;Bailey 1996, no. Q3911, pls. 126–27.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;Ross 1962, no. 39.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;Bailey 1996, nos. Q3920, Q3921, pls. 134–5.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;Ross 1962, no. 38; Weitzmann and Frazer 1979, no. 556; Bailey 1996, nos. Q3920, Q3921, plates 134–35.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34;&gt;Bailey 1996, no. Q3912 EA, pl. 134.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34;&gt;Tassinari 1993, 98, no. 8689.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:18&#34;&gt;Wulff 1909, plate LII, nos. 1031–32.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:18&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:19&#34;&gt;Hayes 1984, no. 182.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:19&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:20&#34;&gt;Fehérvari 1976, no. 23; Khamis 2013, 75–76, nos. 356–61.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:20&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:21&#34;&gt;Bel 1995.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:21&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:22&#34;&gt;Goitein 1983, 141.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:22&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:23&#34;&gt;Irwin 1997, fig. 211.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:23&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:24&#34;&gt;Ward 1993, fig. 7.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:24&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:25&#34;&gt;Hillenbrand 1999, fig. 4; Dimand 1944, fig. 90.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:25&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:26&#34;&gt;Pieraccini 2003.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:26&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:27&#34;&gt;Rosenthal-Heginbottom 1981, 110–11.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:27&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:28&#34;&gt;Khamis 2013, 140–47.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:28&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:29&#34;&gt;Dayagi-Mendels and Rozenberg 2010, no. 91.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:29&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:30&#34;&gt;Bailey 1996, no. Q3870, pls. 102, 104.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:30&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:31&#34;&gt;Bénazeth 2008, no. 36.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:31&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:32&#34;&gt;Bailey 1996, no. Q3927 MLA, plate 137.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:32&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:33&#34;&gt;Davidson 1952, 1053, 1054, plate 72.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:33&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:34&#34;&gt;Ainé 1870, 165, plate 84; Hayes 1984, no. 38.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:34&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:35&#34;&gt;Baer 1983, 8, fig. 1.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:35&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>