<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Vessels on </title>
    <link>/vessels/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Vessels on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    
	<atom:link href="/vessels/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Vessels</title>
      <link>/vessels/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vessels/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bronze Vessels from the Acropolis and the Definition of the Athenian Production in Archaic and Early Classical Periods</title>
      <link>/vessels/24-tarditi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vessels/24-tarditi/</guid>
      <description>In the study of Greek bronze vessels of the Archaic period, important comparisons are always offered by the fragments found during the excavations carried out on the Athenian acropolis. Until now, these fragments were known mainly from some incomplete publications of the late nineteenth or early twentieth century.1 To fill this gap, we studied the bronze vessel fragments found on the acropolis more systematically and completely. The results of this research2 make it possible to draw some conclusions about the extent and features of Athenian bronze vessel production during the Archaic and Classical periods.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bronze Vessels and Related *Instrumenta* at Delphi</title>
      <link>/vessels/25-meirano/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vessels/25-meirano/</guid>
      <description>The circumstances under which the École Française d’Athènes conducted the chief excavation of the sanctuary of Delphi are well known: the so-called Grande Fouille represents a foundational page in the history of archaeological excavations in Greece during the nineteenth century. Between 1892 and 1903, French archaeologists brought to light the major part of the site (fig. 25.1), unveiling the ruins of the celebrated monuments described in the literary texts and contributing to the understanding of one of the most famous sanctuaries of the ancient world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Toward the Derveni Krater</title>
      <link>/vessels/26-gaunt/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vessels/26-gaunt/</guid>
      <description>Figure 26.1. Bronze volute-krater from Vix (Burgundy, France). Greek, Laconian, ca. 570 BC. Chatîllon sur Seine, Musée du Pays Chatîllonais, inv. nnn. Image: Cratère de Vix, Musée du Pays Châtillonnais, Trésor de Vix © Mathieu Rabeau, RMN-GP   Figure 26.2. Volute-krater from Derveni. Bronze with silver and copper. Greek, early fourth century BC. Thessaloniki, Archaeological Museum, inv. B1. Image: © Michael Greenhalgh   A simple observation provides the point of departure for this paper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Iconography of the Sea World on Late Hellenistic Bronze Vessels</title>
      <link>/vessels/27-dedecker/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vessels/27-dedecker/</guid>
      <description>The Mediterranean Sea has always captured the imagination of the Greeks, but at the end of the Hellenistic era, their artistic vision and technical knowledge were transferred to the Italian peninsula, where Roman craftsmen created artifacts that surpassed everything before. These craftsmen portrayed deities such as Poseidon, Amphitrite, Triton, Scylla, and Medusa, who lived in the sea, riding creatures like sea horses (hippocampi), sea wolves (ketos), dolphins, and other real and imaginary marine animals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Anthropomorphic Vessel in the National Museum of Beirut</title>
      <link>/vessels/28-fani/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vessels/28-fani/</guid>
      <description>A bronze anthropomorphic vessel came onto the art market in Damascus in 1953. It was acquired by the late Émir Maurice Chéhab, then director general of antiquities in Lebanon, who actively sought artifacts that had been excavated in his country and subsequently smuggled into Syria for sale. The vessel (inv. 25422) currently is on display at the National Museum of Beirut.
The Beirut vessel has been discussed in the writings of Frances F.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hellenistic, Roman, and Byzantine Influence in the Consolidation of Fatimid Metalware</title>
      <link>/vessels/29-lester/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vessels/29-lester/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Until recently, the availability of early Islamic metal vessels was limited to individual pieces in museums and private collections, and the scholarship was always generalized, with very limited information in regard to typology.1 Metal articles from the early centuries of Islam within the Syrian-Egyptian region are even less common, as Iran and Central Asia attracted the greater portion of attention from researchers.2
The Fatimid dynasty3 is famous for its decorative arts, which have stimulated considerable scholarly interest, and several publications have been dedicated to the subject.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>