<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Large-scale-bronzes on </title>
    <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Large-scale-bronzes on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    
	<atom:link href="https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Large-Scale Bronzes</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Bronze Athlete from Ephesos</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/1-plattner-gschwantler-vak/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/1-plattner-gschwantler-vak/</guid>
      <description>1. Archaeological Background and History of the Bronze’s Classification Among the few preserved bronze statues from antiquity, the Athlete from Ephesos is an outstanding case in several respects (fig. 1.1): (1) discovered in the late nineteenth century (1896), it comes from a clear context within its ancient surroundings; (2) to this day, it ranks among the most complex conservation projects ever undertaken, requiring the reassembly of more than 200 fragments; (3) with the discovery of a “twin” statue in the sea near the coast of Croatia exactly 100 years later, it has recently become part of an intriguing case study and an issue for archaeology and art history.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Was the Colossus of Rhodes Cast in Courses or in Large Sections?</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/2-vedder/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/2-vedder/</guid>
      <description>In the argument over where the monumental statue known as the Colossus of Rhodes was located, its casting has hitherto seldom been considered. The statue—made of cast bronze with a height of 70 cubits (30–35 m, or 98–114 ft.)—must have left at least some remnants of its production. Furthermore, these remnants must be discoverable in the city of Rhodes. However, a requirement for recognizing these remnants is knowledge of the casting technique that was used.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bronzes from the Aegean Sea</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/3-koutsouflakis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/3-koutsouflakis/</guid>
      <description>“Thank God for Vesuvius; thank God for shipwrecks.” Bondo Wyszpolski’s comment1 on the exhibition Power and Pathos: Bronze Sculpture of the Hellenistic World at the Getty Museum accurately sums up an art historical reality: bronze artwork of antiquity rarely survived the vicissitudes of history, except by mere chance. The contribution of Pompeii together with a handful of other sites is well known and recognized; the Villa dei Papiri at Herculaneum, for example, with its exquisite bronze portraiture “catapulted the study of bronzes from antiquarian pastime to art historical discipline,”2 presenting an excellent archaeological context in which the Hellenistic art of portraiture could be well appreciated and understood.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Royal Macedonian Portrait Head from the Sea off Kalymnos</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/4-palagia/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/4-palagia/</guid>
      <description>Figure 4.1. Bronze head of a man wearing a kausia, here identified with Philip V of Macedon. Kalymnos Museum, inv. 3901 Image: Olga Palagia   Figure 4.2. Bronze head of a man wearing a kausia. Right profile. Kalymnos Museum, inv. 3901. Image: Daehner and Lapatin 2015, 195   Figure 4.3. Bronze head of a man wearing a kausia. Left profile. Kalymnos Museum, inv. 3901 Image: Olga Palagia   The fine bronze portrait head of a man wearing a kausia (figs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Bronze Head of Arsinoë III in Mantua and the Typology of Ptolemaic Divinization on the Archelaos Relief</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/5-butz/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/5-butz/</guid>
      <description>Ὑπὲρ Πτολεμαίου ἐμοῦ τοῦ Ἐπιφανεστάτου
 The bronze head of Arsinoë III is one of the most important pieces in the Giuseppe Acerbi Collection of the Museo Civico di Palazzo Te in Mantua, a collection assembled when Acerbi was the Austrian consul general in Alexandria between 1826 and 1834 and later given to his hometown of Mantua (fig. 5.1). Even compared with the exceptional quality of the overall collection, which is particularly strong in Late Period, Ptolemaic, and Roman material, this representation of Arsinoë III is singular.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Apollo from Salerno</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/6-pacifico/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/6-pacifico/</guid>
      <description>The bronze head of Apollo found in the waters of the Gulf of Salerno in 1930 still offers an opportunity to discuss the date, casting and production, place of manufacture, and function of the work of art in antiquity.
Laboratory analysis shows that the bronze has percentages of copper (81%), lead (11%), and tin (5.5%) that can be associated with alloys found in the Roman Imperial period.1 The presence of copper was higher in the oldest bronzes (84–92%).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tiberius from Herculaneum</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/7-risser/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/7-risser/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Building on a collaboration to conserve the bronze Apollo from Pompeii,1 the J. Paul Getty Museum partnered with the Museo Archeologico Nazionale di Napoli between 2012 and 2013 to return the larger-than-life-size portrait of Emperor Tiberius (42 BC‒AD 37) from Herculaneum for display (fig. 7.1).2 The statue, which measured 2.4 meters (8 ft.) in height, had been off view for some twenty years, owing to weaknesses in the legs and base.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When a Statue Is Not a Statue</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/8-mattusch/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/8-mattusch/</guid>
      <description>The Piombino Apollo has recently undergone new studies of its production, measurements, alloy, and associated inscriptions (fig. 8.1, left). That statue and the similar Apollo from Pompeii (fig. 8.1, right) were installed side by side for the first time in the exhibition Power and Pathos, which made it possible to compare and contrast the two figures and to raise new questions about their similarities and differences. The Piombino Apollo was discovered underwater and sold at Livorno in 1832; in 1834 it was acquired by the Louvre.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Second-Century Large Bronze Workshop at Gerasa (Jerash, Jordan)</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/abstract-khalil-seigne-weber/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/abstract-khalil-seigne-weber/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Apoxyomenos</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/abstract-mesic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/abstract-mesic/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Bronze Statue of Germanicus from Ameria (Amelia)</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/abstract-pollini/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/abstract-pollini/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Doryphoros in Bronze</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/abstract-schneider/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/abstract-schneider/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Influence of Ancient Bronzes in Cuban Large-Scale Sculptures</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/abstract-toledo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/abstract-toledo/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Abstracts</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/abstracts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/large-scale-bronzes/abstracts/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>