<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The Helenistic East on </title>
    <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-helenistic-east/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in The Helenistic East on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <atom:link href="https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-helenistic-east/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The Influence of East and West on Bronze Objects Found in Central Anatolia</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-helenistic-east/21-paterakis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-helenistic-east/21-paterakis/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper reviews the influences from the East and West on bronzes (copper-tin alloys) found in Anatolia while focusing on the archaeological finds from the site of Kaman-Kalehöyük. Given its location along ancient trade routes, Kaman-Kalehöyük may have served as a conduit for the intraregional exchange of materials and manufacturing technologies. We examine some of these influences and movements as they relate to ancient bronze technology in Anatolia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kaman-Kalehöyük consists of a tell, or mound, 280 meters in diameter and 16 meters high (918 x 52 ft.). It was a rural settlement situated 100 kilometers (62 miles) southeast of Ankara and 3 kilometers (1 &amp;frac14; miles) east of Kaman in Kırşehir province, in Central Anatolia (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 21.1&lt;/strong&gt;). Since excavation commenced in 1986, cultural levels have been traced from the Early Bronze Age (EBA) through the Ottoman period.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The Japanese Institute of Anatolian Archaeology (JIAA) was established near Kaman in 1998 by the Middle East Culture Center in Tokyo. Two new excavations were initiated in 2009: Buklukale to the Northwest and Yassihoyuk to the East.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;early-bronze-age&#34;&gt;Early Bronze Age&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kaman-Kalehöyük excavations have thus far yielded a total of 9,120 catalogued copper and copper-alloy objects, including arrowheads, spearheads, awls, chisels, axes, pins, rings, stamp seals, and fibulae. A few of these objects have undergone compositional analysis. In the middle of the fourth millennium BC, objects were made from arsenical copper in Anatolia and copper, lead, and silver were mined in the Troad.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The earliest instance of bronze in Anatolia dates from the early third millennium BC (EBA). The sources of tin in Bronze Age Turkey have yet to be located; if small deposits of tin did exist in northwest Anatolia, they were soon exhausted.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Instead, throughout the Bronze Age, the Anatolians traded their plentiful silver for tin, derived most likely from Afghanistan. In the third millennium BC, pure copper, bronze, and arsenical copper were all being used in Anatolia, though bronze was more common in the Troad than in Central Anatolia.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; By the second millennium BC (MBA), arsenical copper was still more common that bronze in Anatolia while bronze artifacts were more prevalent at Kanesh-Kültepe in Central Anatolia.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:6&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The development of copper-alloy metallurgy followed similar paths in Anatolia and Mesopotamia throughout the Bronze Age, with the practice of interring bronze instead of arsenical copper objects in elite burials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;middle-bronze-age&#34;&gt;Middle Bronze Age&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bronze working in the Assyrian Colony period is examined starting with Kanesh-Kültepe, located 192 kilometers (120 miles) southeast of Kaman-Kalehöyük. Kanesh-Kültepe was the capital of the kingdom of Kanesh and during the Assyrian Colony period in the MBA served as the administrative and distribution center of the colony network in Anatolia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2004, X-ray fluorescence (XRF) analysis of numerous copper alloy objects from the MBA (1945–1730 BC) at Kanesh-Kültepe identified small ornamental objects as arsenical bronze and larger weapons as leaded bronze, indicating the intentional selection of arsenic and lead.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:7&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The authors believe these results indicate the selective use of arsenic-bearing sulfide copper ores. Copper-alloy metallurgy during the Assyrian Colony period was heavily influenced by technology in the East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;trade-networks&#34;&gt;Trade Networks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clay tablets from Kanesh-Kültepe document the trade in tin between the East and Anatolia: as much as two tons of tin per year were imported into Kanesh-Kültepe.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:8&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Metal workshops with crucibles and molds have been discovered at Kültepe.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:9&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Complex trade networks developed during the Bronze Age. A cuneiform tablet dating from the eighteenth century BC in Syria documents the distribution of tin to Ugarit and as far west as Crete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A trade route leads from Assur, the capital of the Assyrian Empire (located today in modern Iraq), northwest through Kanesh-Kültepe into Central Anatolia.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:10&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The three sites being excavated by the JIAA—Kaman-Kalehöyük, Yassihoyuk, and Buklukale—are all situated along this route, which promoted Assyrian Colony trade (see fig. 21.1). In addition to the silver being traded from Anatolia for tin from Afghanistan, there was copper from Cyprus flowing into the Near East in the EBA and MBA (nineteenth century BC).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:11&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This trade persisted into the Late Bronze Age (LBA), as we know from the Uluburun shipwreck, which sank off the coast of Turkey while carrying ingots of copper and tin, probably on its way to or from Syria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;evidence-of-bronze-manufacture-discovered-by-the-jiaa&#34;&gt;Evidence of Bronze Manufacture Discovered by the JIAA&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evidence of bronze manufacture consists of numerous crucibles and molds from the three sites excavated by the JIAA: 33 stone molds for the casting of metal objects have been found dating from the Bronze Age and Iron Age, 27 of which derive from Kaman-Kalehöyük. A rectangular, two-sided mold (KL05-34; &lt;strong&gt;fig. 21.2&lt;/strong&gt;) has parallels in Hattusa, the capital during the Hittite Empire period, and dates to the LBA, Hittite Empire period (1400–1200 BC).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:12&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It was used for casting styli, small figurines, and an eight-spoked wheel.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:13&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Another rectangular mold (KL88-127) found at Kaman-Kalehöyük was used for casting arrowheads and other unidentified objects.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:14&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The copper slags from Kaman-Kalehöyük were analyzed using inductively coupled plasma optical emission spectroscopy (ICP-OES) and electron microprobe metallographic analysis (EPMA).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:15&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This study revealed the presence of iron and copper sulfide, indicating that copper sulfide ores (such as chalcopyrite) were smelted to obtain copper at the site during the MBA (1950–1400 BC). Differences in chemical composition among the copper slags indicate that copper ore or smelted copper came from different regions during this period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to a study in 2005, approximately 40 percent of the slag found at Kaman-Kalehöyük between 1996 and 2004 is copper slag with a glassy matrix, indicating copper refining in crucibles.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:16&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The slags were recovered in one area dating to the MBA Old Hittite Kingdom period (1700–1400 BC) and in another area from the Early Iron Age (1200–775 BC). Copper ore with lead and zinc impurities was more prevalent in the Early Iron Age than in the MBA, indicating different sources of copper ore throughout history. The selective use of copper ores containing arsenic impurities is evidenced by the detection of copper and tin in one crucible (KL140628) and copper and arsenic in another crucible (KL140710) with XRF analysis.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:17&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-iron-age&#34;&gt;The Iron Age&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The collapse of the Hittite Empire after 1180 BC led to the beginning of the Iron Age and a very complex period in the history of Central Anatolia. The Early Iron Age is often referred to as the Dark Age, in which a Neo-Hittite civilization sprung up. Kaman-Kalehöyük, Hattusa, and Alişar were three main Iron Age sites in what was previously Hittite territory. During the Iron Age, Kaman-Kalehöyük was exposed to diverse ethnic, cultural, and artistic influences, drawing from a wide radius. The Assyrians entered Central Anatolia in 838 BC, bringing with them strong artistic and cultural influences. They took control of Central Anatolia from 744 to 727 BC, forming the Neo-Assyrian Kingdom of Tabal. Concurrently with the Assyrian presence, an ever-growing Phrygian influence was felt at Kaman-Kalehöyük beginning in the late eighth century BC, with the expansion of the Phrygian Empire over the next few centuries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Late Iron Age, the Medes invaded Central Anatolia from northwest Iran and controlled the area to the east of the Halys River in the region of Kaman-Kalehöyük from around 605 to 550 BC. Northwest Iranian fibulae in the Kaman collection are evidence of this occupation. The Achaemenid Empire replaced the Median Empire from 550 to 334 BC; at this point, the Persian Royal road from Susa to Sardis was established that was used later during the Hellenistic period.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:18&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bronze-fibulae&#34;&gt;Bronze Fibulae&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bronze objects that most readily illustrate the intraregional exchanges and multiethnic influences at Kaman-Kalehöyük are the fibulae dating from the Middle Iron Age to the Hellenistic period. The earliest fibulae come from the Mediterranean area in the thirteenth century BC; they then spread to the Near East, where they were used until the seventh century BC.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:19&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; During the Middle Iron Age, the fibula was introduced to Central Anatolia, where it became very popular. From the beginning of the Kaman-Kalehöyük excavation in 1986, a total of 586 fibulae have been found. The most common type is the Phrygian fibula, followed in order of prominence by north Syrian, northwest Iranian, southeast Anatolian, Greek, and Aegean fibulae (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 21.3&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:20&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:20&#34;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Phrygians were the first Anatolians (apart from the Ionians) to adopt the fibula, which they did around 750 BC.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:21&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:21&#34;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Horizontal horns projecting from the sides of the catch and the semicircular shape are the trademarks of the Phrygian fibula, characterized as Blinkenberg Type XII.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:22&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:22&#34;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The pin was usually cast separately and attached by insertion into a drilled hole. It is unusual for the pin to be preserved, as it has been in the Phrygian fibula in the top left of figure 21.3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gordion, the capital of Phrygia, had abundant trade with the Greeks, resulting in the influx of Greek fibulae at Gordion and Phrygian metalwork in mainland Greece.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:23&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:23&#34;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Aegean and Greek fibulae have been found in many parts of Anatolia, including Kaman-Kalehöyük, as attested to by the Aegean and Greek fibulae (see fig. 21.3, bottom row, center and right). In the Archaic period, the Anatolian kings, such as Midas of Gordion in Phrygia and Croesus of Sardis in Lydia, commissioned numerous works from Greek artists; by the sixth century BC, the art of Gordion and Sardis showed considerable Greek influence.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:24&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:24&#34;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three Phrygian and three north Syrian fibulae from Kaman-Kalehöyük were analyzed with XRF, X-ray diffraction, and X-radiography.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:25&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:25&#34;&gt;25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The fibulae were found to be copper-tin bronze with traces of arsenic, and some were intentionally leaded. Antinomy was found in the Phrygian fibulae and vanadium in a Syrian fibula. Arsenic and antimony were often added to copper, as was tin, to decrease the melting point, to improve hardness when cold working, to render a particular color to the metal, and to improve the quality of casting.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:26&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:26&#34;&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; According to John Twilley’s analysis, the levels of arsenic and antimony were not high enough to have been intentional additions and therefore none are considered to be arsenical copper.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:27&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:27&#34;&gt;27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The Anatolian highlands were rich in polymetallic ores containing many elements including arsenic and antimony, which may account for the Phrygian composition. The fact that vanadium was found only in the north Syrian fibula indicates a diversity of ores being smelted in Syria during this period. Zinc was not found in these Kaman fibulae whereas it was prevalent in several fibulae from Tumulus MM at Gordion.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:28&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:28&#34;&gt;28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few stone and ceramic molds for manufacturing fibulae have been discovered at Kaman-Kalehöyük. The ceramic mold pictured here (KL88-16; &lt;strong&gt;fig. 21.4&lt;/strong&gt;) was for the manufacture of a Phrygian type fibula.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:29&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:29&#34;&gt;29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Evidence of Greek influence is seen in the unfinished fibula (KL90-62; &lt;strong&gt;fig. 21.5&lt;/strong&gt;) found at Kaman-Kalehöyük.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:30&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:30&#34;&gt;30&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Although it closely resembles Blinkenberg Type XII 9h&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:31&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:31&#34;&gt;31&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; from the region of Ankara, it preserves the remnants of a transverse piece, similar to Blinkenberg Type XII 10a&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:32&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:32&#34;&gt;32&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; from Olympia, Greece. A series of studs along the bow and transverse piece would have completed this fibula.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;urartian-bronzes-at-kaman-kalehöyük&#34;&gt;Urartian bronzes at Kaman-Kalehöyük&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This period in the development of the bronze fibula in Anatolia was accompanied by the growth of the powerful Urartian Empire in eastern Anatolia. Urartu was a prominent metalworking center in the Near East in the first millennium BC. Various casting methods were used, after which articles were embellished with repoussé, engraving, chasing, tracing, inlaying, plating, granulation, soldering, and brazing.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:33&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:33&#34;&gt;33&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; First-millennium-BC Urartian bronze has a high proportion of copper-zinc-tin alloys, sometimes with lead, which has been attributed to the intentional smelting of polymetallic ores.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:34&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:34&#34;&gt;34&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Comparisons in alloy composition have been made with Greek bronzes from this period.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:35&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:35&#34;&gt;35&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Urartian bronze objects are found in Gordion and in many areas of Greece. Trade between Urartu and Gordion from 730 to 675 BC followed two east–west routes across northern and southern Anatolia.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:36&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:36&#34;&gt;36&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Given that Kaman is situated between the northern and southern routes, midway between Gordion and Urartu, it is not surprising that Urartian bronzes have been discovered in Kaman-Kalehöyük. A bronze object resembling a quiver (KL03000069) but of undetermined function was discovered in Kaman-Kalehöyük from a Late Iron Age layer dating to the seventh or sixth century BC. It was made from sheet metal that was decorated with repoussé, and it demonstrates several Urartian characteristics such as rows of chevrons alternating with what may be rows of four-legged animals (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 21.6&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:37&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:37&#34;&gt;37&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bronze belt or strap showing strong Urartian characteristics (KL12000010) was found in thirty-four pieces and was reconstructed to a length of 45 centimeters (17 &amp;frac34; in.; &lt;strong&gt;fig. 21.7&lt;/strong&gt;, top).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:38&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:38&#34;&gt;38&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Double rows of decoration delineating horizontal bands of human and animal figures were a common motif on Urartian belts.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:39&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:39&#34;&gt;39&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In raking light, it is possible to distinguish similar two- and four-legged creatures along two registers on an Urartian belt fragment in the Metropolitan Museum of Art (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 21.7&lt;/strong&gt;, bottom).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:40&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:40&#34;&gt;40&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Extensive corrosion of the Urartian bronzes found at Kaman-Kalehöyük impedes a more precise iconographical interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-hellenistic-period&#34;&gt;The Hellenistic Period&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the conquest of Anatolia by Alexander the Great and his death in 323 BC in Babylon, the Seleucid Empire took over much of Central Anatolia, including Kaman-Kalehöyük, from around 312 BC. Under the influence of the ruling Seleucid dynasty, which preserved and promoted Hellenistic culture, a strong Hellenistic influence was felt in Gordion as well as in Kanesh-Kültepe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In about 279 BC the Celts invaded Central Anatolia from Thrace and established the Galatian Empire. The Galatians took over a small area of the Seleucid Empire, making Ankara their capital city. The Hellenistic cities and King Attalus of Pergamon fought the Seleucids and the Galatians, confining them to their own territories, which included Kaman-Kalehöyük. Galatia was much less affected by the Hellenistic movement than was Pergamon, where Hellenistic influences strongly took hold. These influences are most noticeable in the silver coins minted by the later Galatian rulers.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:41&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:41&#34;&gt;41&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Habitation during the Hellenistic period appears to have shifted for the most part off the mound and into surrounding areas. A paleo-environmental study by Kaoru Kashima has determined that rising waters from heavy rainfall partially submerged the mound, which is situated on the lowest terrace of an alluvial fan on the side of Mount Baran.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:42&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:42&#34;&gt;42&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In spite of this population displacement, a few Hellenistic artifacts have been recovered from Kaman-Kalehöyük, such as silver coins of Alexander the Great, a small marble bust, and a terracotta figurine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Skeletal remains of Galatian cult practice in the form of human and animal sacrifices during the Hellenistic period have also been recovered from the mound.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:43&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:43&#34;&gt;43&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Round pits previously used for grain storage were adopted by the Galatians as repositories for human and animal bodies. The Galatians were known to hold sacrificial rituals during the Hellenistic period in Central Anatolia, and similar burials have been found at Gordion from the Galatian occupation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considerable evidence of copper and bronze refining and manufacture has been discovered at Kaman-Kalehöyük from the MBA (1950–1400 BC), when technological and artistic influences came largely from Assyria and Mesopotamia. Copper and bronze refining and manufacture continued there in the Early and Middle Iron Age (ca. 750–ca. 600 BC), a period when fibulae were very popular in Central Anatolia. Greek influence in the Phrygian capital of Gordion preceding the Hellenistic period undoubtedly affected Kaman-Kalehöyük; increased contact with Gordion during the expansion of the Phrygian kingdom is evidenced by the large number of Phrygian fibulae found at the site. The unfinished Phrygian fibula found in Kaman-Kalehöyük, resembling Blinkenberg Type XII 10a found in Olympia, strongly suggests influence from mainland Greece in the eighth century BC (see fig. 21.5).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An in-depth study of copper and bronze working is needed at Kaman-Kalehöyük, to examine the relationship between slag, crucibles, molds, copper and bronze artifacts, and related architectural remains. Such study will elucidate the contribution of this site to the development of the metallurgical industry in Central Anatolia during the Bronze and Iron Ages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bibliography&#34;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Akanuma 2007&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Akanuma, H. 2007. “Analysis of Iron and Copper Production Activity in Central Anatolia During the Assyrian Colony Period.” &lt;em&gt;Anatolian Archaeological Studies&lt;/em&gt; 16: 125–39.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Barjamovic 2011&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Barjamovic, G. 2011. &lt;em&gt;A Historical Geography of Anatolia in the Old Assyrian Colony Period&lt;/em&gt;. Carsten Niebuhr Institute of Near Eastern Studies 38. Copenhagen: Museum Tusculanum Press.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Birmingham 1961&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Birmingham, J. M. 1961. “The Overland Route across Anatolia in the Eighth and Seventh Centuries B.C.” &lt;em&gt;AnatSt&lt;/em&gt; 11: 185–95.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Blinkenberg, C. 1926&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Blinkenberg, C. 1926. &lt;em&gt;Fibules Grecques et Orientales&lt;/em&gt;, Copenhagen: Andr. Fred. Høst &amp;amp; Son, Kgl. Hof-Boghandel; Bianco Lunos Bogtrykkeri.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Boehmer 1979&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Boehmer, R. M. 1979. &lt;em&gt;Die Kleinfunde aus der Unterstadt von Boğazköy&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Grabungskampagnen 1970–1978&lt;/em&gt;. Berlin: Gebr. Mann.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Darbyshire et al. 2000&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Darbyshire, G., S. Mitchell, and L. Vardar. 2000. “The Galatian Settlement in Asia Minor.” &lt;em&gt;AnatSt&lt;/em&gt; 50: 75–97.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Dubin 2016&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Dubin, R. 2016. “Treatment of a Copper Alloy Container from Kaman-Kalehöyük.” &lt;em&gt;Anatolian Archaeological Studies&lt;/em&gt; 19: 175–83.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Ebbinghaus 2014&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Ebbinghaus, S., ed. 2014. &lt;em&gt;Ancient Bronzes through a Modern Lens: Introductory Essays on the Study of Ancient Mediterranean and Near Eastern Bronzes&lt;/em&gt;. Cambridge (MA): Harvard Art Museums.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Eremin 2014&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Eremin, K. 2014. “Analytical Approaches to Ancient Bronzes.” In Ebbinghaus 2014, 65–92.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Ergürer 2010&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Ergürer, H. 2010. “Urartu Kemerleri Üzerindeki İnsan Tasvirleri (Portrayals of Humans on the Belts of Urartu).” &lt;em&gt;Atatürk Üniversitesi Sosyal Bilimler Enstitüsü Dergisi&lt;/em&gt; 14.2: 1–22.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;French 1998&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;French, D. 1998. “Pre- and Early-Roman Roads of Asia Minor: The Persian Royal Road.” &lt;em&gt;Iran&lt;/em&gt; 36: 15–43.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Harl 2011&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Harl, K. 2011. “The Greeks in Anatolia: From Migrations to Alexander the Great.” In &lt;em&gt;The Oxford Handbook of Ancient Anatolia&lt;/em&gt;, ed. S. R. Steadman and G. McMahon, 752–74. Oxford: Oxford University Press.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Hemingway 2014&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Hemingway, S. 2014. “The Age of Bronze in Greece, Cyprus, and the Near East.” In Ebbinghaus 2014, 20–37.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Hughes et al. 1981&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Hughes, J. M. J., J. E. Curtis, and E. T. Hall. 1981. “Analyses of Some Urartian Bronzes.” &lt;em&gt;AnatSt&lt;/em&gt; 31: 141–45.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;JIAA 2014&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;JIAA 2014. &lt;em&gt;Conservation Treatment Report&lt;/em&gt;. Unpublished.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Kashima 2008&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Kashima, K. 2008. “Palaeo-Environmental Changes at Kaman-Kalehöyük, Kirşehir, Turkey: A Verification of the Humid Periods during the Bronze Age and the Iron Age.” &lt;em&gt;Anatolian Archaeological Studies&lt;/em&gt; 17: 251–63.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Kellner 1991&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Kellner, H. J. 1991. &lt;em&gt;Gürtelbleche aus Urartu&lt;/em&gt;. Stuttgart: Steiner.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Lehner 2014&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Lehner, J. W. 2014. “Metal Technology, Organization, and the Evolution of Long-Distance Trade at Kültepe.” In &lt;em&gt;Current Research at Kültepe-Kanesh: An Interdisciplinary and Integrative Approach to Trade Networks, Internationalism, and Identity&lt;/em&gt;, ed. L. Atici, F. Kulakoğlu, G. Barjamovic, and  A. Fairbairn, 135–55. Boston: American School of Oriental Research and Lockwood Press.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Masubuchi and Nakai 2005&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Masubuchi, M., and I. Nakai. 2005. “Scientific Characterization of Metallurgical Slag Excavated from Kaman-Kalehöyük.” &lt;em&gt;Anatolian Archaeological Studies&lt;/em&gt; 14: 183–94.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Masubuchi et al. 2004&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Masubuchi, M., T. Sanada, and I. Nakai. 2004. “X-Ray Fluorescence Analysis of Copper-Based and Noble Metal Artifacts from Kültepe Measured at Kayseri Archaeological Museum.” &lt;em&gt;Anatolian Archaeological Studies&lt;/em&gt; 13: 153–61.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Matsumura 2007&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Matsumura, K. 2007. “Animal and Human Skeletons from Late Stratum II Pits at Kaman-Kalehöyük.” &lt;em&gt;Anatolian Archaeological Studies&lt;/em&gt; 16: 97–110.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Metropolitan Museum of Art 2016&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Metropolitan Museum of Art inv. 52.123, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.metmuseum.org/toah/works-of-art/52.123/&#34;&gt;http://www.metmuseum.org/toah/works-of-art/52.123/&lt;/a&gt; (accessed April 26, 2016).&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Mikami and Omura 1992&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Mikami, T., and S. Omura. 1992. “A Preliminary Report on the Second Excavation at Kaman-Kalehöyük in Turkey (1987).” &lt;em&gt;Bulletin of the Middle Eastern Culture Center in Japan&lt;/em&gt; 6: 27–59.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Mori and Omura 1993&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Mori, M., and S. Omura. 1993. “Preliminary Report on the Third Excavation at Kaman-Kalehöyük in Turkey (1988).” &lt;em&gt;Bulletin of the Middle Eastern Culture Center in Japan&lt;/em&gt; 7: 43–74.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Muscarella 1967&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Muscarella, O. W. 1967. “Phrygian Fibulae from Gordion.” &lt;em&gt;Colt Archaeological Institute Monograph Series&lt;/em&gt; 4: 48–57&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; London: Bernard Quaritch Ltd.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Muscarella 1988&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Muscarella, O. W. 1988. &lt;em&gt;Bronze and Iron: Ancient Near Eastern Artifacts in the Metropolitan Museum of Art&lt;/em&gt;. New York: The Metropolitan Museum of Art.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Omura 1991&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Omura, S. 1991. “1989 Yılı Kaman-Kalehöyük Kazıları.” &lt;em&gt;Kazı Sonuçları Toplantısı I&lt;/em&gt; 7: 427–42.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Omura 1992&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Omura, S. 1992. “1990 Yılı Kaman-Kalehöyük Kazıları.” &lt;em&gt;Kazı Sonuçları Toplantısı I&lt;/em&gt; 8: 319–36.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Omura 2006&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Omura, S. 2006. “Preliminary Report on the 20th Excavation Season at Kaman-Kalehöyük (2005).” &lt;em&gt;Anatolian Archaeological Studies&lt;/em&gt; 15: 1–61.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Omura 2008&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Omura, M. 2008. “Archaeological Surveys at Yassihöyük.” &lt;em&gt;Anatolian Archaeological Studies&lt;/em&gt; 17: 97–169.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Omura 2011&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Omura, S. 2011. “Kaman-Kalehöyük Excavations in Central Anatolia.” In Steadman and McMahon 2011, 1095–1111.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Pernicka et al. 2003&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Pernicka, E., C. Eibner, Ö. Öztunali, and G. A. Wagner. 2003. “Early Bronze Age Metallurgy in the North-East Aegean.” In &lt;em&gt;Troai and the Troad: Scientific Approaches&lt;/em&gt;, ed. G. A. Wagner, E. Pernicka, and H. P. Uerpmann, 143–72. Berlin: Springer.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Piotrovskii 1967&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Piotrovskii, B. B. 1967. &lt;em&gt;Urartu: The Kingdom of Van and Its Art&lt;/em&gt;. New York: Frederick A. Praeger.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Pulak 1998&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Pulak, C. 1998. “The Uluburun Shipwreck: An Overview.” &lt;em&gt;IJNA&lt;/em&gt; 27.3: 188–224.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Sams 2011&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Sams, G. 2011. “Anatolia: The 1st Millenium BCE in Historical Context.” In Steadman and McMahon 2011, 604–22.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Steadman and McMahon 2011&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Steadman, S. R., and G. McMahon, eds. &lt;em&gt;The Oxford Handbook of Ancient Anatolia&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford: Oxford University Press.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Stech 1999&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Stech, T. 1999. “Aspects of Early Metallurgy in Mesopotamia and Anatolia.” In &lt;em&gt;The Archaeometallurgy of the Asian Old World&lt;/em&gt;, ed. V. C. Pigott, 59–71. University Museum Symposium Series 7; University Museum Monograph 89. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Museum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Steinberg 1981&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Steinberg, A. 1981. “Analyses of Selected Gordion Bronzes.” In &lt;em&gt;The Gordion Excavations Final Reports&lt;/em&gt;, vol. 1: &lt;em&gt;Three Great Early Tumuli&lt;/em&gt;, ed. R. S. Young, 286–89. University Museum Monograph 43. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Museum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Stronach 1959&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Stronach, D. 1959. “The Development of the Fibula in the Near East.” &lt;em&gt;Iraq&lt;/em&gt; 21: 181–206.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Tsatsouli 2016&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Tsatsouli, K. 2016. “Conservation Season Report 2012 Kaman-Kalehöyük, Yassıhöyük and Büklükale Excavations.” &lt;em&gt;Anatolian Archaeological Studies&lt;/em&gt; 19: 123–36.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Twilley 1996&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Twilley, J. 1996. “Scientific Analysis of Six Bronze Fibulae from Kaman-Kalehöyük.” &lt;em&gt;Anatolian Archaeological Studies&lt;/em&gt; 5: 237–50.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Vassileva 2012&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Vassileva, M. 2012. “Early Bronze Fibulae and Belts from Gordion Citadel Mound.” In &lt;em&gt;The Archaeology of Phrygian Gordion, Royal City of Midas&lt;/em&gt;, ed. Brian Rose, 111–26. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Wartke 2007&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Wartke, R. 2007. “Bemerkungen zur Metallurgie Urartus.” &lt;em&gt;Acta Iranica&lt;/em&gt;, 411–16.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Yamashita 2000&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Yamashita, M. 2000. &lt;em&gt;Fibeln aus Kaman-Kalehöyük 1986–1999&lt;/em&gt;. Unpublished report, JIAA.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Omura 2011.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;Omura 2008.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;Pernicka et al. 2003, 145.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;Pernicka et al. 2003, 146.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;Stech 1999, 64; Pernicka et al. 2003.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;Stech 1999, 64.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;Masubuchi et al. 2004, 159–60.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;Hemingway 2014, 29–30.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;See Lehner 2014.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;Barjamovic 2011, map insert in back cover.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;Hemingway 2014, 31.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;Boehmer 1979, 62, plate 38, no. 3849a–e.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;Omura 2006, 23, 32–33, color photos 14–15, figs. 59–61 .
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;Mori and Omura 1993, 68, fig. 12.5; 70, plate 1.11.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;Akanuma 2007.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34;&gt;Masubuchi and Nakai 2005.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34;&gt;JIAA 2014.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:18&#34;&gt;French 1998, 22; Sams 2011, 614.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:18&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:19&#34;&gt;Stronach 1959.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:19&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:20&#34;&gt;Yamashita 2000; for KL87-2176, see Mikami and Omura 1992, 48, fig. 11.12, and 57, plate 6.3; for KL89-322, see Omura 1991, 438, Resim 6.5.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:20&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:21&#34;&gt;Muscarella 1988, 425.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:21&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:22&#34;&gt;Blinkenberg 1926; Muscarella 1967, 48.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:22&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:23&#34;&gt;Vassileva 2012, 115, 123.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:23&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:24&#34;&gt;Harl 2011, 757.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:24&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:25&#34;&gt;Twilley 1996.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:25&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:26&#34;&gt;Eremin 2014, 73.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:26&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:27&#34;&gt;Twilley 1996, 238.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:27&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:28&#34;&gt;Steinberg 1981, 289.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:28&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:29&#34;&gt;Mori and Omura 1993, 68, plate 12.6, and 70, plate 1.10.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:29&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:30&#34;&gt;Omura 1992, 331, Resim 7.4.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:30&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:31&#34;&gt;Blinkenberg 1926, 215.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:31&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:32&#34;&gt;Blinkenberg 1926, 217.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:32&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:33&#34;&gt;Piotrovskii 1967; Wartke 2007, 416.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:33&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:34&#34;&gt;Eremin 2014, 81.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:34&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:35&#34;&gt;Hughes et al. 1981, 144.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:35&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:36&#34;&gt;Birmingham 1961, 192.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:36&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:37&#34;&gt;Dubin 2016.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:37&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:38&#34;&gt;Tsatsouli 2016, 124–27.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:38&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:39&#34;&gt;Ergürer 2010, 12, 14, 17, 21, figs. 1, 5, 12, 19 (from Kellner 1991, figs. 8, 122, 182, 185).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:39&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:40&#34;&gt;Muscarella 1988, 433, no. 578; Metropolitan Museum of Art 2016, inv. 52.123; Tsatsouli 2016, 124–27.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:40&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:41&#34;&gt;Darbyshire et al. 2000, 95.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:41&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:42&#34;&gt;Kashima 2008, 262.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:42&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:43&#34;&gt;Matsumura 2007, 97.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:43&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Influence of Bronze Working on Roman Provincial Stone Sculpture</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-helenistic-east/23-albertson/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-helenistic-east/23-albertson/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The prosperity experienced by the elite of the ancient Romano-Syrian city of Palmyra from the late first century BC through the middle of the third century AD is perhaps most visible in their monumental family tombs and the funerary sculpture associated within these tombs. Among the types included within the well-known repertoire of Palmyran funerary reliefs are the distinctive &lt;em&gt;loculus&lt;/em&gt; plaques: rectangular limestone slabs covering the burial cavity, carved in high-relief with a bust depicting the individual interred and often accompanied by an Aramaic inscription denoting the occupant’s name, family lineage, and sometimes even the date of death. By about AD 200, the so-called “large banquet relief” and sarcophagi had also become mainstays within the Palmyran tomb.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Palmyra’s wealth attracted and supported an active artistic community specializing in the carving of stone, specifically the locally quarried limestone. Yet this is a group that did not exist prior to the late first century BC and therefore had no previous local tradition from which to draw. The evolution of Palmyran sculpture and its portraiture is thus characterized by the borrowing of features from outside sources and the adaptation of forms and techniques to meet local tastes. Argued here is that one of these outside sources was contemporary Graeco-Roman bronze statuary.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The physical evidence for the presence of bronze statuary at Palmyra is sparse. Only a handful of fragments remain: a sandaled foot with part of the lower leg from the Sanctuary of Bel; a section of drapery, a hand, and two feet clad in Parthian shoes from the Agora; and a miniature bust of a priest found in the Sanctuary of Nabû.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The context would suggest that the use of bronze was normally confined to honorific statues erected in prominent public areas. A better claim for the wider use of bronze statuary at Palmyra comes from the Tariff Law of AD 137, specifically lines 128–30, which state that bronze statuary coming into the city was to be taxed the same as ordinary bronze, i.e., one statue to be taxed based on half of its weight, two statues by the weight of one.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; These lines would seem to imply that bronze statues were being imported into the city in significant numbers, requiring them not only to be taxed but also to be qualified as to the manner by which they should be taxed.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An examination of the surviving corpus of Palmyran sculpture, particularly that originating from a funerary context and dealing with images of the deceased, would strongly suggest that certain techniques employed on metal were then imitated and adapted by local stone carvers. The features examined here are limited to those that can be documented in works of bronze and are markedly absent in Roman marble sculpture. Such features occur in some 60 to 70 pieces, out of a surviving corpus of some 2,000 examples of Palmyran funerary sculpture.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:6&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One prominent bronze feature seen in Palmyran stone sculpture is the incision of the eyebrows into a distinct herringbone pattern, sometimes referred to as caterpillar eyebrows (&lt;strong&gt;figs. 23.1–2&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:7&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; One might be tempted to propose a Near Eastern origin for such a rendering of the brows; portraits of Gudea of Lagash instantly come to mind.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:8&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; However, there is no evidence to document a continuity of such a form from the late third millennium BC to the early first millennium AD in the sculpture of the ancient Near East. Instead there are more obvious and chronologically closer examples of incised herringbone eyebrows in Graeco-Roman bronze statuary. Among the examples are a series of Gallo-Roman heads from the first century AD, including two bronze busts depicting male youths now in the Getty Villa (&lt;strong&gt;figs. 23.3–4&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:9&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; These can be supplemented by the bronze Doryphoros from the mid-first century BC context of the Villa dei Papiri at Herculaneum.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:10&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Within the realm of earlier Greek bronze statuary, the technique can be traced back through the Hellenistic to the late Classical period, as evidenced by the bronze head of a boxer from Olympia.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:11&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second feature found in Palmyran limestone sculpture that was certainly borrowed from contemporary bronze sculpture is the use of glass paste for the iris and pupil, in place of the more common incised iris and drilled pupil, which were then painted. As seen on the so-called Beauty of Palmyra in Copenhagen, a &lt;em&gt;loculus&lt;/em&gt; plaque belonging to an anonymous Palmyran matron carved in approximately AD 200–210, what normally remains is a large circular cavity with an inner flattened surface (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 23.5&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:12&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The flat surface of the cavity has caused scholars to speculate that such eyes when seen in Palmyran sculpture originally would have had inserted irises of another material.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:13&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This assumption has proved to be correct, for among the series of ten surviving examples, one retains its original inserted eyes: a female head in the Los Angeles County Museum of Art (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 23.6&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:14&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The extensively pitted material is glass paste, and its color, which appears black at first glance, is actually a dark blue. The insertion of the eyes as a separate entity has a long tradition in Greek statuary, but the insertion of only a circular iris has its best parallels in contemporary Roman statuary, most notably a series of Gallo-British examples, best illustrated by a recently discovered head of Marcus Aurelius now in the Ashmolean Museum (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 23.7&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:15&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The fact that this technique may have been popular regionally in southeast Britain and northern Gaul does not rule out that the source is external and chronologically earlier. A bronze head of Hadrian, originally discovered in the Thames near London and currently in the British Museum, shows the method employed in official portraits of the emperors.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:16&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Two Etruscan bronze portraits of male youths from Fiesole dating to the third century BC may be the evidence needed to trace this bronze-working method back to Italy.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:17&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third feature associated with Graeco-Roman bronze sculpture and adopted into Palmyran stone sculpture is the finely incised bordering of the lips, physically enhancing the vermilion border and often with a triangular recession denoting the depression between the lobes of the lower lip (see fig. 23.6). This technique is nearly absent in Roman marble portraiture but well-known in bronze, as seen on the Croatian Apoxyomenos.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:18&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This form in metalworking is surely intended to denote a separation of what would be copper lips from the surrounding bronze flesh, and its origins may stem from an early period when the mouth could be cast separately.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:19&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it seems clear that contemporary bronze statuary was the source for certain features seen in Palmyran limestone sculpture, perhaps the more intriguing questions are when and why this influence occurred. Here we are fortunate in that the methodology exists to date each example of Palmyran funerary sculpture relatively securely to within a 20–25 year span. Such a process is made possible by the existence of examples in which the date of the deceased’s death, and presumably then the date of the relief’s carving, is given in the accompanying inscription.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:20&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:20&#34;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The formulation of an absolute chronology is further assisted by intact tomb groups, where the genealogical context allows each funerary relief to be assigned to its respective generation.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:21&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:21&#34;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; These datable examples then serve as chronological data points and, through a process of stylistic and typological comparison, allows the majority of undated examples to be dated. Consequently, a review of the chronology of those individual features discussed so far—herringbone eyebrows, inserted glass pastes for irises, and engraved lips—helps to shed light on the rationale behind the adoption of such features by Palmyran workshops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incised herringbone-shaped eyebrows can be documented on at least thirty-two examples at Palmyra (see Appendix 1). The form appears shortly after the middle of the second century. The earliest documented instance is the dated bust of ’Atê’aqab, in Istanbul, whose inscription gives AD 157 as the year of death.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:22&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:22&#34;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; However, half of the examples cluster roughly between the years AD 180 and 210. After about AD 210, only a handful of examples appear. The last dated example is the relief of Ḥaggûr, son of Malkû, in the American University Museum, Beirut, inscribed AD 236–237.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:23&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:23&#34;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Of note is the fact that all the known examples represent males, suggesting that Palmyran sculptures consciously saw this manner of rendering the eyebrows as a gender signifier. In addition, at Palmyra the apex of the chevron of each individual eyebrow is pointed toward the bridge of the nose (see fig. 23.2), unlike that of any possible Mesopotamian or Graeco-Roman antecedent where the opposite direction is maintained (see fig. 23.4). This suggests a distinctively Palmyran adaptation of the form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An inserted glass-paste iris and pupil makes its appearance within the Palmyran repertoire of forms in about AD 200. The Beauty of Palmyra in Copenhagen is the earliest (see fig. 23.5). One fragmentary &lt;em&gt;loculus&lt;/em&gt; plaque of a woman&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:24&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:24&#34;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and three female heads, all probably originating from large banquet reliefs and including the example in the Los Angeles County Museum of Art (see fig. 23.6),&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:25&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:25&#34;&gt;25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; fall into the period around AD 200–220. The other five remaining examples are male; all are heads originally belonging to either statues or large banquet reliefs, and all date to about AD 230–250, more likely later in this period than earlier.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:26&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:26&#34;&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Glass-paste eyes thus show an initial appearance in the Palmyran sculptors’ repertoire around AD 200–220, restricted at first to female portraiture. Then, perhaps after a brief pause, they reappear on male portraits for a short time toward the middle of the century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The earliest documented use of incisions bordering and detailing the lips at Palmyra is from “the month of Tebet 466” (January AD 155), the date found on the inscription accompanying the &lt;em&gt;loculus&lt;/em&gt; plaque of Bênnûr, son of Bar’â, in the Louvre.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:27&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:27&#34;&gt;27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; If we follow the examples listed by Gunhild Ploug, in her catalogue of Palmyran sculpture in the Ny Carlsberg Glyptotek, this relief and six others can be placed chronologically within the period of approximately AD 150–170.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:28&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:28&#34;&gt;28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Eight of her examples fall in the later decades of AD 170–190.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:29&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:29&#34;&gt;29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The fashion then quickly fades, with few examples appearing after about AD 200. It ultimately disappears by about AD 220.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:30&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:30&#34;&gt;30&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our ability to date Palmyran sculpture rather accurately provides us with an unexpected result when dealing with the proposed influences of bronze on stone. One might expect the influence of bronze statuary to have a collective role; in other words, all the features with bronze antecedents making an appearance simultaneously, then existing side-by-side to some extent, and ultimately falling out of fashion altogether. Yet at Palmyra this is not the case. Incised lip outlines reach their highpoint of popularity around AD 170–190, then rapidly drop out of use. Incised herringbone eyebrows come into existence around the same time, and show the greatest period of use around AD 180–210, when the lip outlining is already on the decline. Glass paste eyes appear some fifty years after the other bronze-working features, reaching a peak of popularity around AD 230–250, long after the others have essentially dropped out of use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surviving examples thus suggest that the borrowing from bronze statuary was not a wholesale process but one that was done piecemeal. Isolated, individual features were adopted from bronze working and inserted into what remained a predominantly limestone tradition of carving. In addition, it is extremely rare for more than two of the bronze-derived features to appear together on the same portrait. Only two or perhaps three examples from the entire corpus of Palmyran funerary sculpture fall into this category, the head in the Los Angeles County Museum of Art being one.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:31&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:31&#34;&gt;31&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; One could speculate that the allusion to bronze conferred a loftier status on the deceased’s image in stone. The large majority of the examples showing the influence of bronze-working fall into the category of “finer” works, that is, those characterized by a greater attention to detail, a softer modelling of features, and an overall finished appearance. Nevertheless, the chronology supports the idea that the process of selecting features from bronze statuary was random. This eclectic selection process in fact reflects the Palmyran sculptors’ entire approach. Analysis of Palmyran funerary reliefs has revealed that the sculptor began with a concept of a “portrait,” which the sculptor drew from a pre-established repertoire of forms. These forms guided the means of rendering the garments and the arrangement of their folds, the positioning of arms and hands, and the selection of attributes and personal adornment such as jewelry or hairstyle.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:32&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:32&#34;&gt;32&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Even what would normally be considered the distinct, individualized features of the subject—the facial features—are forms repeated from one portrait to another. This strict dependence on typology in Palmyran funerary sculpture sometimes resulted in the creation of identical images representing two different people and different images representing the same person.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:33&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:33&#34;&gt;33&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study of Palmyran portraiture shows clearly that there was a continuous process of selection by the artist from a prescribed corpus of forms, perhaps due to the nature of the sculptural environment in which these reliefs were displayed and an emphasis on conveying the identity of the deceased, both as an individual and as a member of a larger community. What perhaps makes Palmyran portraiture so distinct is the fact that this repertoire of forms is constantly being augmented, with new forms drawn externally from Graeco-Roman art, including forms, as shown here, created in imitation of contemporary sculpture cast in bronze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;appendix-1-palmyran-reliefs-with-incised-herringbone-eyebrows&#34;&gt;Appendix 1: Palmyran Reliefs with Incised Herringbone Eyebrows&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Items are in chronological order; all are &lt;em&gt;loculus&lt;/em&gt; plaques depicting males unless otherwise noted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Date (AD)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Example&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;150&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;157&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Istanbul, Archaeological Museum inv. 3840T (Ingholt 1928, 34–35 PS 11, plate 4; &lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;, 476 no. 4616, plate 47)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;160&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Once Berlin, collection von Hahn 462–63 (Ingholt 1928, 119 PS 252; &lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;, 462–63 no. 4573); Istanbul, Archaeological Museum inv. 3837T (Ingholt 1928, 117 PS 237; &lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;, 363 no. 4299, plate 48)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;170&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Paris Louvre inv. AO 28381 (Dentzer-Feydey and Teixidor 1993, 244 no. 237); Palmyra, Palmyra Museum inv. B2729/9166: statue (Charles-Gaffiot et al. 2001, 320 no. 26, fig. on 190); Palmyra, Palmyra Museum inv. 1951/7043 (Sadurska and Bounni 1994, 51–52 no. 59, fig. 114)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;180&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Palmyra, Palmyra Museum inv. 1955/7047 (Sadurska and Bounni 1994, 53–54 no. 63, fig. 92); New York, Sotheby’s (Sotheby’s 2007, lot 31)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;187&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;New Haven, Yale University Art Gallery inv. 1954.30.3 (&lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;, 454 no. 4549, plate 61)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;189&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;St. Petersburg, Hermitage inv. 8840 (&lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;, 360 no. 4292, plate 52)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;190&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;London, British Museum 125032 (Ingholt 1928, 112 PS 201; &lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;, 362–63 no. 4297, plate 52); Toronto, Royal Ontario Museum inv. 953x94.4 (Ingholt 1928, 113 n.1 PS 203); Gaziantep, Archaeological Museum inv. 211 (Parlasca 2005, 143, 148 fig. 4); Damascus, National Museum, from Hypogeum of Yarḥai (Tanabe 1986, plate 280, fig. 249); Jerusalem, Church of St. Anne, Museum inv. PB 2670: double bust (Ingholt 1928, 110 PS 183; &lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;, 374–75 no. 4329, plate 54); Minneapolis, Minneapolis Institute of Art acc. 2008.28.2 (&lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;, 393 no. 4379; Sotheby’s 2002, lot 119); Oslo, Museum of Cultural History inv. C42235 (Ingholt 1928, 114 PS 217; &lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;, 369 no. 4314, plate 53)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;200&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Copenhagen, Ny Carlsberg Glyptotek inv. 1043 (Ploug 1995, 174–76 no. 70); New York, Metropolitan Museum of Art acc. 02.29.2 (Ingholt 1928, 109 PS 171); London, British Museum 125020 (Ingholt 1928, 119 PS 246; &lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;, 372 no. 4323, plate 38); Copenhagen, NCG inv. 1145: head (Ploug 1995, 222–23 no. 92); Palmyra, Palmyra Museum inv. 8522/2321 (Charles-Gaffiot et al. 2001, 347 no. 163, fig. on 271); Palmyra, Southeast Necropolis, Tomb H (Taibbôl), relief of Yarḥai; London, Christie’s (Christie’s 2012, lot 190)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;210&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;ew York, Metropolitan Museum of Art inv. 98.19.3 (Ingholt 1928, 122 PS 282; &lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;, 374 no. 4327, plate 36); Istanbul, Archaeological Museum (Ingholt 1928, 117 PS 237); Once New York, private collection (Ingholt 1928, 112 PS 197; Ingholt 1934, 36 n. 42)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;230&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Palmyra, Palmyra Museum inv. 457/1660: head (Colledge 1976, fig. 142; Tanabe 1986, plate 486 fig. 460); Damascus, National Museum inv. C18: plaster head (Tanabe 1986, plate 484 fig. 458; Charles-Gaffiot et al. 2001, 336 no. 99, fig. on 236); Berlin, Staatliche Museen inv. VA 50 (Ingholt 1928, 122 PS 279; &lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;, 395 no. 4385, plate 45)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;236–37&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Beirut, American University Museum inv. 32.35 (Ingholt 1934, 36–38, plate 9.1); Middlebury (VT), Middlebury College Museum of Art inv. 2009.002 (Sotheby’s 2008, lot 68)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;250&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bibliography&#34;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Albertson 2016&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Albertson, F. 2016. “Typology, Attribution, and Identity in Palmyran Funerary Portraiture.” In &lt;em&gt;The World of Palmyra&lt;/em&gt;, ed. Rubina Raja, 152–68. Scientia Danica, Serie H. Humanistica 4. Copenhagen: Royal Danish Academy of Sciences and Letters.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Chabot 1897&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Chabot, J.-B. 1897. “Notes d&amp;rsquo;épigraphie et d&amp;rsquo;archéologie orientale.” *JA* 10: 308–55.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Charles-Gaffiot et al. 2001&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Charles-Gaffiot, J., H. Lavagne, and J.-M. Hofman, eds. 2001. &lt;em&gt;Moi, Zénobie, reine de Palmyre&lt;/em&gt;. Milan: Skira.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Christie’s 2012&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Christie’s 2012. &lt;em&gt;Antiquities&lt;/em&gt;. Auction catalogue 4925. April 26, 2012, London.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;em&gt;Corpus Inscriptionum Semiticarum&lt;/em&gt;. [1926] 1947. Part 2, vol. 3: &lt;em&gt;Inscriptiones Palmyrenae&lt;/em&gt;, ed. J. B. Chabot. Paris: C. Klincksieck.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Colledge 1976&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Colledge, M. A. R. 1976. &lt;em&gt;The Art of Palmyra&lt;/em&gt;. Boulder (CO): Westview Press.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Daehner and Lapatin 2015&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Daehner, J., and K. Lapatin, eds. 2015. &lt;em&gt;Power and Pathos: Bronze Sculpture of the Hellenistic World&lt;/em&gt;. Los Angeles: J. Paul Getty Museum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Dentzer-Feydy and Teixidor 1993&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Dentzer-Feydy, J., and J. Teixidor. 1993. &lt;em&gt;Les antiquités de Palmyre au Musée du Louvre&lt;/em&gt;. Paris: Réunion des musées nationaux.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Fortin 1999&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Fortin, M. 1999. &lt;em&gt;Syria: Land of Civilizations&lt;/em&gt;. Trans. J. Macaulay. Montreal: Editions de l’Homme.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Ingholt 1928&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Ingholt, H. 1928. &lt;em&gt;Studier over Palmyrensk Skulptur&lt;/em&gt;. Copenhagen: C. A. Reitzels.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Ingholt 1934&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Ingholt, H. 1934. “Palmyrene Sculptures in Beirut.” &lt;em&gt;Berytus&lt;/em&gt; 1: 32–43.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Johansen 1978&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Johansen, F. 1978. &lt;em&gt;Statues of Gudea: Ancient and Modern&lt;/em&gt;. Mesopotamia 6. Copenhagen: Akademisk Forlag.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Kropp and Raja 2014&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Kropp, A., and R. Raja. 2014. “The Palmyra Portrait Project.” &lt;em&gt;Syria&lt;/em&gt; 91: 393–408.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Lahusen and Formigli 2001&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Lahusen. F., and E. Formigli. 2001. &lt;em&gt;Römische Bildnisse aus Bronze: Kunst und Technik&lt;/em&gt;. Munich: Hirmer.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Matthews 1984&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Matthews, J. 1984. “The Tax Law of Palmyra: Evidence for Economic History in a City of the Roman East.” &lt;em&gt;JRS&lt;/em&gt; 74: 157–80.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Mattusch 1988&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Mattusch, C. 1988. &lt;em&gt;Greek Bronze Statuary: From the Beginnings through the Fifth Century B.C.&lt;/em&gt; Ithaca: Cornell University Press.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Mattusch 1996&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Mattusch, C. C. 1996. &lt;em&gt;Classical Bronzes: The Art and Craft of Greek and Roman Statuary&lt;/em&gt;. Ithaca: Cornell University Press.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Parlasca 1989&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Parlasca, K. 1989. “Palmyrenische Bildnisse aus dem Umkreis Zenobias.” In &lt;em&gt;Festschrift für Robert Werner zu seinem 65. Geburtstag&lt;/em&gt;, ed. W. Dahlheim, W. Schuller, and J. von Ungern-Sternberg, 205–11. Xenia 22. Constance: Universitätsverlag.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Parlasca 1990&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Parlasca, K. 1990. “Palmyrenische Skulpturen in Museen an der amerikanischen Westküste.” In &lt;em&gt;Roman Funerary Monuments in the J. Paul Getty Museum&lt;/em&gt;, vol. 1, ed. M. True and G. Koch, 133–44. Occasional Papers on Antiquities 6. Malibu: J. Paul Getty Museum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Parlasca 2005&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Parlasca, K. 2005. “ Zu palmyrenischen Inschriften auf Reliefs.” In &lt;em&gt;A Journey to Palmyra: Collected Essays to Remember Delbert R. Hillers&lt;/em&gt;, ed. D. Hillers and E. Cussini, 137–49. Leiden and Boston: Brill.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Ploug 1995&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Ploug, G. 1995. &lt;em&gt;Catalogue of the Palmyrene Sculptures: Ny Carlsberg Glyptotek&lt;/em&gt;. Copenhagen: Ny Carlsberg Glyptotek.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Pollini 2001&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Pollini, J. 2001. “Two Bronze Portrait Busts of Slave-Boys from a Shrine of Cobannus in Roman Gaul.” In &lt;em&gt;Studia Varia from the J. Paul Getty Museum&lt;/em&gt;, vol. 2, ed. M. True and M. Hart, 115–52. Occasional Papers on Antiquities of The J. Paul Getty Museum 10. Malibu: J. Paul Getty Museum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Romano 1979&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Romano, J. 1979. &lt;em&gt;The Luxor Museum of Ancient Egyptian Art: Catalogue.&lt;/em&gt; Cairo: ASOR.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Sadurska and Bounni 1994&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Sadurska, A., and A. Bounni. 1994&lt;em&gt;. Les sculptures funéraires de Palmyre&lt;/em&gt;. RdA suppl. 13. Rome: G. Bretschneider.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Sotheby’s 2002&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Sotheby’s. 2002. &lt;em&gt;Antiquities&lt;/em&gt;. Auction catalogue 7858. December 11, 2002, New York.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Sotheby’s 2007&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Sotheby’s. 2007. &lt;em&gt;Egyptian, Classical and Western Asiatic Antiquities&lt;/em&gt;. Auction catalogue 8373. December 5, 2007, New York.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Sotheby’s 2008&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Sotheby’s 2008. &lt;em&gt;Egyptian, Classical and Western Asiatic Antiquities&lt;/em&gt;. Auction catalogue 8500. December 10, 2008, New York.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Tanabe 1986&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Tanabe, K. 1986. &lt;em&gt;Sculptures of Palmyra&lt;/em&gt;. Memoirs of the Ancient Orient Museum 1. Tokyo: Ancient Orient Museum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Walker 2014&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Walker, S. 2014. “Emperors and Deities in Rural Britain: A Copper-Alloy Head of Marcus Aurelius from Steane, near Brackley (Northants).” &lt;em&gt;Britannia&lt;/em&gt; 45: 223–42.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;For a general discussion, see Colledge 1976, 63–82.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;Note previous connection made by Colledge 1976, 90, and Parlasca 1989, 206 n. 17.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;Colledge 1976, 90 and n. 299, with bibliography. The hand from the Agora (Palmyra Museum inv. 4801/1) is now published: Charles-Gaffiot et al. 2001, 329 no. 64, fig. on 212.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;, no. 3913, 128–30 (Palmyrene version); Matthews 1984, 180.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;Colledge 1976, 190.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;Kropp and Raja 2014, 393.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;Illustrated here: Minneapolis, Minneapolis Institute of Art acc. 2008.28.2: &lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;, 393 no. 4379; Sotheby’s 2002, lot 119. See Appendix 23.1 for additional examples.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;Examples and illustrations of herringbone eyebrows: Johansen 1978, pls. 43, 44, 47, 59, 70, 71, 84, 92, 94, 97, 99, 101, 105, 113, and 120. They are also found, rarely, in Egyptian sculpture, as seen on the head of Senusret III from Karnak in the Luxor Museum: Romano 1979, 32–35 no. 40, figs. 28–31.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;J. Paul Getty Museum inv. 89.AB.67.1 and 89.AB.67.2 (illustrated here). Pollini 2001, with additional examples cited; note specific references to herringbone eyebrows on 137.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;Naples, Museo Archeologico Nazionale inv. 4885. Daehner and Lapatin 2015, 296–97 no. 50.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;Athens, National Archaeological Museum no. 6439. Mattusch 1996, 84–87, fig. 3.5.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;Ny Carlsberg Glyptotek inv. 2795: Ploug 1995, 188–92 no. 77. Such a form differs from similar large cavities for the iris appearing on other Palmyran examples (e.g., Ny Carlsberg Glyptotek inv. 1151: Ploug 1995, 234–36 no. 103); in these instances, the hollow is concave and not as deep, and there seems to be a distinction here between the iris and the pupil.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;Colledge 1976, 120; Ploug 1995, 190 and 229.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;Los Angeles County Museum of Art inv. M.82.77.2: Parlasca 1990, 140 no. 10, 139 fig. 10.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;Ashmolean Museum inv. AN2011.46; Walker 2008. It should be noted that both Colledge and Ploug (above, n. 13) tentatively suggest a Parthian source, citing inset eyes found on sculptures from Hatra.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34;&gt;British Museum inv. BEP 1848,1103.1. Lahusen and Formigli 2001, 190–92 no. 114, figs. 114.1–4.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34;&gt;Paris, Louvre inv. Br 19, and Florence, National Archaeological Museum inv. 548: Lahusen and Formigli 2001, 18–19 no. 1, figs. 1.1–4; 20 no. 2, figs. 2.1–4; 462 and 466 figs. 1–3 (eyes).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:18&#34;&gt;Daehner and Lapatin 2015, 274–75 no. 41.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:18&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:19&#34;&gt;Mattusch 1988, 205.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:19&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:20&#34;&gt;Ploug 1995, 12–13.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:20&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:21&#34;&gt;Sadurska and Bounni 1994.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:21&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:22&#34;&gt;Istanbul Archaeological Museum inv. 3840T: Ingholt 1928, 34–35 PS 11, plate 4; &lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;, 476 no. 4616, plate 47.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:22&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:23&#34;&gt;Beirut, American University Museum inv. 32.35: Ingholt 1934, 36–38 no. 3, plate 9.1.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:23&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:24&#34;&gt;First recorded in the collection of Guillaume Proche in Aleppo, illustrated by Chabot 1897, fig. 10. Present location not confirmed. Included in the series based on Ploug 1995, 229.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:24&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:25&#34;&gt;For the head in Los Angeles, see n. 14 above. The other two are: New York, Metropolitan Museum of Art acc. 65.77 (unpublished); and Palmyra Museum inv. B2770/9254 (Charles-Gaffiot et al. 2001, 329 no. 66, fig. on 214).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:25&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:26&#34;&gt;Copenhagen, Ny Carlsberg Glyptotek inv. 1117 (Ploug 1995, 238–39 no. 107); Copenhagen, Ny Carlsberg Glyptotek inv. 1121 (Ploug 1995, 227–30 no. 97); Palmyra Museum inv. B2727/9127 (Charles-Gaffiot et al. 2001, 367 no. 252, fig. on 311); Palmyra Museum inv. B2726/9163 (Fortin 1999, 114 no. 64); Damascus, National Museum inv. C18, in plaster (Tanabe 1986, plate 484 fig. 458; Charles-Gaffiot et al. 2001, 336 no. 99, fig. on 236).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:26&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:27&#34;&gt;Louvre inv. AO 2201. Dentzer-Feydy and Teixidor 1993, 185 no. 186.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:27&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:28&#34;&gt;Ploug 1995, 142. Another example may be added: London, British Museum 125022 (Ingholt 1928, 110 PS 180).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:28&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:29&#34;&gt;To which three more should be added: Grenoble, Musée de Grenoble inv. 1578 (Ingholt 1928, 141 PS 442); Pittsfield, Berkshire Museum acc. 1903.7.3 (Albertson 2016, 159–60 fig. 7); Portland (OR), Portland Museum of Art acc. 54.2 (Parlasca 1990, 138–39, 136 fig. 5).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:29&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:30&#34;&gt;The last in the sequence, ca. AD 200, is the relief in Berlin, Staatliche Museen inv. VA 48 (Ingholt 1928, 149 PS 494).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:30&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:31&#34;&gt;The other two would be the relief in Minneapolis (see n. 7 above), combining incised outlining of the lips and herringbone eyebrows, and a plaster head in Damascus, National Museum inv. C18 (see above n. 26), with herringbone eyebrows and glass paste eyes.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:31&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:32&#34;&gt;Kropp and Raja 2014, 403; Albertson 2016, 153.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:32&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:33&#34;&gt;Discussed and examples cited in Kropp and Raja 2014, 403–404; Albertson 2016, 154–55.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:33&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Transformation of Bronze Sculpture in the Hellenistic East and the Iranian World</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-helenistic-east/abstract-canepa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-helenistic-east/abstract-canepa/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Hellenistic Heritage of Termez</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-helenistic-east/abstract-mirzaev/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artistryinbronze/the-helenistic-east/abstract-mirzaev/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>