<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The-artists on </title>
    <link>/the-artist/</link>
    <description>Recent content in The-artists on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    
	<atom:link href="/the-artist/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Artist</title>
      <link>/the-artist/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/the-artist/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More Than Holes!</title>
      <link>/the-artist/9-adornato/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/the-artist/9-adornato/</guid>
      <description>1. Defining the Severe-style Period The artistic revolution in Greek sculpture is generally associated with one fundamental historical event, the Persian Wars; with two of the most important sculptors of the late sixth–early fifth century BC, Kritios and Nesiotes; and with a sculptural group: the Tyrannicides. The chronological span between the end of the Persian Wars—marked by the destruction of the monuments on the Athenian Acropolis (480/79 BC)—and the beginning of the construction of the Parthenon (448/7 BC) is commonly labelled as the “Severe style period” in archaeological literature.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Polykleitos at Work</title>
      <link>/the-artist/10-haga-et-al/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/the-artist/10-haga-et-al/</guid>
      <description>Introduction For more than a century, arguments have been made both for and against the identification of the Doryphoros with the “Canon” of Polykleitos without a definitive conclusion being reached. Although the most important information is Pliny’s famous phrase, it also is the cause of controversy. He writes: “Polyclitus &amp;hellip; et doryphorum viriliter puerum fecit. quem canona artifices vocant, liniamenta artis ex eo petentes veluti a lege quadam &amp;hellip;” [“Polykleitos made &amp;hellip; and a Doryphoros, a virile-looking boy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Looking at the Bronze of Lost Sculptures</title>
      <link>/the-artist/11-falaschi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/the-artist/11-falaschi/</guid>
      <description>At the beginning of his writing On the Pythian Responses (De Pythiae oraculis), Plutarch dedicates several chapters (395b–396c) to the blue patina that characterized bronze Delphian votive offerings. Several studies have tried to give a scientific explanation for this patina and to identify it in artworks brought to light during excavations.1 This contribution focuses on a different aspect, strictly linked to the reception and perception of art in the Imperial age.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mobility and Migration</title>
      <link>/the-artist/12-horne/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/the-artist/12-horne/</guid>
      <description>Our understanding of the ancient sculptor’s profession, like so much of ancient sculpture itself, is fragmentary. The particulars of ephemeral facets such as training and organization come primarily from literary sources, supplemented by meager evidence found at sites of bronze and marble sculpture production. As a result, the clearest picture forms around the major figures of antiquity such as Praxiteles and Pheidias, who, according to ancient accounts, were sought out to complete major works across the Aegean.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Praxiteles’ Bronze Sculpture at Delphi</title>
      <link>/the-artist/abstract-ajootian/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/the-artist/abstract-ajootian/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>