<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The-hellenistic-easts on </title>
    <link>/the-hellenistic-east/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in The-hellenistic-easts on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <atom:link href="/the-hellenistic-east/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The Hellenistic East</title>
      <link>/the-hellenistic-east/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/the-hellenistic-east/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Influence of East and West on Bronze Objects Found in Central Anatolia</title>
      <link>/the-hellenistic-east/21-paterakis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/the-hellenistic-east/21-paterakis/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper reviews the influences from the East and West on bronzes (copper-tin alloys) found in Anatolia while focusing on the archaeological finds from the site of Kaman-Kalehöyük. Given its location along ancient trade routes, Kaman-Kalehöyük may have served as a conduit for the intraregional exchange of materials and manufacturing technologies. We examine some of these influences and movements as they relate to ancient bronze technology in Anatolia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kaman-Kalehöyük consists of a tell, or mound, 280 meters in diameter and 16 meters high (918 x 52 ft.). It was a rural settlement situated 100 kilometers (62 miles) southeast of Ankara and 3 kilometers (1 &amp;frac14; miles) east of Kaman in Kırşehir province, in Central Anatolia (&lt;a href=&#34;#21.1&#34;&gt;fig. 21.1&lt;/a&gt;). Since excavation commenced in 1986, cultural levels have been traced from the Early Bronze Age (EBA) through the Ottoman period.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The Japanese Institute of Anatolian Archaeology (JIAA) was established near Kaman in 1998 by the Middle East Culture Center in Tokyo. Two new excavations were initiated in 2009: Buklukale to the Northwest and Yassihoyuk to the East.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



  
  

    
    
    &lt;figure class=&#34;q-figure&#34; id=&#34;21.1&#34;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&#34;q-figure__wrapper&#34;&gt;
        
          &lt;img  src=&#34;../figures/fig_21.01_Paterakis.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
        
        

      &lt;/div&gt;
      
      
        &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;q-figure-label&#34;&gt;Figure 21.1. &lt;/span&gt;Map showing the location of Kaman-Kalehöyük in relation to Ankara in Turkey. Photo: © Middle Eastern Culture Center in Japan&lt;/figcaption&gt;
      
      
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    

  




&lt;h2 id=&#34;early-bronze-age&#34;&gt;Early Bronze Age&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kaman-Kalehöyük excavations have thus far yielded a total of 9,120 catalogued copper and copper-alloy objects, including arrowheads, spearheads, awls, chisels, axes, pins, rings, stamp seals, and fibulae. A few of these objects have undergone compositional analysis. In the middle of the fourth millennium BC, objects were made from arsenical copper in Anatolia and copper, lead, and silver were mined in the Troad.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The earliest instance of bronze in Anatolia dates from the early third millennium BC (EBA). The sources of tin in Bronze Age Turkey have yet to be located; if small deposits of tin did exist in northwest Anatolia, they were soon exhausted.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Instead, throughout the Bronze Age, the Anatolians traded their plentiful silver for tin, derived most likely from Afghanistan. In the third millennium BC, pure copper, bronze, and arsenical copper were all being used in Anatolia, though bronze was more common in the Troad than in Central Anatolia.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; By the second millennium BC (MBA), arsenical copper was still more common that bronze in Anatolia while bronze artifacts were more prevalent at Kanesh-Kültepe in Central Anatolia.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:6&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The development of copper-alloy metallurgy followed similar paths in Anatolia and Mesopotamia throughout the Bronze Age, with the practice of interring bronze instead of arsenical copper objects in elite burials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;middle-bronze-age&#34;&gt;Middle Bronze Age&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bronze working in the Assyrian Colony period is examined starting with Kanesh-Kültepe, located 192 kilometers (120 miles) southeast of Kaman-Kalehöyük. Kanesh-Kültepe was the capital of the kingdom of Kanesh and during the Assyrian Colony period in the MBA served as the administrative and distribution center of the colony network in Anatolia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2004, X-ray fluorescence (XRF) analysis of numerous copper alloy objects from the MBA (1945–1730 BC) at Kanesh-Kültepe identified small ornamental objects as arsenical bronze and larger weapons as leaded bronze, indicating the intentional selection of arsenic and lead.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:7&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The authors believe these results indicate the selective use of arsenic-bearing sulfide copper ores. Copper-alloy metallurgy during the Assyrian Colony period was heavily influenced by technology in the East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;trade-networks&#34;&gt;Trade Networks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clay tablets from Kanesh-Kültepe document the trade in tin between the East and Anatolia: as much as two tons of tin per year were imported into Kanesh-Kültepe.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:8&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Metal workshops with crucibles and molds have been discovered at Kültepe.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:9&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Complex trade networks developed during the Bronze Age. A cuneiform tablet dating from the eighteenth century BC in Syria documents the distribution of tin to Ugarit and as far west as Crete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A trade route leads from Assur, the capital of the Assyrian Empire (located today in modern Iraq), northwest through Kanesh-Kültepe into Central Anatolia.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:10&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The three sites being excavated by the JIAA—Kaman-Kalehöyük, Yassihoyuk, and Buklukale—are all situated along this route, which promoted Assyrian Colony trade (see &lt;a href=&#34;#21.1&#34;&gt;fig. 21.1&lt;/a&gt;). In addition to the silver being traded from Anatolia for tin from Afghanistan, there was copper from Cyprus flowing into the Near East in the EBA and MBA (nineteenth century BC).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:11&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This trade persisted into the Late Bronze Age (LBA), as we know from the Uluburun shipwreck, which sank off the coast of Turkey while carrying ingots of copper and tin, probably on its way to or from Syria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;evidence-of-bronze-manufacture-discovered-by-the-jiaa&#34;&gt;Evidence of Bronze Manufacture Discovered by the JIAA&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evidence of bronze manufacture consists of numerous crucibles and molds from the three sites excavated by the JIAA: 33 stone molds for the casting of metal objects have been found dating from the Bronze Age and Iron Age, 27 of which derive from Kaman-Kalehöyük. A rectangular, two-sided mold (KL05-34; &lt;a href=&#34;#21.2&#34;&gt;fig. 21.2&lt;/a&gt;) has parallels in Hattusa, the capital during the Hittite Empire period, and dates to the LBA, Hittite Empire period (1400–1200 BC).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:12&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It was used for casting styli, small figurines, and an eight-spoked wheel.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:13&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Another rectangular mold (KL88-127) found at Kaman-Kalehöyük was used for casting arrowheads and other unidentified objects.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:14&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



  
  

    
    
    &lt;figure class=&#34;q-figure&#34; id=&#34;21.2&#34;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&#34;q-figure__wrapper&#34;&gt;
        
          &lt;img  src=&#34;../figures/fig_21.02_Paterakis.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
        
        

      &lt;/div&gt;
      
      
        &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;q-figure-label&#34;&gt;Figure 21.2. &lt;/span&gt;Stone mold from Kaman-Kalehöyük, inv. KL05-34. Photo: © Middle Eastern Culture Center in Japan&lt;/figcaption&gt;
      
      
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    

  




&lt;p&gt;The copper slags from Kaman-Kalehöyük were analyzed using inductively coupled plasma optical emission spectroscopy (ICP-OES) and electron microprobe metallographic analysis (EPMA).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:15&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This study revealed the presence of iron and copper sulfide, indicating that copper sulfide ores (such as chalcopyrite) were smelted to obtain copper at the site during the MBA (1950–1400 BC). Differences in chemical composition among the copper slags indicate that copper ore or smelted copper came from different regions during this period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to a study in 2005, approximately 40 percent of the slag found at Kaman-Kalehöyük between 1996 and 2004 is copper slag with a glassy matrix, indicating copper refining in crucibles.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:16&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The slags were recovered in one area dating to the MBA Old Hittite Kingdom period (1700–1400 BC) and in another area from the Early Iron Age (1200–775 BC). Copper ore with lead and zinc impurities was more prevalent in the Early Iron Age than in the MBA, indicating different sources of copper ore throughout history. The selective use of copper ores containing arsenic impurities is evidenced by the detection of copper and tin in one crucible (KL140628) and copper and arsenic in another crucible (KL140710) with XRF analysis.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:17&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-iron-age&#34;&gt;The Iron Age&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The collapse of the Hittite Empire after 1180 BC led to the beginning of the Iron Age and a very complex period in the history of Central Anatolia. The Early Iron Age is often referred to as the Dark Age, in which a Neo-Hittite civilization sprung up. Kaman-Kalehöyük, Hattusa, and Alişar were three main Iron Age sites in what was previously Hittite territory. During the Iron Age, Kaman-Kalehöyük was exposed to diverse ethnic, cultural, and artistic influences, drawing from a wide radius. The Assyrians entered Central Anatolia in 838 BC, bringing with them strong artistic and cultural influences. They took control of Central Anatolia from 744 to 727 BC, forming the Neo-Assyrian Kingdom of Tabal. Concurrently with the Assyrian presence, an ever-growing Phrygian influence was felt at Kaman-Kalehöyük beginning in the late eighth century BC, with the expansion of the Phrygian Empire over the next few centuries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Late Iron Age, the Medes invaded Central Anatolia from northwest Iran and controlled the area to the east of the Halys River in the region of Kaman-Kalehöyük from around 605 to 550 BC. Northwest Iranian fibulae in the Kaman collection are evidence of this occupation. The Achaemenid Empire replaced the Median Empire from 550 to 334 BC; at this point, the Persian Royal road from Susa to Sardis was established that was used later during the Hellenistic period.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:18&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bronze-fibulae&#34;&gt;Bronze Fibulae&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bronze objects that most readily illustrate the intraregional exchanges and multiethnic influences at Kaman-Kalehöyük are the fibulae dating from the Middle Iron Age to the Hellenistic period. The earliest fibulae come from the Mediterranean area in the thirteenth century BC; they then spread to the Near East, where they were used until the seventh century BC.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:19&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; During the Middle Iron Age, the fibula was introduced to Central Anatolia, where it became very popular. From the beginning of the Kaman-Kalehöyük excavation in 1986, a total of 586 fibulae have been found. The most common type is the Phrygian fibula, followed in order of prominence by north Syrian, northwest Iranian, southeast Anatolian, Greek, and Aegean fibulae (&lt;a href=&#34;#21.3&#34;&gt;fig. 21.3&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:20&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:20&#34;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



  
  

    
    
    &lt;figure class=&#34;q-figure&#34; id=&#34;21.3&#34;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&#34;q-figure__wrapper&#34;&gt;
        
          &lt;img  src=&#34;../figures/fig_21.03_Paterakis.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
        
        

      &lt;/div&gt;
      
      
        &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;q-figure-label&#34;&gt;Figure 21.3. &lt;/span&gt;Top row, left to right: inv. KL08-8 (Phrygian); inv. KL87-2176 (north Syrian); inv. KL95-16 (northwest Iranian). Bottom row, left to right: inv. KL92-1075 (southeast Anatolian); inv. KL89-322 (Greek); inv. KL91-21 (Aegean). Photo: © Middle Eastern Culture Center in Japan&lt;/figcaption&gt;
      
      
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    

  




&lt;p&gt;The Phrygians were the first Anatolians (apart from the Ionians) to adopt the fibula, which they did around 750 BC.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:21&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:21&#34;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Horizontal horns projecting from the sides of the catch and the semicircular shape are the trademarks of the Phrygian fibula, characterized as Blinkenberg Type XII.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:22&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:22&#34;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The pin was usually cast separately and attached by insertion into a drilled hole. It is unusual for the pin to be preserved, as it has been in the Phrygian fibula in the top left of &lt;a href=&#34;#21.3&#34;&gt;figure 21.3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gordion, the capital of Phrygia, had abundant trade with the Greeks, resulting in the influx of Greek fibulae at Gordion and Phrygian metalwork in mainland Greece.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:23&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:23&#34;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Aegean and Greek fibulae have been found in many parts of Anatolia, including Kaman-Kalehöyük, as attested to by the Aegean and Greek fibulae (see &lt;a href=&#34;#21.3&#34;&gt;fig. 21.3&lt;/a&gt;, bottom row, center and right). In the Archaic period, the Anatolian kings, such as Midas of Gordion in Phrygia and Croesus of Sardis in Lydia, commissioned numerous works from Greek artists; by the sixth century BC, the art of Gordion and Sardis showed considerable Greek influence.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:24&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:24&#34;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three Phrygian and three north Syrian fibulae from Kaman-Kalehöyük were analyzed with XRF, X-ray diffraction, and X-radiography.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:25&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:25&#34;&gt;25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The fibulae were found to be copper-tin bronze with traces of arsenic, and some were intentionally leaded. Antinomy was found in the Phrygian fibulae and vanadium in a Syrian fibula. Arsenic and antimony were often added to copper, as was tin, to decrease the melting point, to improve hardness when cold working, to render a particular color to the metal, and to improve the quality of casting.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:26&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:26&#34;&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; According to John Twilley’s analysis, the levels of arsenic and antimony were not high enough to have been intentional additions and therefore none are considered to be arsenical copper.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:27&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:27&#34;&gt;27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The Anatolian highlands were rich in polymetallic ores containing many elements including arsenic and antimony, which may account for the Phrygian composition. The fact that vanadium was found only in the north Syrian fibula indicates a diversity of ores being smelted in Syria during this period. Zinc was not found in these Kaman fibulae whereas it was prevalent in several fibulae from Tumulus MM at Gordion.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:28&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:28&#34;&gt;28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few stone and ceramic molds for manufacturing fibulae have been discovered at Kaman-Kalehöyük. The ceramic mold pictured here (KL88-16; &lt;a href=&#34;#21.4&#34;&gt;fig. 21.4&lt;/a&gt;) was for the manufacture of a Phrygian type fibula.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:29&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:29&#34;&gt;29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Evidence of Greek influence is seen in the unfinished fibula (KL90-62; &lt;a href=&#34;#21.5&#34;&gt;fig. 21.5&lt;/a&gt;) found at Kaman-Kalehöyük.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:30&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:30&#34;&gt;30&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Although it closely resembles Blinkenberg Type XII 9h&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:31&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:31&#34;&gt;31&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; from the region of Ankara, it preserves the remnants of a transverse piece, similar to Blinkenberg Type XII 10a&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:32&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:32&#34;&gt;32&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; from Olympia, Greece. A series of studs along the bow and transverse piece would have completed this fibula.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;q-figure &#34;&gt;




  
  &lt;figure class=&#34;q-figure__inner-figure&#34; id=&#34;21.4&#34; &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;q-figure__wrapper&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img  src=&#34;../figures/fig_21.04_Paterakis.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
    
  &lt;/div&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;q-figure-label&#34;&gt;Figure 21.4. &lt;/span&gt;Ceramic fibula mold, inv. KL88-16. Photo:© Middle Eastern Culture Center in Japan&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  


  
  &lt;figure class=&#34;q-figure__inner-figure&#34; id=&#34;21.5&#34; &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;q-figure__wrapper&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img  src=&#34;../figures/fig_21.05_Paterakis.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
    
  &lt;/div&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;q-figure-label&#34;&gt;Figure 21.5. &lt;/span&gt;Bronze fibula, inv. KL90-62. Photo: © Middle Eastern Culture Center in Japan&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  


&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;h2 id=&#34;urartian-bronzes-at-kaman-kalehöyük&#34;&gt;Urartian bronzes at Kaman-Kalehöyük&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This period in the development of the bronze fibula in Anatolia was accompanied by the growth of the powerful Urartian Empire in eastern Anatolia. Urartu was a prominent metalworking center in the Near East in the first millennium BC. Various casting methods were used, after which articles were embellished with repoussé, engraving, chasing, tracing, inlaying, plating, granulation, soldering, and brazing.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:33&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:33&#34;&gt;33&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; First-millennium-BC Urartian bronze has a high proportion of copper-zinc-tin alloys, sometimes with lead, which has been attributed to the intentional smelting of polymetallic ores.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:34&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:34&#34;&gt;34&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Comparisons in alloy composition have been made with Greek bronzes from this period.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:35&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:35&#34;&gt;35&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Urartian bronze objects are found in Gordion and in many areas of Greece. Trade between Urartu and Gordion from 730 to 675 BC followed two east–west routes across northern and southern Anatolia.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:36&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:36&#34;&gt;36&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Given that Kaman is situated between the northern and southern routes, midway between Gordion and Urartu, it is not surprising that Urartian bronzes have been discovered in Kaman-Kalehöyük. A bronze object resembling a quiver (KL03000069) but of undetermined function was discovered in Kaman-Kalehöyük from a Late Iron Age layer dating to the seventh or sixth century BC. It was made from sheet metal that was decorated with repoussé, and it demonstrates several Urartian characteristics such as rows of chevrons alternating with what may be rows of four-legged animals (&lt;a href=&#34;#21.6&#34;&gt;fig. 21.6&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:37&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:37&#34;&gt;37&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



  
  

    
    
    &lt;figure class=&#34;q-figure&#34; id=&#34;21.6&#34;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&#34;q-figure__wrapper&#34;&gt;
        
          &lt;img  src=&#34;../figures/fig_21.06_Paterakis.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
        
        

      &lt;/div&gt;
      
      
        &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;q-figure-label&#34;&gt;Figure 21.6. &lt;/span&gt;Urartian bronze object, inv. KL03000069. Photo: © Middle Eastern Culture Center in Japan&lt;/figcaption&gt;
      
      
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    

  




&lt;p&gt;A bronze belt or strap showing strong Urartian characteristics (KL12000010) was found in thirty-four pieces and was reconstructed to a length of 45 centimeters (17 &amp;frac34; in.; &lt;a href=&#34;#21.7a&#34;&gt;fig. 21.7a&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:38&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:38&#34;&gt;38&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Double rows of decoration delineating horizontal bands of human and animal figures were a common motif on Urartian belts.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:39&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:39&#34;&gt;39&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In raking light, it is possible to distinguish similar two- and four-legged creatures along two registers on an Urartian belt fragment in the Metropolitan Museum of Art (&lt;a href=&#34;#21.7b&#34;&gt;fig. 21.7b&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:40&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:40&#34;&gt;40&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Extensive corrosion of the Urartian bronzes found at Kaman-Kalehöyük impedes a more precise iconographical interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;



  
  

    
    
    &lt;figure class=&#34;q-figure&#34; id=&#34;21.7a&#34;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&#34;q-figure__wrapper&#34;&gt;
        
          &lt;img  src=&#34;../figures/fig_21.07a_Paterakis.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
        
        

      &lt;/div&gt;
      
      
        &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;q-figure-label&#34;&gt;Figure 21.7a. &lt;/span&gt;Fragment of Urartian bronze belt with four-legged figure delineated, inv. KL12000010. Photo: © Middle Eastern Culture Center in Japan&lt;/figcaption&gt;
      
      
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    

  






  
  

    
    
    &lt;figure class=&#34;q-figure&#34; id=&#34;21.7b&#34;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&#34;q-figure__wrapper&#34;&gt;
        
          &lt;img  src=&#34;../figures/fig_21.07b_Paterakis.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
        
        

      &lt;/div&gt;
      
      
        &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;q-figure-label&#34;&gt;Figure 21.7b. &lt;/span&gt;Urartian bronze belt, inv. 52.123 Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York. Photo: © Metropolitan Museum of Art&lt;/figcaption&gt;
      
      
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    

  




&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-hellenistic-period&#34;&gt;The Hellenistic Period&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the conquest of Anatolia by Alexander the Great and his death in 323 BC in Babylon, the Seleucid Empire took over much of Central Anatolia, including Kaman-Kalehöyük, from around 312 BC. Under the influence of the ruling Seleucid dynasty, which preserved and promoted Hellenistic culture, a strong Hellenistic influence was felt in Gordion as well as in Kanesh-Kültepe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In about 279 BC the Celts invaded Central Anatolia from Thrace and established the Galatian Empire. The Galatians took over a small area of the Seleucid Empire, making Ankara their capital city. The Hellenistic cities and King Attalus of Pergamon fought the Seleucids and the Galatians, confining them to their own territories, which included Kaman-Kalehöyük. Galatia was much less affected by the Hellenistic movement than was Pergamon, where Hellenistic influences strongly took hold. These influences are most noticeable in the silver coins minted by the later Galatian rulers.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:41&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:41&#34;&gt;41&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Habitation during the Hellenistic period appears to have shifted for the most part off the mound and into surrounding areas. A paleo-environmental study by Kaoru Kashima has determined that rising waters from heavy rainfall partially submerged the mound, which is situated on the lowest terrace of an alluvial fan on the side of Mount Baran.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:42&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:42&#34;&gt;42&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In spite of this population displacement, a few Hellenistic artifacts have been recovered from Kaman-Kalehöyük, such as silver coins of Alexander the Great, a small marble bust, and a terracotta figurine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Skeletal remains of Galatian cult practice in the form of human and animal sacrifices during the Hellenistic period have also been recovered from the mound.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:43&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:43&#34;&gt;43&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Round pits previously used for grain storage were adopted by the Galatians as repositories for human and animal bodies. The Galatians were known to hold sacrificial rituals during the Hellenistic period in Central Anatolia, and similar burials have been found at Gordion from the Galatian occupation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considerable evidence of copper and bronze refining and manufacture has been discovered at Kaman-Kalehöyük from the MBA (1950–1400 BC), when technological and artistic influences came largely from Assyria and Mesopotamia. Copper and bronze refining and manufacture continued there in the Early and Middle Iron Age (ca. 750–ca. 600 BC), a period when fibulae were very popular in Central Anatolia. Greek influence in the Phrygian capital of Gordion preceding the Hellenistic period undoubtedly affected Kaman-Kalehöyük; increased contact with Gordion during the expansion of the Phrygian kingdom is evidenced by the large number of Phrygian fibulae found at the site. The unfinished Phrygian fibula found in Kaman-Kalehöyük, resembling Blinkenberg Type XII 10a found in Olympia, strongly suggests influence from mainland Greece in the eighth century BC (&lt;a href=&#34;#21.5&#34;&gt;fig. 21.5&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An in-depth study of copper and bronze working is needed at Kaman-Kalehöyük, to examine the relationship between slag, crucibles, molds, copper and bronze artifacts, and related architectural remains. Such study will elucidate the contribution of this site to the development of the metallurgical industry in Central Anatolia during the Bronze and Iron Ages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;notes&#34;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Omura 2011.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;Omura 2008.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;Pernicka et al. 2003, 145.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;Pernicka et al. 2003, 146.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;Stech 1999, 64; Pernicka et al. 2003.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;Stech 1999, 64.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;Masubuchi et al. 2004, 159–60.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;Hemingway 2014, 29–30.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;See Lehner 2014.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;Barjamovic 2011, map insert in back cover.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;Hemingway 2014, 31.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;Boehmer 1979, 62, plate 38, no. 3849a–e.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;Omura 2006, 23, 32–33, color photos 14–15, figs. 59–61 .
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;Mori and Omura 1993, 68, fig. 12.5; 70, plate 1.11.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;Akanuma 2007.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34;&gt;Masubuchi and Nakai 2005.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34;&gt;JIAA 2014.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:18&#34;&gt;French 1998, 22; Sams 2011, 614.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:18&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:19&#34;&gt;Stronach 1959.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:19&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:20&#34;&gt;Yamashita 2000; for KL87-2176, see Mikami and Omura 1992, 48, fig. 11.12, and 57, plate 6.3; for KL89-322, see Omura 1991, 438, Resim 6.5.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:20&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:21&#34;&gt;Muscarella 1988, 425.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:21&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:22&#34;&gt;Blinkenberg 1926; Muscarella 1967, 48.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:22&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:23&#34;&gt;Vassileva 2012, 115, 123.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:23&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:24&#34;&gt;Harl 2011, 757.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:24&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:25&#34;&gt;Twilley 1996.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:25&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:26&#34;&gt;Eremin 2014, 73.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:26&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:27&#34;&gt;Twilley 1996, 238.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:27&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:28&#34;&gt;Steinberg 1981, 289.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:28&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:29&#34;&gt;Mori and Omura 1993, 68, plate 12.6, and 70, plate 1.10.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:29&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:30&#34;&gt;Omura 1992, 331, Resim 7.4.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:30&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:31&#34;&gt;Blinkenberg 1926, 215.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:31&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:32&#34;&gt;Blinkenberg 1926, 217.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:32&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:33&#34;&gt;Piotrovskii 1967; Wartke 2007, 416.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:33&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:34&#34;&gt;Eremin 2014, 81.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:34&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:35&#34;&gt;Hughes et al. 1981, 144.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:35&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:36&#34;&gt;Birmingham 1961, 192.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:36&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:37&#34;&gt;Dubin 2016.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:37&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:38&#34;&gt;Tsatsouli 2016, 124–27.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:38&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:39&#34;&gt;Ergürer 2010, 12, 14, 17, 21, figs. 1, 5, 12, 19 (from Kellner 1991, figs. 8, 122, 182, 185).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:39&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:40&#34;&gt;Muscarella 1988, 433, no. 578; Metropolitan Museum of Art 2016, inv. 52.123; Tsatsouli 2016, 124–27.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:40&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:41&#34;&gt;Darbyshire et al. 2000, 95.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:41&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:42&#34;&gt;Kashima 2008, 262.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:42&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:43&#34;&gt;Matsumura 2007, 97.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:43&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Portrait of a Hellenistic Ruler in the National Museum of Iran</title>
      <link>/the-hellenistic-east/22-Lindstroem/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/the-hellenistic-east/22-Lindstroem/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;discovery-in-1935-in-ancient-elymais&#34;&gt;Discovery in 1935 in Ancient Elymais&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The portrait head of a Hellenistic ruler (&lt;a href=&#34;#22.1&#34;&gt;fig. 22.1&lt;/a&gt;) was discovered more than eighty years ago in Kal-e Chendar in the valley of Shami, north of Izeh in present-day Khuzistan (ancient Elymais). It is often stated that Sir Aurel Stein (1862–1943), the famous Hungaro-British explorer, excavated the portrait. In fact, it was found accidently in the course of construction work, shortly before Stein arrived at the site.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In 1935 local semi-nomadic Bakhtiaris had been obliged to settle down, and as they dug the foundations for a dwelling they discovered fragments of ancient statues made of bronze and marble. Of these the so-called Parthian nobleman—a nearly complete statue of a man in Parthian dress, some 2 meters (6 &amp;frac12; ft.) high—is the most well-known.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; When the military governor of the district came to learn of the discoveries, he ordered that the site be left undisturbed and transported all the finds to his house at Malamir (modern Izeh). About six months later, Stein visited the region during his Fourth Expedition into Iran. He saw the finds at the governor’s house, took some photographs of the statues, and decided to visit the place of their discovery.&lt;/p&gt;



  
  

    
    
    &lt;figure class=&#34;q-figure&#34; id=&#34;22.1&#34;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&#34;q-figure__wrapper&#34;&gt;
        
          &lt;img  src=&#34;../figures/fig_22.01_Lindstroem.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
        
        

      &lt;/div&gt;
      
      
        &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;q-figure-label&#34;&gt;Figure 22.1. &lt;/span&gt;Bronze portrait head of a ruler. Tehran, National Museum of Iran, inv. 2477. Photo G. Lindström&lt;/figcaption&gt;
      
      
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    

  




&lt;h2 id=&#34;excavations-by-sir-aurel-stein-in-1936&#34;&gt;Excavations by Sir Aurel Stein in 1936&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stein excavated at Kal-e Chendar for six days between January 28 and February 3, 1936.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; During this period, he conducted a brief survey of the whole site and opened a trench in the area where the sculptures were found. He found the remains of a quadrangular enclosure, about 12.5 by 23.5 meters (41 x 77 ft.), with an altar built of burnt bricks in the center. These suggested to Stein a shrine with veranda-like halls along the walls and a central area left open to the sky. The structural remains are documented in a sketch plan, with marks for the findspots of the objects recovered during the archaeological investigations and for the earlier excavated sculptural fragments, as reported by the local villagers.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Altogether, fragments of seven large-scale bronze sculptures and six smaller figures of bronze and marble were found. Based on the presumed dating of the sculptures, Stein wrote, “it has proved a shrine where local worship, continued into Parthian times, had in a syncretistic fashion common to the Near East combined Hellenistic cult of Greek divinities with the worship of deified royal personages, perhaps from Alexander the Great down to Iranian chiefs for us nameless.”&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recent-investigations-at-kal-e-chendar-by-the-iranian-italian-mission&#34;&gt;Recent Investigations at Kal-e Chendar by the Iranian-Italian mission&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite these extraordinary discoveries, Kal-e Chendar soon fell into oblivion, at least among archaeologists.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:6&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; However, in 2012 the Iranian-Italian Joint Expedition in Khuzistan carried out a new survey and started archaeological investigations.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:7&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; According to their preliminary results, the site consisted of at least three monumental terraces. The photographs taken by Stein in 1936 enabled the archaeologists to determine the approximate spot where Stein excavated, which is now covered over and cultivated. The Stein trench is at a peripheral part of the largest terrace, which extends for more than 6,000 square meters (65,000 sq. ft.). Therefore, the discovered enclosure was hardly the main building of the sanctuary. Rather, the focal point was a large temple, which is attested so far only by column drums and blocks of ancient masonry, scattered on the surface or re-used in the walls of modern houses. The sculptures found in 1935 and 1936 most likely belong to the presumed temple, and their number and quality indicate that it must have been one of the most renowned religious places of ancient Elymais. Given the style and date of the ruler portrait in question, the sanctuary must have been established already in Hellenistic times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-head&#34;&gt;The Head&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The head was found in two pieces, obviously severed in antiquity. The first published photo shows both fragments lying on their sides, juxtaposed (&lt;a href=&#34;#22.2&#34;&gt;fig. 22.2&lt;/a&gt;). Although Stein noted that the two parts fit together, the side views of the faces differ sufficiently that some scholars assume that they represent two different portraits.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:8&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In any case, for aesthetic and museum reasons the two parts were fixed together sometime in the 1960s and the join was covered with epoxy. The fragments comprise a clean-shaven face with both ears, parts of the hair, and the front part of the neck, which is bent forward. The upper and posterior parts of the head were detached from the face and are not preserved.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:9&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Although there is a deep dent in the right cheek, the appearance of the right side is still vigorous. The left side is quite different: the jawline is bent outward forming a chubby cheek (see &lt;a href=&#34;#22.5&#34;&gt;fig. 22.5&lt;/a&gt;). The frontal view shows that the entire face is bent toward the right side along the bridge of the nose. All in all, the facial features are so distorted that it is impossible to identify the ruler.&lt;/p&gt;



  
  

    
    
    &lt;figure class=&#34;q-figure&#34; id=&#34;22.2&#34;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&#34;q-figure__wrapper&#34;&gt;
        
          &lt;img  src=&#34;../figures/fig_22.02_Lindstroem.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
        
        

      &lt;/div&gt;
      
      
        &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;q-figure-label&#34;&gt;Figure 22.2. &lt;/span&gt;Two fragments of the bronze portrait head as published by A. Stein in 1940. After Stein 1940, pl. IV&lt;/figcaption&gt;
      
      
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    

  




&lt;h2 id=&#34;proposed-identifications&#34;&gt;Proposed Identifications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, numerous attempts have been made to identify the sitter. The size and the quality of the head indicate that it is a portrait of a ruler. And because it was discovered in Iran it is most probably a king of the Seleucid dynasty, which ruled the Hellenistic East until the Parthian invasion of 141 BC. Several identifications have been proposed from Alexander the Great&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:10&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to Antiochus I and II or Seleucus II,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:11&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to Antiochus III,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:12&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Antiochus IV,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:13&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and Antiochus VII.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:14&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It has even been proposed that the head represents Kamnaskires I,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:15&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; the first king of a local Elymaean dynasty ruling under Parthian domination from the middle of the second century BC. But most of these identifications are merely speculations, based on historical considerations rather than on a comparison with the coin portraits of the respective kings. Because of the strong deformation of the face, some scholars admit that it is difficult or even impossible to identify the ruler.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:16&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; So despite Stein’s hope that expert examination of the head might lead to a solid identification, the depicted ruler even today is still unknown.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:17&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-deliberate-breakage-of-the-head&#34;&gt;The Deliberate Breakage of the Head&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, the head was broken into two pieces, and not merely for the purpose of melting down the metal. A photograph taken by Stein, preserved in the archives of the British Library and published here for the first time (&lt;a href=&#34;#22.3&#34;&gt;fig. 22.3&lt;/a&gt;), shows the assembled parts of the head before restoration. The marks of a chisel are visible at the left side of the forehead (&lt;a href=&#34;#22.4&#34;&gt;fig. 22.4&lt;/a&gt;). From there, the cut runs along the bridge of the nose to the chin. This is not the easiest line along which to divide a bronze head, therefore a non-pragmatic purpose of the partition has to be considered. Moreover, the dent in the right cheek was the result of several heavy blows with an edged tool, presumably a stone. The entire nose is pushed to the right side of the face, compressing the right side of the nose and bulging out the left cheek. The brutality of the actions and the deliberate distortion is obvious. Presumably the damage is a form of &lt;em&gt;damnatio memoriae&lt;/em&gt; and the performers aimed to destroy the image and the memory of the ruler.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;q-figure q-figure-grid&#34;&gt;




  
  &lt;figure class=&#34;q-figure__inner-figure&#34; id=&#34;22.3&#34; style=&#34;flex-basis: calc( (100% - 2rem) / 2)&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;q-figure__wrapper&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img  src=&#34;../figures/fig_22.03_Lindstroem.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
    
  &lt;/div&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;q-figure-label&#34;&gt;Figure 22.3. &lt;/span&gt;Two fragments of the head as assembled in the British Museum in 1937. © The British Library Board, India Office Select Materials, Prints and Drawings Collection, Photo 392/39 (406)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  


  
  &lt;figure class=&#34;q-figure__inner-figure&#34; id=&#34;22.4&#34; style=&#34;flex-basis: calc( (100% - 2rem) / 2)&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;q-figure__wrapper&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img  src=&#34;../figures/fig_22.04_Lindstroem.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
    
  &lt;/div&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;q-figure-label&#34;&gt;Figure 22.4. &lt;/span&gt;Detail of fig. 22.3 showing cut marks made by a chisel. © The British Library Board, India Office Select Materials, Prints and Drawings Collection, Photo 392/39 (406)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  


&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-first-reconstruction&#34;&gt;A First Reconstruction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A first attempt to reconstruct the original features of the portrait was made soon after its discovery. This is attested only by a photograph taken by Stein in 1937, which is reproduced in Michael Rostovtzeff’s &lt;em&gt;The&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Social and Economic History of the Hellenistic World&lt;/em&gt; (Rostovtzeff 1941). The caption reads: “photograph of a lead cast supplied by Sir Aurel Stein” and “&lt;em&gt;pro tempore&lt;/em&gt; in the British Museum.”&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:18&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This label seems surprising, because the piece of art was found in Iran and has long since been in the National Museum of Iran. But indeed the head made a short trip to London. Because Stein was a famous explorer, the Iranian authorities allowed him temporarily to send all finds from his expedition to the British Museum for examination.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:19&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; During its time in London, the sculptor Frank Bowcher made a piece mold of the head and produced a lead cast.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:20&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:20&#34;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The sculptor added the eye, squeezed out the depression in the right cheek, and put some parts of the head back in place, such as the neck.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:21&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:21&#34;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Unfortunately, this reconstruction could not be traced in the British Museum or in any other collection in the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-intended-reconstruction-of-the-original-features-of-the-head&#34;&gt;The Intended Reconstruction of the Original Features of the Head&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reconstruction of the original features of the Hellenistic ruler has been attempted again in a project started in August 2015. Based upon a series of digital images and by means of photogrammetry, a three-dimensional state model was created (&lt;a href=&#34;#22.5&#34;&gt;fig. 22.5&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:22&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:22&#34;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This model, in turn, will serve to reconstruct the original physiognomy of the face by means of computer animation. For example, relatively well-preserved sections such as the upper cheek and eye of the right side of the face can be cut out, mirrored, and inserted on the other side of the head. Dents and bulges can be straightened, and the cracks joined. But it is still a work in progress. The reconstructed portrait should enable comparison to coin portraits of the Seleucid kings. Of course, such an approach has to consider the problems particular to comparison between a three-dimensional representation to two-dimensional coin designs. Nevertheless, we hope be able to identify the sitter of the bronze portrait in the National Museum of Iran.&lt;/p&gt;



  
  

    
    
    &lt;figure class=&#34;q-figure&#34; id=&#34;22.5&#34;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&#34;q-figure__wrapper&#34;&gt;
        
          &lt;img  src=&#34;../figures/fig_22.05_Lindstroem.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
        
        

      &lt;/div&gt;
      
      
        &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;q-figure-label&#34;&gt;Figure 22.5. &lt;/span&gt;State model of the head: profiles, front, and back view. Image: Th. Kersten and M. Lindstaedt, Photogrammetry &amp;amp; Laserscanning Lab, HafenCity University Hamburg.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
      
      
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    

  




&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-remains-of-the-sculpture&#34;&gt;Other Remains of the Sculpture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The photos from the Stein archive show further pieces of bronze sculpture, most likely belonging to the same sculpture as the bronze head in question. Some pieces were already illustrated in Stein’s report, but others have not been published until now. Unlike Stein’s plates, the photos from the archive provide an exact size scale. Five fragments show similar proportions, which are in turn in accordance with the scale of the head. Using the photos from the archives, colleagues at the National Museum of Iran easily identified the requested pieces, some of which were on display in the Museum halls and others located in storage. Gathered together for the first time, it turned out that three fragments fit together.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:23&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:23&#34;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; They form a raised left arm, the fingers in the pose of grasping a long object, perhaps a spear (&lt;a href=&#34;#22.6&#34;&gt;fig. 22.6&lt;/a&gt;). Being significantly larger than the arm of an average-size European, the bronze arm indicates a sculpture slightly more than two meters (6 &amp;frac12; feet) tall. The inner surface of the sculptural fragment reveals details that are related to the casting process: two parallel raised lines with soft surfaces indicate a wax-to-wax join (&lt;a href=&#34;#22.7&#34;&gt;fig. 22.7&lt;/a&gt;). Apparently two halves of a master mold met there, each lined with rectangular-cut wax sheets, and the seam between these sheets was covered with a wax strip. Fragments of a bare left leg from below the knee to above the ankle and of a right arm show the same technological features.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:24&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:24&#34;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Therefore, they most likely belong to the same sculpture.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:25&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:25&#34;&gt;25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;q-figure q-figure-grid&#34;&gt;




  
  &lt;figure class=&#34;q-figure__inner-figure&#34; id=&#34;22.6&#34; style=&#34;flex-basis: calc( (100% - 2rem) / 2)&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;q-figure__wrapper&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img  src=&#34;../figures/fig_22.06_Lindstroem.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
    
  &lt;/div&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;q-figure-label&#34;&gt;Figure 22.6. &lt;/span&gt;Raised left arm of the sculpture, compared to the arm of a man 1.76 meters tall. Photo G. Lindström&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  


  
  &lt;figure class=&#34;q-figure__inner-figure&#34; id=&#34;22.7&#34; style=&#34;flex-basis: calc( (100% - 2rem) / 2)&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;q-figure__wrapper&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img  src=&#34;../figures/fig_22.07_Lindstroem.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
    
  &lt;/div&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;q-figure-label&#34;&gt;Figure 22.7. &lt;/span&gt;Back and inside view of the left arm. Photo: G. Lindström&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  


&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;h2 id=&#34;reconstruction-of-the-statue-type&#34;&gt;Reconstruction of the Statue Type&lt;/h2&gt;



  
  

    
    
    &lt;figure class=&#34;q-figure q-float-right&#34; id=&#34;22.8&#34;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&#34;q-figure__wrapper&#34;&gt;
        
          &lt;img  src=&#34;../figures/fig_22.08_Lindstroem.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
        
        

      &lt;/div&gt;
      
      
        &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;q-figure-label&#34;&gt;Figure 22.8. &lt;/span&gt;Proposed reconstruction of the sculpture using scaled photos of the preserved fragments. Drawing and photos: G. Lindström&lt;/figcaption&gt;
      
      
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    

  




&lt;p&gt;The preserved bronze fragments represent less than twenty percent of the statue. However, the bare limbs suggest that it was an undraped male. And with the position of the arm one can infer a statue with a raised arm, leaning on a spear (&lt;a href=&#34;#22.8&#34;&gt;fig. 22.8&lt;/a&gt;). The princely pose and the size of the sculpture indicate that it represented a ruler, even if a diadem is not preserved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trudy S. Kawami (1987) noted that “the presence of such an important work so far from a major city is difficult to explain.”&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:26&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:26&#34;&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; However, judging from the first results of the Iranian-Italian excavations at Kal-e Chendar, the sculpture was erected at one of the most important religious places of ancient Elymais. From a Mediterranean point of view, the quality and “Greekness” of the reassembled statue may cause surprise, especially given its discovery in Iran. However, this just points out our limited knowledge of Hellenism in the regions east of the Tigris River.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;acknowledgments&#34;&gt;Acknowledgments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work was supported by the Fritz Thyssen Stiftung. My thanks go also to Dr. Jebrael Nokandeh, the director of the National Museum of Iran, who enabled the investigations, and to the entire museum staff, especially Firouzeh Sepidnameh (head of the Exhibition Department) and Masoumeh Ahmadi (International Affairs). Further thanks go to Ursula Sims-Williams, who drew my attention to the material of the Stein archives in the British Museum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;notes&#34;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;The account of the discovery follows the report by Stein 1938 and 1940.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;Canepa 2015, 85–87, fig. 6.4.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;First reports are Stein 1936 and 1938. The final report is included in Stein 1940, 130–35, 141–58.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;Stein 1940, 145, plan II.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;Stein 1940, 155.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;The Director of the Iranian Archaeological Services, André Godard, did a short investigation at the site in 1937, but the results are not published (Ghirshman 1976, 237). The structures recovered by Stein were already spoiled when the site was visited in 1968 by Klaus Schippmann (1971, 230) and in 1971 by Roman Ghirshman (Ghirshman 1976, 236).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;Messina and Mehr Kian 2014.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;Ghirshman 1962, 21 (“a seleucid king and his wife”); Colledge 1967, 156, 221 (“perhaps Antiochus IV and his queen”); idem. 1987, 152 (“a female and a male portrait head”); Parlasca 1991, 465 (“two bronze heads”); Fischer 1970, 53, n. 111 (“Antiochus VII and his son Seleucus”). Fleischer (2016) considered the present state of the head to be a modern pastiche of two different ancient fragments. But after viewing the image discovered during the present investigation (&lt;a href=&#34;#22.3&#34;&gt;fig. 22.3&lt;/a&gt;), he was convinced that they belong together (personal communication).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;Stein (1940, 151 plate 5.1) believed a top part of a bronze head with a diadem to belong to the face. Because the fragment could not be traced in the National Museum of Iran, a direct comparison to the face was not possible. In any case, the dissimilarities in the style of the hair and possible overlaps above the left temple suggest that the pieces do not belong together.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;Stein 1940, 151 (following a suggestion by the numismatist George F. Hill); Colledge 1977, 82; idem. 1984, 22.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;Mørkholm 1963, 67.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;Herrmann 1977, 39.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;Rostovtzeff 1941, 66, plate 10.1; Ghirshman 1954, 236, 278, plate 29b; idem. 1962, 20–21; 1976, 237; Mussche 1955–56, 61; vanden Berghe 1959, 64, plate 94c; Eddy 1961, 146; Richter 1965, 271; Porada 1962, 180, fig. 89; Lukonin 1967, plate 13; Colledge 1967, 156, 221; idem. 1977, 82; idem. 1984, 22; Herrmann 1977, 39; Parlasca 1991, 465. Sherwin-White (1984, 160) rules out an identification as Antiochus IV.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;Fischer 1970, 53 n. 111; Houghton 1989; Smith 1988, 81, 119, 173; idem. 1991, 226; Stewart 1990, 1: 218; 2: fig. 768.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;Godard 1962, 183. Canepa (2015, 85) and, based on historical considerations, Boyce and Grenet (1991, 43) suggest a king of a local Elymaean dynasty.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34;&gt;Identifications considered too problematic by Kyrieleis 1980, 22 n. 28; Kawami 1987, 28; Boyce and Grenet 1991, 42–43 (“identifications of the mask are risky”); Fleischer 1991, 105–106; Fleischer 2000; Fleischer 2016; Mathiesen 1992, 88–89.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34;&gt;Stein 1938, 325.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:18&#34;&gt;Rostovtzeff 1941, plate 10.1. The cast was already illustrated by Stein (1938, fig. 9) and Picard (1939, fig. 35) with no reference that it is a reconstruction.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:18&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:19&#34;&gt;Stein 1940, XIV; Sarkosh Curtis and Pazooki 2004, 24; Sims-Williams 2004, 1. Stein incorporated several objects into his own findings, even though they were discovered by the locals. In 1938 these objects, including the bronze head, were returned to Tehran.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:19&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:20&#34;&gt;This procedure is documented only in correspondence between Stein and Fred Andrews, who supervised the examinations at the British Museum. The letters are published in extracts by Sims-Williams 2004.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:20&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:21&#34;&gt;If compared with the corresponding view of the head, the reconstruction is quite reliable, even if Boyce and Grenet (1991, 43) state that important details appear to have been completed from imagination.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:21&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:22&#34;&gt;The photogrammetry and the creation of the state model were made by Prof. Thomas Kersten and Dr. Maren Lindstaedt of the Photogrammetry &amp;amp; Laserscanning Lab of the HafenCity University in Hamburg. They will also conduct the technical implementation of the reconstruction.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:22&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:23&#34;&gt;National Museum of Iran, inv. 2471: a hand considered by Stein (1940, 151 plate 5.4) to belong to a colossal sculpture; inv. 2874: a large part of the arm not mentioned by Stein but illustrated by Godard (1937, fig. 126); inv. 2473: a fragment of the lower arm mentioned by neither Stein nor Godard.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:23&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:24&#34;&gt;National Museum of Iran, inv. 2478, the leg: Stein 1940, 151 plate 5.6; inv. 2470: a piece of the right arm mentioned by neither Stein nor Godard.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:24&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:25&#34;&gt;Other remains of bronze sculpture from Kal-e Chendar, which were examined within the project, do not show the straight elevated lines on the interior surface.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:25&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:26&#34;&gt;Kawami 1987, 28.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:26&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Influence of Bronze Working on Roman Provincial Stone Sculpture</title>
      <link>/the-hellenistic-east/23-albertson/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/the-hellenistic-east/23-albertson/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The prosperity experienced by the elite of the ancient Romano-Syrian city of Palmyra from the late first century BC through the middle of the third century AD is perhaps most visible in their monumental family tombs and the funerary sculpture associated within these tombs. Among the types included within the well-known repertoire of Palmyran funerary reliefs are the distinctive &lt;em&gt;loculus&lt;/em&gt; plaques: rectangular limestone slabs covering the burial cavity, carved in high-relief with a bust depicting the individual interred and often accompanied by an Aramaic inscription denoting the occupant’s name, family lineage, and sometimes even the date of death. By about AD 200, the so-called “large banquet relief” and sarcophagi had also become mainstays within the Palmyran tomb.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Palmyra’s wealth attracted and supported an active artistic community specializing in the carving of stone, specifically the locally quarried limestone. Yet this is a group that did not exist prior to the late first century BC and therefore had no previous local tradition from which to draw. The evolution of Palmyran sculpture and its portraiture is thus characterized by the borrowing of features from outside sources and the adaptation of forms and techniques to meet local tastes. Argued here is that one of these outside sources was contemporary Graeco-Roman bronze statuary.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The physical evidence for the presence of bronze statuary at Palmyra is sparse. Only a handful of fragments remain: a sandaled foot with part of the lower leg from the Sanctuary of Bel; a section of drapery, a hand, and two feet clad in Parthian shoes from the Agora; and a miniature bust of a priest found in the Sanctuary of Nabû.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The context would suggest that the use of bronze was normally confined to honorific statues erected in prominent public areas. A better claim for the wider use of bronze statuary at Palmyra comes from the Tariff Law of AD 137, specifically lines 128–30, which state that bronze statuary coming into the city was to be taxed the same as ordinary bronze, i.e., one statue to be taxed based on half of its weight, two statues by the weight of one.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; These lines would seem to imply that bronze statues were being imported into the city in significant numbers, requiring them not only to be taxed but also to be qualified as to the manner by which they should be taxed.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An examination of the surviving corpus of Palmyran sculpture, particularly that originating from a funerary context and dealing with images of the deceased, would strongly suggest that certain techniques employed on metal were then imitated and adapted by local stone carvers. The features examined here are limited to those that can be documented in works of bronze and are markedly absent in Roman marble sculpture. Such features occur in some 60 to 70 pieces, out of a surviving corpus of some 2,000 examples of Palmyran funerary sculpture.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:6&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One prominent bronze feature seen in Palmyran stone sculpture is the incision of the eyebrows into a distinct herringbone pattern, sometimes referred to as caterpillar eyebrows (&lt;a href=&#34;#23.1&#34;&gt;figs. 23.1–2&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:7&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; One might be tempted to propose a Near Eastern origin for such a rendering of the brows; portraits of Gudea of Lagash instantly come to mind.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:8&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; However, there is no evidence to document a continuity of such a form from the late third millennium BC to the early first millennium AD in the sculpture of the ancient Near East. Instead there are more obvious and chronologically closer examples of incised herringbone eyebrows in Graeco-Roman bronze statuary. Among the examples are a series of Gallo-Roman heads from the first century AD, including two bronze busts depicting male youths now in the Getty Villa (&lt;a href=&#34;#23.3&#34;&gt;figs. 23.3–4&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:9&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; These can be supplemented by the bronze Doryphoros from the mid-first century BC context of the Villa dei Papiri at Herculaneum.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:10&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Within the realm of earlier Greek bronze statuary, the technique can be traced back through the Hellenistic to the late Classical period, as evidenced by the bronze head of a boxer from Olympia.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:11&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;q-figure q-figure-grid&#34;&gt;




  
  &lt;figure class=&#34;q-figure__inner-figure&#34; id=&#34;23.1&#34; style=&#34;flex-basis: calc( (100% - 2rem) / 2)&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;q-figure__wrapper&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img  src=&#34;../figures/fig_23.01_Albertson.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
    
  &lt;/div&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;q-figure-label&#34;&gt;Figure 23.1. &lt;/span&gt;Limestone &lt;em&gt;loculus&lt;/em&gt; plaque of Repabôl, son of Rustic’â, (son of) Šaddai, from Palmyra. ca. AD 180–200. Minneapolis, Minneapolis Institute of Arts inv. 2008.28.2. Photo: Minneapolis Institute of Arts, MN, USA / Gift of the Miller Family in memory of Dulcy B. Miller / Bridgeman Images)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  


  
  &lt;figure class=&#34;q-figure__inner-figure&#34; id=&#34;23.2&#34; style=&#34;flex-basis: calc( (100% - 2rem) / 2)&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;q-figure__wrapper&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img  src=&#34;../figures/fig_23.02_Albertson.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
    
  &lt;/div&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;q-figure-label&#34;&gt;Figure 23.2. &lt;/span&gt;Detail of fig. 23.1&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  


&lt;/figure&gt;




&lt;figure class=&#34;q-figure q-figure-grid&#34;&gt;




  
  &lt;figure class=&#34;q-figure__inner-figure&#34; id=&#34;23.3&#34; style=&#34;flex-basis: calc( (100% - 2rem) / 2)&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;q-figure__wrapper&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img  src=&#34;../figures/fig_23.03_Albertson.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
    
  &lt;/div&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;q-figure-label&#34;&gt;Figure 23.3. &lt;/span&gt;Bronze bust of a young male, from Roman Gaul. ca. AD 50–80. Malibu, J. Paul Getty Museum, Villa Collection inv. 89.AB.67.2. Photo: Courtesy of the J. Paul Getty Museum&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  


  
  &lt;figure class=&#34;q-figure__inner-figure&#34; id=&#34;23.4&#34; style=&#34;flex-basis: calc( (100% - 2rem) / 2)&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;q-figure__wrapper&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img  src=&#34;../figures/fig_23.04_Albertson.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
    
  &lt;/div&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;q-figure-label&#34;&gt;Figure 23.4. &lt;/span&gt;Detail of fig. 23.3&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  


&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;p&gt;A second feature found in Palmyran limestone sculpture that was certainly borrowed from contemporary bronze sculpture is the use of glass paste for the iris and pupil, in place of the more common incised iris and drilled pupil, which were then painted. As seen on the so-called Beauty of Palmyra in Copenhagen, a &lt;em&gt;loculus&lt;/em&gt; plaque belonging to an anonymous Palmyran matron carved in approximately AD 200–210, what normally remains is a large circular cavity with an inner flattened surface (&lt;a href=&#34;#23.5&#34;&gt;fig. 23.5&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:12&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The flat surface of the cavity has caused scholars to speculate that such eyes when seen in Palmyran sculpture originally would have had inserted irises of another material.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:13&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This assumption has proved to be correct, for among the series of ten surviving examples, one retains its original inserted eyes: a female head in the Los Angeles County Museum of Art (&lt;a href=&#34;#23.6&#34;&gt;fig. 23.6&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:14&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The extensively pitted material is glass paste, and its color, which appears black at first glance, is actually a dark blue. The insertion of the eyes as a separate entity has a long tradition in Greek statuary, but the insertion of only a circular iris has its best parallels in contemporary Roman statuary, most notably a series of Gallo-British examples, best illustrated by a recently discovered head of Marcus Aurelius now in the Ashmolean Museum (&lt;a href=&#34;#23.7&#34;&gt;fig. 23.7&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:15&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The fact that this technique may have been popular regionally in southeast Britain and northern Gaul does not rule out that the source is external and chronologically earlier. A bronze head of Hadrian, originally discovered in the Thames near London and currently in the British Museum, shows the method employed in official portraits of the emperors.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:16&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Two Etruscan bronze portraits of male youths from Fiesole dating to the third century BC may be the evidence needed to trace this bronze-working method back to Italy.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:17&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



  
  

    
    
    &lt;figure class=&#34;q-figure&#34; id=&#34;23.5&#34;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&#34;q-figure__wrapper&#34;&gt;
        
          &lt;img  src=&#34;../figures/fig_23.05_Albertson.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
        
        

      &lt;/div&gt;
      
      
        &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;q-figure-label&#34;&gt;Figure 23.5. &lt;/span&gt;Limestone &lt;em&gt;loculus&lt;/em&gt; plaque, “The Beauty of Palmyra,” from Palmyra. ca. AD 200–210. Copenhagen, Ny Carlsberg Glyptotek inv. 2795. Photo: Courtesy of the Ny Carlsberg Glyptotek, Copenhagen / Bridgeman Images&lt;/figcaption&gt;
      
      
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    

  






  
  

    
    
    &lt;figure class=&#34;q-figure&#34; id=&#34;23.6&#34;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&#34;q-figure__wrapper&#34;&gt;
        
          &lt;img  src=&#34;../figures/fig_23.06_Albertson.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
        
        

      &lt;/div&gt;
      
      
        &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;q-figure-label&#34;&gt;Figure 23.6. &lt;/span&gt;Limestone head of a woman, probably from a banquet relief, from Palmyra. ca. AD 200–220. Los Angeles, Los Angeles County Museum of Art inv. M.82.77.2, Gift of Robert Blaugrund. Photo: &lt;a href=&#34;http://collections.lacma.org/node/243803&#34;&gt;http://collections.lacma.org/node/243803&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
      
      
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    

  






  
  

    
    
    &lt;figure class=&#34;q-figure&#34; id=&#34;23.7&#34;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&#34;q-figure__wrapper&#34;&gt;
        
          &lt;img  src=&#34;../figures/fig_23.07_Albertson.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
        
        

      &lt;/div&gt;
      
      
        &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;q-figure-label&#34;&gt;Figure 23.7. &lt;/span&gt;Bronze head of Marcus Aurelius, found near Brackley, Northamptonshire (England). ca. AD 170. Oxford, Ashmolean Museum inv. AN 2011.46. Photo: © Ashmolean Museum, University of Oxford / Bridgeman Images&lt;/figcaption&gt;
      
      
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    

  




&lt;p&gt;The third feature associated with Graeco-Roman bronze sculpture and adopted into Palmyran stone sculpture is the finely incised bordering of the lips, physically enhancing the vermilion border and often with a triangular recession denoting the depression between the lobes of the lower lip (&lt;a href=&#34;#23.6&#34;&gt;fig. 23.6&lt;/a&gt;). This technique is nearly absent in Roman marble portraiture but well-known in bronze, as seen on the Croatian Apoxyomenos.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:18&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This form in metalworking is surely intended to denote a separation of what would be copper lips from the surrounding bronze flesh, and its origins may stem from an early period when the mouth could be cast separately.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:19&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it seems clear that contemporary bronze statuary was the source for certain features seen in Palmyran limestone sculpture, perhaps the more intriguing questions are when and why this influence occurred. Here we are fortunate in that the methodology exists to date each example of Palmyran funerary sculpture relatively securely to within a 20–25 year span. Such a process is made possible by the existence of examples in which the date of the deceased’s death, and presumably then the date of the relief’s carving, is given in the accompanying inscription.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:20&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:20&#34;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The formulation of an absolute chronology is further assisted by intact tomb groups, where the genealogical context allows each funerary relief to be assigned to its respective generation.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:21&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:21&#34;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; These datable examples then serve as chronological data points and, through a process of stylistic and typological comparison, allows the majority of undated examples to be dated. Consequently, a review of the chronology of those individual features discussed so far—herringbone eyebrows, inserted glass pastes for irises, and engraved lips—helps to shed light on the rationale behind the adoption of such features by Palmyran workshops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incised herringbone-shaped eyebrows can be documented on at least thirty-two examples at Palmyra (see Appendix 1). The form appears shortly after the middle of the second century. The earliest documented instance is the dated bust of ’Atê’aqab, in Istanbul, whose inscription gives AD 157 as the year of death.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:22&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:22&#34;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; However, half of the examples cluster roughly between the years AD 180 and 210. After about AD 210, only a handful of examples appear. The last dated example is the relief of Ḥaggûr, son of Malkû, in the American University Museum, Beirut, inscribed AD 236–237.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:23&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:23&#34;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Of note is the fact that all the known examples represent males, suggesting that Palmyran sculptures consciously saw this manner of rendering the eyebrows as a gender signifier. In addition, at Palmyra the apex of the chevron of each individual eyebrow is pointed toward the bridge of the nose (see &lt;a href=&#34;#23.2&#34;&gt;fig. 23.2&lt;/a&gt;), unlike that of any possible Mesopotamian or Graeco-Roman antecedent where the opposite direction is maintained (see &lt;a href=&#34;#23.6&#34;&gt;fig. 23.4&lt;/a&gt;. This suggests a distinctively Palmyran adaptation of the form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An inserted glass-paste iris and pupil makes its appearance within the Palmyran repertoire of forms in about AD 200. The Beauty of Palmyra in Copenhagen is the earliest (see &lt;a href=&#34;#23.5&#34;&gt;fig. 23.5&lt;/a&gt;). One fragmentary &lt;em&gt;loculus&lt;/em&gt; plaque of a woman&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:24&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:24&#34;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and three female heads, all probably originating from large banquet reliefs and including the example in the Los Angeles County Museum of Art (see &lt;a href=&#34;#23.6&#34;&gt;fig. 23.6&lt;/a&gt;),&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:25&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:25&#34;&gt;25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; fall into the period around AD 200–220. The other five remaining examples are male; all are heads originally belonging to either statues or large banquet reliefs, and all date to about AD 230–250, more likely later in this period than earlier.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:26&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:26&#34;&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Glass-paste eyes thus show an initial appearance in the Palmyran sculptors’ repertoire around AD 200–220, restricted at first to female portraiture. Then, perhaps after a brief pause, they reappear on male portraits for a short time toward the middle of the century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The earliest documented use of incisions bordering and detailing the lips at Palmyra is from “the month of Tebet 466” (January AD 155), the date found on the inscription accompanying the &lt;em&gt;loculus&lt;/em&gt; plaque of Bênnûr, son of Bar’â, in the Louvre.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:27&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:27&#34;&gt;27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; If we follow the examples listed by Gunhild Ploug, in her catalogue of Palmyran sculpture in the Ny Carlsberg Glyptotek, this relief and six others can be placed chronologically within the period of approximately AD 150–170.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:28&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:28&#34;&gt;28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Eight of her examples fall in the later decades of AD 170–190.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:29&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:29&#34;&gt;29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The fashion then quickly fades, with few examples appearing after about AD 200. It ultimately disappears by about AD 220.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:30&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:30&#34;&gt;30&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our ability to date Palmyran sculpture rather accurately provides us with an unexpected result when dealing with the proposed influences of bronze on stone. One might expect the influence of bronze statuary to have a collective role; in other words, all the features with bronze antecedents making an appearance simultaneously, then existing side-by-side to some extent, and ultimately falling out of fashion altogether. Yet at Palmyra this is not the case. Incised lip outlines reach their highpoint of popularity around AD 170–190, then rapidly drop out of use. Incised herringbone eyebrows come into existence around the same time, and show the greatest period of use around AD 180–210, when the lip outlining is already on the decline. Glass paste eyes appear some fifty years after the other bronze-working features, reaching a peak of popularity around AD 230–250, long after the others have essentially dropped out of use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surviving examples thus suggest that the borrowing from bronze statuary was not a wholesale process but one that was done piecemeal. Isolated, individual features were adopted from bronze working and inserted into what remained a predominantly limestone tradition of carving. In addition, it is extremely rare for more than two of the bronze-derived features to appear together on the same portrait. Only two or perhaps three examples from the entire corpus of Palmyran funerary sculpture fall into this category, the head in the Los Angeles County Museum of Art being one.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:31&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:31&#34;&gt;31&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; One could speculate that the allusion to bronze conferred a loftier status on the deceased’s image in stone. The large majority of the examples showing the influence of bronze-working fall into the category of “finer” works, that is, those characterized by a greater attention to detail, a softer modelling of features, and an overall finished appearance. Nevertheless, the chronology supports the idea that the process of selecting features from bronze statuary was random. This eclectic selection process in fact reflects the Palmyran sculptors’ entire approach. Analysis of Palmyran funerary reliefs has revealed that the sculptor began with a concept of a “portrait,” which the sculptor drew from a pre-established repertoire of forms. These forms guided the means of rendering the garments and the arrangement of their folds, the positioning of arms and hands, and the selection of attributes and personal adornment such as jewelry or hairstyle.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:32&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:32&#34;&gt;32&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Even what would normally be considered the distinct, individualized features of the subject—the facial features—are forms repeated from one portrait to another. This strict dependence on typology in Palmyran funerary sculpture sometimes resulted in the creation of identical images representing two different people and different images representing the same person.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:33&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:33&#34;&gt;33&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study of Palmyran portraiture shows clearly that there was a continuous process of selection by the artist from a prescribed corpus of forms, perhaps due to the nature of the sculptural environment in which these reliefs were displayed and an emphasis on conveying the identity of the deceased, both as an individual and as a member of a larger community. What perhaps makes Palmyran portraiture so distinct is the fact that this repertoire of forms is constantly being augmented, with new forms drawn externally from Graeco-Roman art, including forms, as shown here, created in imitation of contemporary sculpture cast in bronze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;appendix-1-palmyran-reliefs-with-incised-herringbone-eyebrows&#34;&gt;Appendix 1: Palmyran Reliefs with Incised Herringbone Eyebrows&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Items are in chronological order; all are &lt;em&gt;loculus&lt;/em&gt; plaques depicting males unless otherwise noted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Date (AD)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Example&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;150&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;157&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Istanbul, Archaeological Museum inv. 3840T (Ingholt 1928, 34–35 PS 11, plate 4; &lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;, 476 no. 4616, plate 47)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;160&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Once Berlin, collection von Hahn 462–63 (Ingholt 1928, 119 PS 252; &lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;, 462–63 no. 4573); Istanbul, Archaeological Museum inv. 3837T (Ingholt 1928, 117 PS 237; &lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;, 363 no. 4299, plate 48)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;170&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Paris Louvre inv. AO 28381 (Dentzer-Feydey and Teixidor 1993, 244 no. 237); Palmyra, Palmyra Museum inv. B2729/9166: statue (Charles-Gaffiot et al. 2001, 320 no. 26, fig. on 190); Palmyra, Palmyra Museum inv. 1951/7043 (Sadurska and Bounni 1994, 51–52 no. 59, fig. 114)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;180&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Palmyra, Palmyra Museum inv. 1955/7047 (Sadurska and Bounni 1994, 53–54 no. 63, fig. 92); New York, Sotheby’s (Sotheby’s 2007, lot 31)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;187&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;New Haven, Yale University Art Gallery inv. 1954.30.3 (&lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;, 454 no. 4549, plate 61)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;189&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;St. Petersburg, Hermitage inv. 8840 (&lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;, 360 no. 4292, plate 52)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;190&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;London, British Museum 125032 (Ingholt 1928, 112 PS 201; &lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;, 362–63 no. 4297, plate 52); Toronto, Royal Ontario Museum inv. 953x94.4 (Ingholt 1928, 113 n.1 PS 203); Gaziantep, Archaeological Museum inv. 211 (Parlasca 2005, 143, 148 fig. 4); Damascus, National Museum, from Hypogeum of Yarḥai (Tanabe 1986, plate 280, fig. 249); Jerusalem, Church of St. Anne, Museum inv. PB 2670: double bust (Ingholt 1928, 110 PS 183; &lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;, 374–75 no. 4329, plate 54); Minneapolis, Minneapolis Institute of Art acc. 2008.28.2 (&lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;, 393 no. 4379; Sotheby’s 2002, lot 119); Oslo, Museum of Cultural History inv. C42235 (Ingholt 1928, 114 PS 217; &lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;, 369 no. 4314, plate 53)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;200&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Copenhagen, Ny Carlsberg Glyptotek inv. 1043 (Ploug 1995, 174–76 no. 70); New York, Metropolitan Museum of Art acc. 02.29.2 (Ingholt 1928, 109 PS 171); London, British Museum 125020 (Ingholt 1928, 119 PS 246; &lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;, 372 no. 4323, plate 38); Copenhagen, NCG inv. 1145: head (Ploug 1995, 222–23 no. 92); Palmyra, Palmyra Museum inv. 8522/2321 (Charles-Gaffiot et al. 2001, 347 no. 163, fig. on 271); Palmyra, Southeast Necropolis, Tomb H (Taibbôl), relief of Yarḥai; London, Christie’s (Christie’s 2012, lot 190)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;210&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ew York, Metropolitan Museum of Art inv. 98.19.3 (Ingholt 1928, 122 PS 282; &lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;, 374 no. 4327, plate 36); Istanbul, Archaeological Museum (Ingholt 1928, 117 PS 237); Once New York, private collection (Ingholt 1928, 112 PS 197; Ingholt 1934, 36 n. 42)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;230&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Palmyra, Palmyra Museum inv. 457/1660: head (Colledge 1976, fig. 142; Tanabe 1986, plate 486 fig. 460); Damascus, National Museum inv. C18: plaster head (Tanabe 1986, plate 484 fig. 458; Charles-Gaffiot et al. 2001, 336 no. 99, fig. on 236); Berlin, Staatliche Museen inv. VA 50 (Ingholt 1928, 122 PS 279; &lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;, 395 no. 4385, plate 45)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;236–37&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Beirut, American University Museum inv. 32.35 (Ingholt 1934, 36–38, plate 9.1); Middlebury (VT), Middlebury College Museum of Art inv. 2009.002 (Sotheby’s 2008, lot 68)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;250&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;notes&#34;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;For a general discussion, see Colledge 1976, 63–82.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;Note previous connection made by Colledge 1976, 90, and Parlasca 1989, 206 n. 17.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;Colledge 1976, 90 and n. 299, with bibliography. The hand from the Agora (Palmyra Museum inv. 4801/1) is now published: Charles-Gaffiot et al. 2001, 329 no. 64, fig. on 212.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;, no. 3913, 128–30 (Palmyrene version); Matthews 1984, 180.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;Colledge 1976, 190.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;Kropp and Raja 2014, 393.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;Illustrated here: Minneapolis, Minneapolis Institute of Art acc. 2008.28.2: &lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;, 393 no. 4379; Sotheby’s 2002, lot 119. See Appendix 23.1 for additional examples.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;Examples and illustrations of herringbone eyebrows: Johansen 1978, pls. 43, 44, 47, 59, 70, 71, 84, 92, 94, 97, 99, 101, 105, 113, and 120. They are also found, rarely, in Egyptian sculpture, as seen on the head of Senusret III from Karnak in the Luxor Museum: Romano 1979, 32–35 no. 40, figs. 28–31.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;J. Paul Getty Museum inv. 89.AB.67.1 and 89.AB.67.2 (illustrated here). Pollini 2001, with additional examples cited; note specific references to herringbone eyebrows on 137.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;Naples, Museo Archeologico Nazionale inv. 4885. Daehner and Lapatin 2015, 296–97 no. 50.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;Athens, National Archaeological Museum no. 6439. Mattusch 1996, 84–87, fig. 3.5.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;Ny Carlsberg Glyptotek inv. 2795: Ploug 1995, 188–92 no. 77. Such a form differs from similar large cavities for the iris appearing on other Palmyran examples (e.g., Ny Carlsberg Glyptotek inv. 1151: Ploug 1995, 234–36 no. 103); in these instances, the hollow is concave and not as deep, and there seems to be a distinction here between the iris and the pupil.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;Colledge 1976, 120; Ploug 1995, 190 and 229.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;Los Angeles County Museum of Art inv. M.82.77.2: Parlasca 1990, 140 no. 10, 139 fig. 10.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;Ashmolean Museum inv. AN2011.46; Walker 2008. It should be noted that both Colledge and Ploug (above, n. 13) tentatively suggest a Parthian source, citing inset eyes found on sculptures from Hatra.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34;&gt;British Museum inv. BEP 1848,1103.1. Lahusen and Formigli 2001, 190–92 no. 114, figs. 114.1–4.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34;&gt;Paris, Louvre inv. Br 19, and Florence, National Archaeological Museum inv. 548: Lahusen and Formigli 2001, 18–19 no. 1, figs. 1.1–4; 20 no. 2, figs. 2.1–4; 462 and 466 figs. 1–3 (eyes).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:18&#34;&gt;Daehner and Lapatin 2015, 274–75 no. 41.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:18&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:19&#34;&gt;Mattusch 1988, 205.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:19&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:20&#34;&gt;Ploug 1995, 12–13.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:20&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:21&#34;&gt;Sadurska and Bounni 1994.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:21&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:22&#34;&gt;Istanbul Archaeological Museum inv. 3840T: Ingholt 1928, 34–35 PS 11, plate 4; &lt;em&gt;CIS&lt;/em&gt;, 476 no. 4616, plate 47.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:22&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:23&#34;&gt;Beirut, American University Museum inv. 32.35: Ingholt 1934, 36–38 no. 3, plate 9.1.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:23&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:24&#34;&gt;First recorded in the collection of Guillaume Proche in Aleppo, illustrated by Chabot 1897, fig. 10. Present location not confirmed. Included in the series based on Ploug 1995, 229.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:24&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:25&#34;&gt;For the head in Los Angeles, see n. 14 above. The other two are: New York, Metropolitan Museum of Art acc. 65.77 (unpublished); and Palmyra Museum inv. B2770/9254 (Charles-Gaffiot et al. 2001, 329 no. 66, fig. on 214).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:25&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:26&#34;&gt;Copenhagen, Ny Carlsberg Glyptotek inv. 1117 (Ploug 1995, 238–39 no. 107); Copenhagen, Ny Carlsberg Glyptotek inv. 1121 (Ploug 1995, 227–30 no. 97); Palmyra Museum inv. B2727/9127 (Charles-Gaffiot et al. 2001, 367 no. 252, fig. on 311); Palmyra Museum inv. B2726/9163 (Fortin 1999, 114 no. 64); Damascus, National Museum inv. C18, in plaster (Tanabe 1986, plate 484 fig. 458; Charles-Gaffiot et al. 2001, 336 no. 99, fig. on 236).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:26&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:27&#34;&gt;Louvre inv. AO 2201. Dentzer-Feydy and Teixidor 1993, 185 no. 186.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:27&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:28&#34;&gt;Ploug 1995, 142. Another example may be added: London, British Museum 125022 (Ingholt 1928, 110 PS 180).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:28&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:29&#34;&gt;To which three more should be added: Grenoble, Musée de Grenoble inv. 1578 (Ingholt 1928, 141 PS 442); Pittsfield, Berkshire Museum acc. 1903.7.3 (Albertson 2016, 159–60 fig. 7); Portland (OR), Portland Museum of Art acc. 54.2 (Parlasca 1990, 138–39, 136 fig. 5).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:29&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:30&#34;&gt;The last in the sequence, ca. AD 200, is the relief in Berlin, Staatliche Museen inv. VA 48 (Ingholt 1928, 149 PS 494).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:30&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:31&#34;&gt;The other two would be the relief in Minneapolis (see n. 7 above), combining incised outlining of the lips and herringbone eyebrows, and a plaster head in Damascus, National Museum inv. C18 (see above n. 26), with herringbone eyebrows and glass paste eyes.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:31&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:32&#34;&gt;Kropp and Raja 2014, 403; Albertson 2016, 153.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:32&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:33&#34;&gt;Discussed and examples cited in Kropp and Raja 2014, 403–404; Albertson 2016, 154–55.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:33&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Transformation of Bronze Sculpture in the Hellenistic East and the Iranian World</title>
      <link>/the-hellenistic-east/abstract-canepa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/the-hellenistic-east/abstract-canepa/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Hellenistic Heritage of Termez</title>
      <link>/the-hellenistic-east/abstract-mirzaev/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/the-hellenistic-east/abstract-mirzaev/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>