<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The-hellenistic-easts on </title>
    <link>/the-hellenistic-east/</link>
    <description>Recent content in The-hellenistic-easts on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    
	<atom:link href="/the-hellenistic-east/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Hellenistic East</title>
      <link>/the-hellenistic-east/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/the-hellenistic-east/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Influence of East and West on Bronze Objects Found in Central Anatolia</title>
      <link>/the-hellenistic-east/21-paterakis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/the-hellenistic-east/21-paterakis/</guid>
      <description>Introduction This paper reviews the influences from the East and West on bronzes (copper-tin alloys) found in Anatolia while focusing on the archaeological finds from the site of Kaman-Kalehöyük. Given its location along ancient trade routes, Kaman-Kalehöyük may have served as a conduit for the intraregional exchange of materials and manufacturing technologies. We examine some of these influences and movements as they relate to ancient bronze technology in Anatolia.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Portrait of a Hellenistic Ruler in the National Museum of Iran</title>
      <link>/the-hellenistic-east/22-lindstroem/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/the-hellenistic-east/22-lindstroem/</guid>
      <description>Discovery in 1935 in Ancient Elymais The portrait head of a Hellenistic ruler (fig. 22.1) was discovered more than eighty years ago in Kal-e Chendar in the valley of Shami, north of Izeh in present-day Khuzistan (ancient Elymais). It is often stated that Sir Aurel Stein (1862–1943), the famous Hungarian-British explorer, excavated the portrait. In fact, it was found accidentally in the course of construction work, shortly before Stein arrived at the site.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Influence of Bronze-Working on Roman Provincial Stone Sculpture</title>
      <link>/the-hellenistic-east/23-albertson/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/the-hellenistic-east/23-albertson/</guid>
      <description>The prosperity experienced by the elite of the ancient Roman-Syrian city of Palmyra from the late first century BC through the middle of the third century AD is perhaps most visible in their monumental family tombs and the funerary sculpture associated within these tombs. Among the types included within the well-known repertoire of Palmyran funerary reliefs are the distinctive loculus plaques: rectangular limestone slabs covering the burial cavity, carved in high relief with a bust depicting the individual interred and often accompanied by an Aramaic inscription denoting the occupant’s name, family lineage, and sometimes even the date of death.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Transformation of Bronze Sculpture in the Hellenistic East and the Iranian World</title>
      <link>/the-hellenistic-east/abstract-canepa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/the-hellenistic-east/abstract-canepa/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Hellenistic Heritage of Termez</title>
      <link>/the-hellenistic-east/abstract-mirzaev/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/the-hellenistic-east/abstract-mirzaev/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Abstracts</title>
      <link>/the-hellenistic-east/abstracts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/the-hellenistic-east/abstracts/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>