<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Statuettes on </title>
    <link>/statuettes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Statuettes on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    
	<atom:link href="/statuettes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Statuettes</title>
      <link>/statuettes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/statuettes/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Assertions by the Portable</title>
      <link>/statuettes/13-barr-sharrar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/statuettes/13-barr-sharrar/</guid>
      <description>Discussing Polykleitos’s Doryphoros in his landmark Masterpieces of Greek Sculpture (1895), Adolf Furtwängler included a few bronze statuettes pertinent to his subject. The largest and most important known to him was a statuette from Fins d’Annecy now in the Musée du Petit Palais in Paris (fig. 13.1).1 Suggestive of Roman marble copies of the Doryphoros with the movement of the arms reversed, Furtwängler said it had previously been identified by Adolf Michaelis and other late nineteenth-century scholars as a copy of the Hermes by Polykleitos mentioned by Pliny as “once in Lysimachea” (Naturalis historia 34.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Use of Inlays in Early Greek Bronzes</title>
      <link>/statuettes/14-hemingway-abramitis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/statuettes/14-hemingway-abramitis/</guid>
      <description>Ancient Greek bronze-smiths used a variety of techniques to enhance the appearance of their creations. Due to their often fragmentary state of preservation, the modern observer tends to think of early Greek bronzes as monochromatic, but it is clear that the practice of inlaying other materials into bronze started early in ancient Greece. This paper looks at the evidence for the Geometric (ca. 900–700 BC) and Archaic (ca. 700–480 BC) periods from many different regions, with particular reference to artworks in the collection of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, where a variety of nondestructive scientific analyses were conducted in the Museum’s conservation and scientific laboratories.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Poet as Artisan</title>
      <link>/statuettes/15-mcgowan/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/statuettes/15-mcgowan/</guid>
      <description>Figure 15.1   Figure 15.2   Figure 15.3   Bronze statuette of an artisan. New York, Metropolitan Museum of Art inv. 1972.11.1. Rogers Fund, 1972. © The Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York, www.metmuseum.org  Many of the papers in this volume deal with the technical aspects of bronze manufacture and analysis of fabric and technique. But what of the artisans themselves? A large, relatively well-preserved Hellenistic bronze statuette in the Metropolitan Museum of Art, said to have been found off the coast of North Africa, appears to be an image of an artisan (fig.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Paramythia Bronzes</title>
      <link>/statuettes/16-sharpe/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/statuettes/16-sharpe/</guid>
      <description>Introduction This paper will focus on a hoard of bronze statuettes found near Paramythia (Epirus) at the end of the eighteenth century (fig. 16.1–14).1 It is appropriate to review these bronzes in light of recent scholarship on Roman Greece and current discussions regarding aspects of Roman identity.2 A reappraisal of the Paramythia material can contribute to recent deliberations concerning how material culture, in particular personal items, might reflect and reinforce the patron’s social and cultural identity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roman Bronze Figurines of Deities in the National Archaeological Museum of the Marche (Ancona)</title>
      <link>/statuettes/17-frapiccini/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/statuettes/17-frapiccini/</guid>
      <description>The collection of Roman bronze statuettes in the National Archaeological Museum of the Marche at Ancona includes numerous representations of deities. The majority of these statuettes are probably from domestic lararia in the territory, which in ancient times belonged to the regiones of Umbria and Piceno. This paper analyzes some of the most interesting statuettes including the bronze figurines from Sentinum, where a foundry is known to have existed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Function and Use of Roman Medium-Sized Statuettes in the Northwestern Provinces</title>
      <link>/statuettes/18-kaufmann/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/statuettes/18-kaufmann/</guid>
      <description>When we think of figural bronzes from the northwestern provinces of the Roman world, a considerable number of small statuettes and some impressive fragments of life-size statues come to mind. Medium-sized statuettes, between approximately 40 and 100 cm (16 to 39 in.) high, however, are less well documented, as they seem to have had less chance of surviving either intact, as did small bronzes, or as fragments, as did large statues.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Through Celts and Romans</title>
      <link>/statuettes/19-grossi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/statuettes/19-grossi/</guid>
      <description>Introduction The symbology characterizing the Roman world, as much as its artistic production, often manifests a beautiful syncretism: there are many cases in which a theme, a figure, or a meaning is re-arranged and presented in a different way, and it is often possible to see that their roots are planted far away. From this point of view the Celts were very important, because their myths, rites, and interpretations influenced Roman ones over a long span of time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Representations of Zeus/Jupiter in the Small-Scale Bronze</title>
      <link>/statuettes/20-veseli/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/statuettes/20-veseli/</guid>
      <description>Zeus/Jupiter was one of the most venerated gods in ancient Albania, a country situated on one of the crossroads of the Mediterranean. The area was heavily influenced culturally by the Graeco-Roman world. The eclectic religious life of this Graeco-Roman civilization ensured that the indigenous Illyrian pantheon was very similar to the Greek, and that most of the Olympian gods were venerated, as were Roman deities in a later era. Zeus/Jupiter, one of the most important gods, is represented in the small-scale bronze sculpture found in Albania, and in particular by the four examples discussed here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roman-Age Casting Techniques of Small Bronzes from Marche</title>
      <link>/statuettes/abstract-fazzini/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/statuettes/abstract-fazzini/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Figural Bronze Statuettes in the Ashmolean Collection and the Aesthetics of Replication</title>
      <link>/statuettes/abstract-west/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/statuettes/abstract-west/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>