<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Artifacts on Quire Starter Kit</title>
    <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artifacts/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Artifacts on Quire Starter Kit</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://gettypubs.github.io/artifacts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Minoan Status Symbols</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artifacts/30-ferrence-giumlia-mair/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artifacts/30-ferrence-giumlia-mair/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our project on Minoan metallurgy, many objects of various sizes, belonging to several classes, and made of different metals were analyzed by X-ray fluorescence (XRF). The items come from different sites in eastern Crete, one of which is the Minoan town of Gournia, which was excavated in the early twentieth century.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; With the support of the University of Pennsylvania Museum of Archaeology and Anthropology (hereafter, Penn Museum) in Philadelphia and private donors, Harriet Boyd Hawes and her collaborators, Richard Seager and Edith Hall, excavated the settlement of Gournia in three campaigns in 1901, 1903, and 1904 and published the discoveries in 1908.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The settlement was situated on a low hill overlooking the Gulf of Mirabello. It thrived from the Early Bronze Age until it was destroyed at the end of Late Minoan (LM) IB (ca. 1450 BC). The town consisted of paved and cobblestone laneways among many irregularly shaped, multi-room houses. Many types of artifacts were found throughout the site including fine examples of Late Minoan IB Marine Style pottery and also earlier examples of silver and ceramic kantharoi.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Stone vessels and tools came to light, such as bird’s nest bowls, rhyta, lamps, mortars, and pestles. A lapidary workshop probably existed in the town. Additionally, other utilitarian items, especially metal tools and objects such as daggers, double axes, saws, chisels, and sickles, were uncovered during the excavations. Most of these objects were incorporated into the collection of the Candia Museum, which is now the Herakleion Archaeological Museum in Crete, but a smaller number of items also was offered at that time to the Penn Museum as a gift to create a study collection in the United States. This collection is one of the most important groups of Minoan objects outside of Greece, second only to the Knossian collection of the Ashmolean Museum at Oxford University.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wide range of types of metal objects that were found at Gournia—from ingots to sheets and strips to finished tools to scrap metal—in addition to other finds from the settlement—such as stone hammers and stone molds, which were discovered in a cache in Room Fh—indicate that the people who lived in the town probably manufactured metal objects in one or more workshops. The metalsmiths may have been housed in Rooms Ea and Cg based upon the sheer number of metal objects that were found in those rooms.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The collection of the Penn Museum contains over fifty cataloged metal items, most of which likely date to the time of the destruction of the town at the end of Late Minoan IB. Dating metal objects, however, can be problematic because scholars have documented the continuity of tool type and morphology from the Early through the Late Bronze Age in Greece based solely on stratigraphical contexts. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Also, metal objects tend to be long-lived, so the manufacture of some may actually date to earlier periods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hawes’s excavation report of 1908 set a high standard for quality publication in her day, but unfortunately it does not measure up to modern levels of scholarship. She did not fully catalog the majority of the objects that were found nor completely document their contexts at the site. In the final report, only 72 out of 157 copper-based objects were listed and illustrated from the entire site. The Penn Museum has over 53 of the 157 objects, but not all of them are shown in the original publication, so additional objects were clearly omitted from the final publication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the metal finds from Gournia that are housed in the Penn Museum have been analyzed with XRF, but we will focus here on a few select pieces, namely the small copper-based tools and personal items such as tweezers, cosmetic scrapers, and the so-called weaving hooks. The composition, production techniques, and finishing processes of the artifacts have been investigated and allow for the reconstruction of the various stages of fabrication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;methodology&#34;&gt;Methodology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each object chosen for analysis was visually examined under various magnification (x50, x100, x200) devices to determine its current state of preservation and to identify the best locations on the surface for performing the analytical measurements. Comprehensive visual examination also reveals evidence for manufacturing techniques and even indications for the attachment of organic handles that have long since disappeared. Wherever necessary, the chief conservator of the museum removed a small area of the patina layers before taking measurements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;XRF was chosen for the scientific analysis because it is a non-destructive method perfect for use on museum pieces. The particular system employed was also transportable and was specially developed for the analysis of cultural heritage objects. The equipment consisted of an XRF-source on a support with devices to control the position and stability of the X-ray beam, a transformer, a stabilizer, and a computer with dedicated software. The characteristics of the equipment, the dedicated software, and the standards specifically created for use with ancient metal alloys (produced &lt;em&gt;ad hoc&lt;/em&gt; by AGM Archeoanalisi) greatly enhanced the precision of the system. Each measurement illuminated a spot on the object with X-rays for a short time, usually about 15 minutes, but longer if the location was very small. The irradiated zone measures approximately 1.5–2.0 mm in diameter, but it can be reduced or enlarged depending upon the size and surface texture of the object. An acoustic signal indicates when the distance from the sample is correct and a laser pointer marks the exact location to be measured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A wide range of elements—particularly metals and alloys—can be quantified with precision, if proper standards are used.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:6&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Those utilized in our analytical program represent various compositions of ancient metal alloys. They are an important aspect of evaluating the XRF results. During the project at the Penn Museum, the standards were run each day at regular intervals. Drift and any interference therefore could be identified and accounted for while gauging the results. This procedure maintains precision and assures reliable results. This system is transportable, yet it is as accurate as any classic laboratory XRF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;results-composition-of-small-decorative-objects-of-personal-use&#34;&gt;Results: Composition of Small Decorative Objects of Personal Use&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personal ornaments made of metal were an important type of object during the Cretan Bronze Age. This class commonly shows a better quality of manufacture than everyday objects and tools. Their presence in mortuary contexts dating back to the beginning of the Early Bronze Age indicates that the Minoans had a long history of exhibiting social status through personal adornment with metal items.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The XRF results (&lt;strong&gt;table 30.1&lt;/strong&gt;) show that a small group of four hook-shaped pins (MS4203–MS4205 [&lt;strong&gt;fig. 30.1&lt;/strong&gt;], MS4740), which have been called “weaving hooks” or jewelry in the literature,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:7&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; contain a relatively high amount of tin, at 2–5 percent, with measurable arsenic in a couple of the specimens. The four pieces were manufactured with different techniques. Two of the pins are square in section and therefore seem to have been simple cast objects; the other two examples (MS4203, MS4205) are round in section, so they were most probably hammered into shape after casting. Furthermore, one of these pins (MS4203) was created using a third technique, namely twisting together two lengths of wire, as evidenced by the spiral-form seam visible under magnification. The shaft was hammered and then polished with an abrasive tool. The fabrication techniques rendered delicate decorative forms, while the composition of the alloys containing relatively high amounts of tin with some arsenic would have resulted in a lighter color of the metal, perhaps imitating gold or silver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hook-shaped pins from the Minoan culture have been construed at times to be weaving hooks, but the metallurgical composition and method of manufacture of those from Gournia are comparable to those of decorative objects instead of utilitarian tools. Furthermore, according to scholars who specialize in textiles of the Aegean Bronze Age, so-called weaving hooks do not actually exist in the repertoire of tools necessary for the fabrication of cloth.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:8&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Our hook-shaped pins from Gournia are paralleled by examples from other sites made of gold, silver, and ivory.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:9&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Specifically, a total of ten ivory pins were excavated in a Late Minoan I house at Mochlos, a Minoan harbor town near Gournia, along with an ivory box filled with amethyst, carnelian, and lapis lazuli beads.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:10&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The entire set must have belonged to a very important lady who was not unlike those depicted with hair accessories in frescoes from Knossos in Crete and Akrotiri on the island of Thera. The Miniature Grandstand Fresco at Knossos&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:11&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; illustrates two ladies with hook-shaped pins adorning their hair (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 30.2&lt;/strong&gt;). The “injured adorant” in the Xeste 3 wall paintings at Akrotiri wears a hook-shaped pin in her coiffure that ends in the form of an iris.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:12&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; These painted parallels support the idea that metal hook-shaped pins probably were not simple tools. They had a special social meaning because the ladies in the frescos certainly held an elevated status in Minoan society. The use of these decorative items as personal ornaments therefore seems much more logical than as a textile tool without a single parallel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the largest classes of metal objects within the Gournia collection at the Penn Museum is the tweezers (see fig. 30.1, lower left). The alloy used to create them was specially prepared with well-purified copper and the addition of higher amounts of tin. Their compositions show 2–3 percent tin, comparable to the alloys used for other personal ornaments. These alloys were commonly manufactured with refined copper that also contained noticeable amounts of tin and some arsenic. The objects were carefully finished and even repaired when broken (e.g., MS4196) instead of being melted down for recycling, indicating that the tweezers were important objects of some significance and perhaps had a special meaning. They could have been worn by the owner, maybe as a pendant or on the belt, and functioned as small personal adornments. The composition of the tweezers can indeed be compared to that of other ornaments. One of the pieces (MS4746K) in particular contains only traces of tin but a higher arsenic content of 2.4 percent. Tools composed of this alloy are just as functional as examples manufactured with tin bronze. The color of the arsenic-rich tweezer also would have been conspicuously lighter, perhaps improving its aesthetics. Unfortunately, this particular example from Gournia is in poor condition, meaning the data should be considered only indicative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another object from Gournia is a small “scraper” that was formed with a loop for use as a possible handle (MS4198; see fig. 30.1, lower center). Again, this small personal item was made with a similar kind of metallurgical composition. It may have been used as a cosmetic scraper of some sort, and the loop would have provided a way to wear it as a personal ornament in the same manner as suggested for the tweezers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two other examples (MS4190 [see fig. 1, lower right], MS4746F) from Gournia are simpler in composition. A small implement with a flaring blade (MS4190) shows evidence for careful finishing. Under magnification, one can also see that the cutting edge exhibits traces of use-wear and reworking. The blade is composed of copper with only traces of tin and no measurable arsenic, while the rivets are less refined unalloyed copper. The presence of relatively high zinc and iron in this object is only due to corrosion. The other small blade (MS4746F) was made of unalloyed copper that contained only traces of arsenic and silver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our study has demonstrated that the Minoan metalsmiths were able to purify their copper whenever the need arose. For some classes of utilitarian objects, however, thorough purification was not deemed necessary, so impure copper was used. The arsenic and tin content shown in the XRF results of these copper-based objects from Gournia suggests that tin was a rare and expensive commodity and that recycling scrap metal was relatively common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, as the smiths gained empirical metallurgical experience over time, their growing knowledge enabled them to recognize the beneficial properties of arsenic-rich copper, and to appreciate its pale silvery color. This would have contributed to their production of tools that were more resistant and harder than copper, and also to the manufacture of decorative items that could be lighter and more attractive in color.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The XRF analyses have demonstrated that the copper-based objects from Gournia presented here were actually prestige items because the alloys contain certain metals in particular quantities (one of which is a precious metal) to convey the color and status of silver and gold. These alloys used for personal ornaments and jewelry are refined to a higher degree and contain more alloying elements, such as tin and arsenic, than the copper-based alloys usually used for simple utilitarian tools. Additionally, the hook-shaped pins, tweezers, and cosmetic scrapers were manufactured with high-quality alloys comparable to those used in jewelry pieces. These small personal items therefore were not simple tools but were highly valued in Minoan society. The owners would have worn them as decorative accessories of their garments and hairstyle as an indication of their social status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;acknowledgments&#34;&gt;Acknowledgments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We thank the Penn Museum for permission to study, analyze, and publish the metal objects from Gournia. We gratefully acknowledge funding provided by the Institute for Aegean Prehistory (INSTAP), Philadelphia, PA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bibliography&#34;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Betancourt 1979&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Betancourt, P. P. 1979. “The Pottery Chronology: A Brief Sketch.” In &lt;em&gt;Gournia, Crete: The 75th Anniversary of the Excavations&lt;/em&gt; (Temple University Aegean Symposium 4), ed. P. Betancourt, 7–10. Philadelphia: Temple University.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Betancourt and Silverman 1991&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Betancourt, P. P, and J. S. Silverman. 1991. &lt;em&gt;The Cretan Collection in the University Museum, University of Pennsulvania&lt;/em&gt;. Vol. 2: &lt;em&gt;Pottery from Gournia&lt;/em&gt;. University Museum Monograph 72. Philadelphia: University Museum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Betancourt et al. 1978&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Betancourt, P. P., T. S. Wheeler, R. Maddin, and J. D. Muhly. 1978. “Metallurgy at Gournia.” &lt;em&gt;MASCAJ&lt;/em&gt; 1: 7–8.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Boardman 1961&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Boardman, J. 1961. &lt;em&gt;The Cretan Collection in Oxford: The Dictaean Cave and Iron Age Crete&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford: Clarendon.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Boyd 1904&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Boyd, H. A. 1904. “Gournia: Report of the American Exploration Society’s Excavations at Gournia, Crete.” &lt;em&gt;Transactions, Department of Archaeology, University of Pennsylvania&lt;/em&gt; 1.1: 7–44.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Boyd Hawes et al. 1908&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Boyd Hawes, H. A., B. E. Williams, R. B. Seager, and E. H. Hall. 1908. &lt;em&gt;Gournia, Vasiliki, and Other Prehistoric Sites on the Isthmus of Hierapetra, Crete: Excavations of the Wells-Houston-Cramp Expeditions, 1901, 1903, 1904&lt;/em&gt;. Philadelphia: American Exploration Society, Free Museum of Science and Art.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Branigan 1974&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Branigan, K. 1974. &lt;em&gt;Aegean Metalwork of the Early and Middle Bronze Age&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford: Clarendon.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Evans 1964&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Evans, A. 1964. &lt;em&gt;The Palace of Minos: A Comparative Account of the Successive Stages of the Early Cretan Civilization as Illustrated by the Discoveries at Knossos&lt;/em&gt;. Vol. 3. New York: Biblo and Tannen.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Fotou 1993&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Fotou, V. 1993. &lt;em&gt;New Light on Gournia: Unknown Documents of the Excavation at Gournia and Other Sites on the Isthmus of Ierapetra&lt;/em&gt;. Aegaeum 9. Liège: Université de Liège; Austin: University of Texas.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Hahn-Weinheimer, Hirner, and Weber-Diefenbach 1995&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Hahn-Weinheimer, P., A. Hirner, and K. Weber-Diefenbach. 1995. &lt;em&gt;Röntgenfluoreszenzanalytische Methoden: Grundlagen und praktische Anwendung in den Geo-, Material- und Umweltwissenschaften&lt;/em&gt;. Braunschweig: Vieweg.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Lutz and Pernicka 1996&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Lutz, J., and E. Pernicka. 1996. “EDXRF Analysis of Ancient Copper Alloys.” &lt;em&gt;Archaeometry&lt;/em&gt; 38.2: 313–23.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Soles and Davaras 2010&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Soles, J. S., and C. Davaras. 2010. “2010 Greek-American Excavations at Mochlos.” &lt;em&gt;Kentro: The Newsletter of the INSTAP Study Center for East Crete&lt;/em&gt; 13: 1–3.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Vlachopoulos and Georma 2012&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Vlachopoulos, A., and F. Georma. 2012. “Jewellery and Adornment at Akrotiri, Thera: The Evidence from the Wall Paintings and the Finds.” In &lt;em&gt;Kosmos: Jewellery, Adornment and Textiles in the Aegean Bronze Age: Proceedings of the 13th International Aegean Conference, University of Copenhagen, Danish National Research Foundation’s Centre for Textile Research, 21–26 April 2010&lt;/em&gt; (Aegaeum 33), ed. M.-L. Nosch and R. Laffineur, 35–42. Leuven and Liège: Peeters.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Boyd 1904; Boyd Hawes et al. 1908.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;Betancourt 1979; Betancourt and Silverman 1991; Fotou 1993.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;Boardman 1961.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;Betancourt et al. 1978, 7.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;See, for example, Branigan 1974.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;See Hahn-Weinheimer, Hirner, and Weber-Diefenbach 1995; Lutz and Pernicka 1996.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;Branigan 1974, 35, pl. 17.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;J. Cutler, pers. comm.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;Branigan 1974; Soles and Davaras 2010.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;Soles and Davaras 2010, 1–3.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;Evans 1964, 46–57, plates XVI, XVII.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;Vlachopoulos and Georma 2012, esp. 40, plate XVIId.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bronze Trees from the Greek to the Roman World</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artifacts/31-castoldi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artifacts/31-castoldi/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;It is well known that trees, gardens, and landscapes are not commonly represented in Greek art until the Hellenistic period. In vase painting, the focus is on men, gods, and heroes; war, hunting, labor, rituals, weddings, death, and festivals offer the opportunity to represent humans, who are at the center of philosophy and art in ancient Greece. Nature and landscapes, by contrast, rarely appear in vase painting; floral patterns, tendrils, and leaves only appear as subsidiary decoration. In a few cases, flowers and trees acquire life on their own as gods’ attributes or to give emphasis to a sacred setting, as for example the palm tree linked to the birth of Apollo and the sanctuary of Delos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Greek world, fruit and vegetables played an important role as offerings and anathemata. Items such as firstfruits were given to the gods, but these were perishable items meant to be burnt on the altars the same day.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fruit and vegetables could became more durable offerings if they were modeled from clay, ivory, bronze, or gold,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; as for instance the famous “golden harvest” dedicated from Metaponto to Delphi; the gold celery from Selinus; or the &lt;em&gt;silphium&lt;/em&gt; from Ampelos.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In addition to such fruits and vegetables given as anathemata, trees made from bronze and precious metals have been reported as offerings at some of the major Greek sanctuaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These objects are well-known thanks to the ancient sources. For example, Plutarch described the bronze palm dedicated in the sanctuary of Delphi by Kypselos—perhaps a &lt;em&gt;sphyrelaton&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;—and one offered by the Athenians after the battle of the Eurymedon (470/69 BC).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:6&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The base of the latter has been identified to the northeast of the front side of the Apollo temple: a statue of Athena with an owl stood on top of the palm tree, which had bunches of golden dates and was still standing at the time of Pausanias.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:7&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Another famous bronze palm tree was offered by Nikias at the Apollo sanctuary of Delos around 417 BC, as mentioned by Plutarch; its base is preserved not far from the &lt;em&gt;oikos&lt;/em&gt; of the Naxians.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:8&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we also have many &lt;em&gt;realia&lt;/em&gt;. A good example in bronze was found during the excavations of Karapanos in Dodona; it represents a branch of an oak, the tree sacred to Zeus.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:9&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Moreover, we may remember the bronze branches and laurel leaves in the sanctuary of Apollo in Klaros, and those found in Magna Graecia, in Kroton, Kaulonia, and Metaponto (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 31.1&lt;/strong&gt;); these testify to the practice of dedicating bronze laurel trees to Apollo.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:10&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among profane artworks, I would note the golden grapevine adorned with precious stones attributed by some scholars to the versatile artist Theodoros of Samos and the golden plane tree, both decorating the Persian royal palace: the grapevine was hung over the king’s bed like a baldachin. According to the majority of sources, this work combined the monumentality of bronze sculptures with the elegance of jewelry.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:11&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ancient texts date these ornaments to the period of Darius I (522–486 BC), but it is likely that they remained in use until the time of Alexander the Great. They might therefore have become a source of inspiration for some of the toreutic art in the Hellenistic and Roman period, such as a golden grapevine offered as anathema in the Artemision of Delos in the third century BC, and the one offered by Aristobulos II to Pompey when he arrived in Syria: εἴτε ἄμπελος εἴτε κῆπος.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:12&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This may be the same one that Pliny the Elder remembered as being displayed during a triumph in Rome, “a square mountain of gold with deer, lions and every variety of fruit on it and a golden vine entwined around it,” which was then exhibited in the temple of Jupiter Capitolinus.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:13&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, we know that various metal trees served as interior decorations for sacred temples, such as the ingenious bronze palm tree in the Erechtheion crafted by Kallimachos.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:14&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; A famous candelabrum, perhaps trunk-shaped, with lamps shaped like fruits, was once held in the temple of Apollo Ismenios in Thebes. It was taken away by Alexander the Great, then dedicated in the temple of Apollo at Cyme (Kyme), and finally carried to Rome to be shown in the Apollo temple on the Palatine. Pliny may be the only source that refers to this installation, but a &lt;em&gt;terminus ante quem&lt;/em&gt; for its creation is given by the conquest of Thebes by Alexander the Great in 335 BC.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:15&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Hellenistic art, unlike in Classical Greek art, vegetal themes were very popular, perhaps following the model of the Persian royal gardens, which Alexander himself knew well.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:16&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Flowers and plants were used, for instance, in the luxurious decoration of the famous pavilion (&lt;em&gt;skené&lt;/em&gt;) and procession of Ptolemy Philadelphus in the court of Alexandria,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:17&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; whose golden plants and furniture with floral decorations were described by Athenaeus.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:18&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, gardens like the one in Alexandria were artificial: the exuberance of nature was subordinated to the rigor of architecture and architectural decoration. The same concept is evident in the wall-paintings of Imperial villas, for example in the famous villa of Livia (&lt;em&gt;Villa ad gallinas albas&lt;/em&gt;) at Prima Porta, where the gardens are depicted according to architectural rules.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:19&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The taste for ornamental plants spread in the arts and crafts of early Imperial Rome. They evoked the spirit of the Alexandrian gardens and the tree-shaped artworks and precious monumental anathemata in the Greek temples and sanctuaries (i.e., laurel trees, palms, and grapevines in bronze or gold) that were still visible in Roman times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Candelabra in the form of trees, more or less naturalistic, were widespread. The most common were certainly lampstands with slender shafts &lt;em&gt;a canna&lt;/em&gt; (cane-like), representing bamboo or lopped branches, surmounted by a disk to hold a single lamp (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 31.2&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:20&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:20&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This type was most likely produced in Central Italy and was manufactured in a small, tabletop version, and in a larger version, to be placed on the floor.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:21&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:21&#34;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to such stylized variants, however, there is also evidence of more naturalistic representations. There are medium-sized lampstands, trunk-shaped, made to be placed on tables or supports, with small lamps suspended from their branches like fruits, such as the specimens from Pompeii and the famous lampstand from the Meloria (Livorno) (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 31.3&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:22&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:22&#34;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; These “trees” have few leaves: evidently, the lamps, like small luminous fruit, replaced the foliage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some ornate stands have a large rectangular base upon which statuettes of heroes, satyrs, or gods could be placed, as for instance a beautiful acanthus-shaped candelabrum, with Attis or Alexander Helios, which is now in Geneva.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:23&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:23&#34;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In these examples, the tree can be naturalistic, with twisted trunk and branches, in the manner of Hellenistic art, or modeled with more architectural forms, such as a floral column. In addition to examples of this type from the early Imperial period, there is evidence of more complex objects in which the tree is the support of statuettes, leaning toward the plant. I recall here examples in Pompeii, Ephesos, Baden (Switzerland), the one now in Kansas City, and perhaps the one from Hungary (Brigetio).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:24&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:24&#34;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; These artworks testify to the decorative function of certain metal trees, which is very evident in the Roman world; the tree, after a long life as &lt;em&gt;agalma&lt;/em&gt; or gift to the gods, is now a “bringer of light” that found its way out of the sanctuaries and into the wealthy &lt;em&gt;domus&lt;/em&gt; of the Romans as luxury furniture.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:25&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:25&#34;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other bronze trees in the Roman world had a votive function: such is likely the case for the candelabrum in the British Museum, a true &lt;em&gt;signum pantheum&lt;/em&gt;, in which a twisted tree became the support for pantheistic attributes in relief. This is a unique object, as far as I know, which due to its small size should be assigned to a &lt;em&gt;lararium&lt;/em&gt; or a small domestic shrine setting.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:26&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:26&#34;&gt;25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In northern Italy, a group found in the region of Verona is of great interest. It consisted of a small bronze tree and a statuette of Minerva (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 31.4&lt;/strong&gt;): one can assume that they too were likely placed in a &lt;em&gt;lararium&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:27&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:27&#34;&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Lamps modeled in the form of an acanthus bud are known also from among the famous findings of Montorio Veronese, some of which were likely part of a &lt;em&gt;lararium&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:28&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:28&#34;&gt;27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Individual leaves, too, are represented in Roman times among votive offerings, as we know from many examples from northern Italy.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:29&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:29&#34;&gt;28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some finds derive from the provinces also, but these materials are mostly without context; the hypothesis that they belong to &lt;em&gt;lararia&lt;/em&gt; or domestic shrines is considered here because of the small size of the objects. Small trees have notably been found in the Magdalensberg (Noricum); in Strasbourg (Argentoratae) and in Seltz (both in Alsace); in Hintzerath (Trier); in Zugmantel; and in Bonn.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:30&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:30&#34;&gt;29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; These examples are scattered over a wide area, but always within the Roman Empire; some of them are quite alike (and may have been produced in the same area&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:31&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:31&#34;&gt;30&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;) and they all attest to the practice of dedicating more or less naturalistic little figures of trees to the gods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can gain a sense of the importance of plants from two famous statuettes. One is the miniature silver statuette from northern Italy, considered the &lt;em&gt;Terra mater/salus&lt;/em&gt;, of the Summano mountain site.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:32&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:32&#34;&gt;31&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The find is linked to transhumance routes but also to practices that evoke the rural fertility cults: the goddess sits on a throne, with a patera, snakes, and branches. The second is the well-known Dea Artio from Muri (Bern), with a tree that seems to represent the wild landscape.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:33&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:33&#34;&gt;32&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we turn from votive objects to wall-painting, we can see that, at least in southern Italy, branches, plants, and flowers are widespread in &lt;em&gt;lararia&lt;/em&gt;, in scenes of sacrifice—representing the natural landscape of the ritual—or to recall the ancient &lt;em&gt;lucus&lt;/em&gt;, the sacred grove.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:34&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:34&#34;&gt;33&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would speculate that these small bronze trees, when they were placed in &lt;em&gt;lararia&lt;/em&gt; or domestic shrines, are more than mere small-sized tree-shaped lamp-holders. Rather they may reference the &lt;em&gt;lucus&lt;/em&gt; or the ancient offering of firstfruits that was always of great importance in the Roman world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;acknowledgments&#34;&gt;Acknowledgments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper was given at the 19th International Bronze Congress; it is published here without significant changes or additions, except in the bibliography. I would like to thank the Organizing Committee for this extremely interesting Bronze Congress and for the warm welcome in Los Angeles. I would also like to thank all my colleagues who helped me with comments, suggestions, and collaborations: Silvia Amicone, Barbara Arbeid, Margherita Bolla, Brunella Bruno, Antonio De Siena, Federica Grossi, Kurt Gschwentler, Kenneth Lapatin, Lucia Mordeglia, Mara Romaniello, and Ambra Spinelli.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bibliography&#34;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Amandry 1954&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Amandry, P. 1954. “Notes de topographie et d’architecture delphiques. IV. Le palmier de bronze de l’Eurymédon.” &lt;em&gt;BCH&lt;/em&gt; 78: 295–315.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Bailey 1996&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Bailey, D. M. 1996. &lt;em&gt;A Catalogue of the Lamps in the British Museum.&lt;/em&gt; Vol. 4: &lt;em&gt;Lamps of Metal and Stone and Lampstands&lt;/em&gt;. London: The Trustees of the British Museum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Beschi 1962&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Beschi, L. 1962. &lt;em&gt;I bronzetti romani di Montorio Veronese&lt;/em&gt;. Venice: Istituto Veneto.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Beschi 1984&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Beschi, L. 1984. “Bronzi antichi da un naufragio alla Meloria di Livorno.” In &lt;em&gt;Toreutik und figürliche Bronzen römischer Zeit: Akten der 6. Tagung über antike Bronzen (Berlin 1980),&lt;/em&gt; ed. U. Gehrig, 50–58. Berlin: Staatliche Museen Preussischer Kulturbesitz, Antikenmuseum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Bieber 1963&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Bieber, M. 1963. “A Satyr in Pergamene Style in Kansas City.” &lt;em&gt;AJA&lt;/em&gt; 67: 275–78.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Bol 1970&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Bol, P. C. 1970. “Die Herakles-Kentauren-Gruppe in Wien.” &lt;em&gt;AntP&lt;/em&gt; 10: 81–90.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Bolla 2007&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Bolla, M. 2007. “Bronzi figurati romani dal veronese: un aggiornamento.” &lt;em&gt;NumAntCl&lt;/em&gt; 36: 245–85.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Bolla 2015&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Bolla, M. 2015. “Arredi e oggetti vari del tempio di età imperiale.” In &lt;em&gt;Archeologia e storia sul Monte Castelon di Marano di Valpolicella&lt;/em&gt;, ed. B. Bruno and G. Falezza, 271–92. Mantua: SAP Società Archeologica s.r.l.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Bommelaer and Laroche 1991&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Bommelaer, J. F., and D. Laroche. 1991. &lt;em&gt;Guide de Delphes: Le site&lt;/em&gt;. Paris: École française d’Athènes.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Büttner 1962&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Büttner, A. 1962. “Figürlich verzierte Bronzen von Kastell Zugmantel.” &lt;em&gt;SaalbJb&lt;/em&gt; 22: 62–75.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Calandra 2008&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Calandra, E. 2008. “L’occasione e l’eterno: la tenda di Tolomeo Filadelfo nei palazzi di Alessandria. 1. Materiali per la ricostruzione.” &lt;em&gt;Lanx&lt;/em&gt; 1: 26–74. http:riviste.unimi.it/index.php/lanx/index.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Calandra 2009&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Calandra, E. 2009. “L’occasione e l’eterno: la tenda di Tolomeo Filadelfo nei palazzi di Alessandria. 2. Una proposta di ricostruzione.” &lt;em&gt;Lanx&lt;/em&gt; 2: 1–77. http:riviste.unimi.it/index.php/lanx/index.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Calandra 2011&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Calandra, E. 2011. &lt;em&gt;The Ephemeral and the Eternal: The Pavilion of Ptolemy Philadelphos in the Court of Alexandria&lt;/em&gt;. Athens: Scuola Archeologica Italiana di Atene.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Calandra 2015&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Calandra, E. 2015. “I giardini di Alessandria.” In Sena Chiesa and Pontrandolfo 2015, 256–64.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Carapanos 1878&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Carapanos, C. 1878. &lt;em&gt;Dodone et ses ruines&lt;/em&gt;. 2 vols. Paris: Hachette.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Castoldi 2005&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Castoldi, M. 2005. “Cremona e l’&lt;em&gt;ager cremonensis&lt;/em&gt;: elementi d’arredo in
bronzo.” In Slavazzi 2005, 187–204.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Castoldi 2010&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Castoldi, M. 2010. “Gli arredi in bronzo della &lt;em&gt;domus&lt;/em&gt; di Piazza Marconi a Cremona.” In &lt;em&gt;Arredi di lusso di età romana: Marmi e bronzi nelle case della Cisalpina: Atti della Giornata di Studi (Milano 2009&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; ed. F. Slavazzi (&lt;em&gt;Lanx&lt;/em&gt; 6), 150–60. http:riviste.unimi.it/index.php/lanx/index.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Castoldi 2014&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Castoldi, M. 2014. &lt;em&gt;Alberi di bronzo: Piante in bronzo e in metalli preziosi nell’antica Grecia&lt;/em&gt;. Bari: Edipuglia.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Clément and Dumoulin 2010&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Clément, N., and F. Dumoulin. 2010. “Deux nouveaux éléments de la statuaire antique d’ &lt;em&gt;Alba Helvorum&lt;/em&gt; sorten de l’ombre.” &lt;em&gt;RANarb&lt;/em&gt; 43: 331–38.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Courbin 1973&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Courbin, P. 1973. “Le colosse naxien et le palmier de Nicias.” &lt;em&gt;BCH&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Suppl&lt;/em&gt; 1.1: 157–72.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Deimel 1987&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Deimel, M. 1987. &lt;em&gt;Die Bronzekleinfunde vom Magdalensberg&lt;/em&gt;. Klagenfurt: Verlag des Landesmuseum für Kärnten.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eichholz 1971&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eichholz, D. E., ed. and trans. 1971. &lt;em&gt;Pliny, Natural History X: Libri XXXVI–XXXVII&lt;/em&gt;. London: W. Heinemann Ltd.; Cambridge (MA): Harvard University Press.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Forrer 1927&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Forrer, R. 1927. &lt;em&gt;Strasbourg&lt;/em&gt;-Argentoratae&lt;em&gt;: préhistorique, gallo-romain et mérovingien&lt;/em&gt;. Strasbourg: Istra.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Gamba 2012&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Gamba, M. 2012. “Il Monte Summano: Un santuario sulle vie della transumanza.” In &lt;em&gt;La lana nella Cisalpina romana: Economia e società: Studi in onore di Stefania Pesavento Mattioli: Atti del Convegno (Padova-Verona 2011&lt;/em&gt;), ed. M. S. Busana and P. Basso, 81–95. Padua: University Press.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Gentili 2013&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Gentili, G., ed. 2013. &lt;em&gt;Cleopatra: Roma e l’incantesimo dell’Egitto.&lt;/em&gt; Exh. cat. Rome, Chiostro del Bramante. Milan: Skira.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Gerding 2006&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Gerding, H. 2006. “The Erechtheion and the Panathenaic Procession.” &lt;em&gt;AJA&lt;/em&gt; 110: 389–401.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Giacobello 2005&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Giacobello, F. 2005. “Portalucerne romani in bronzo dall’Italia settentrionale.” In Slavazzi 2005, 119–30.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Giacobello, F. 2008&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Giacobello, F. 2008. &lt;em&gt;Larari pompeiani: Iconografia e culto dei Lari in ambito domestico&lt;/em&gt;. Milan: LED Edizioni Universitarie di Lettere Economia Diritto.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Gschwantler 1986&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Gschwantler, K. 1986. &lt;em&gt;Guss + Form: Sonderausstellung: Bronzen aus der Antikensammlung&lt;/em&gt;. Vienna: Kunsthistorisches Museum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Kaufmann-Heinimann 1998&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Kaufmann-Heinimann, A. 1998. &lt;em&gt;Götter und Lararien aus Augusta Raurica: Herstellung, Fundzusammenhänge und sakrale Funktion figürlicher Bronzen in einer römischen Stadt&lt;/em&gt;. Forschungen in Augst 26. Augts: Römermuseum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Kaufmann-Heinimann 2002&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Kaufmann-Heinimann, A. 2002. &lt;em&gt;Dea Artio, die Bärengöttin von Muri: römische Bronzestatuetten aus einem ländlichen Heiligtum&lt;/em&gt;. Zürich: Chronos; Bern: Bernisches Historisches Museum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Kaufmann-Heinimann and Deschler-Erb 2013&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Kaufmann-Heinimann, A., and E. Deschler-Erb. 2013. &lt;em&gt;Göttlich, menschlich: Römische Bronzen der Schweiz&lt;/em&gt;, ed. M. Bürge. Exh. cat. Zürich, Archaologisches Institut der Universität Zürich.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Kyrieleis 1988&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Kyrieleis, H. 1988. “Offerings of ‘the Common Man’ in the Heraion at Samos.” In &lt;em&gt;Early Greek Cult Practice:Proceedings of the Fifth International Symposium at the Swedish Institute at Athens, Athens 1986&lt;/em&gt;, ed. R. Hägg, N. Marinatos, and G. C. Nordquist, 215–21. Stockholm and Göteborg: P. Åströms Förlag.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Kyrieleis 1993&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Kyrieleis, H. 1993. “The Heraion at Samos.” In &lt;em&gt;Greek Sanctuaries: New Approaches&lt;/em&gt;, ed. N. Marinatos and R. Hägg, 125–53. London: Routledge.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Menzel 1966&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Menzel, H. 1966. &lt;em&gt;Die römischen Bronzen aus Deutschland&lt;/em&gt;. Vol. 2: &lt;em&gt;Trier&lt;/em&gt;. Mainz: Verlag des Römisch-Germanischen Zentralmuseums.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Palagia 1984&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Palagia, O. 1984. “A Niche for Kallimachos’ Lamp?” &lt;em&gt;AJA&lt;/em&gt; 88: 515–21.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Pirzio Biroli Stefanelli 1990&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Pirzio Biroli Stefanelli, L. 1990. &lt;em&gt;Il bronzo dei Romani: Arredo e suppellettile&lt;/em&gt;. Rome: L’Erma di Bretschneider.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Rouse 1902&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Rouse, W. H. D. 1902. &lt;em&gt;Greek Votive Offerings: An Essay in the History of Greek Religion&lt;/em&gt;. Cambridge (MA): At the University Press.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Schaeffer 1927&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Schaeffer, F. A. 1927. &lt;em&gt;Un dépôt d’outils et en trésor de bronzes de l’époque gallo-romaine découverts à Seltz (Bas Rhin)&lt;/em&gt;. Haguenau: Imprimerie Municipale.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Schnitzler 1995&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Schnitzler, B. 1995. &lt;em&gt;Bronzes antique d’Alsace: Musée archéologique de Strasbourg, Musées de Biesheim, Colmar, Haguenau, Mulhouse, Niederbronn, Wissembourg&lt;/em&gt;. Inventaire des collections publiques française 37. Paris: Réunion des musée nationaux.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Sena Chiesa and Pontrandolfo 2015&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Sena Chiesa, G., and A. Pontrandolfo, eds. 2015. &lt;em&gt;Mito e natura: Dalla Grecia a Pompei&lt;/em&gt;. Exh. cat. Milan, Palazzo Reale. Milan: Electa.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Slavazzi 2005&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Slavazzi, F., ed. 2005. &lt;em&gt;Arredi di lusso di età&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;romana: Da Roma alla Cisalpina&lt;/em&gt;. Flos Italiae 6. Florence: All’insegna del giglio.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Slavazzi 2015&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Slavazzi, F. 2015. “La rappresentazione della natura nelle residenze imperiali: le immagini dei giardini.” In Sena Chiesa and Pontrandolfo 2015, 231–38.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Zieling and Leih 2004&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Zieling, N., and S. Leih 2004. “Rheinisches Amt für Bodendenkmalpflege\ Ausgrabungen, Funde und Befunde 2001 und 2002.” &lt;em&gt;BJb&lt;/em&gt; 204: 273–357.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;Castoldi 2014, 11–13, with bibliography.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;Rouse 1902, 66; Kyrieleis 1988; Kyrieleis 1993, 138.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;See Castoldi 2014, 18–27, with bibliography.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;The source is Plutarch &lt;em&gt;De Pythiae oraculis&lt;/em&gt; 399e; idem., &lt;em&gt;Convivium septem sapientium&lt;/em&gt; 164a; see Castoldi 2014, 44–51.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;Plutarch &lt;em&gt;Nicias&lt;/em&gt; 13.5; &lt;em&gt;De Pythiae oraculis&lt;/em&gt; 397f; Castoldi 2014, 51–58.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;Pausanias 10.15.4. Amandry 1954; Bommelaer and Laroche 1991, 186, no. 420.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;Plutarch &lt;em&gt;Nicias&lt;/em&gt; 3.7. Courbin 1973; Castoldi 2014, 58–60.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;Carapanos 1878, 91, plate XLIX.8. This beautiful branch is now displayed in the National Archaeological Museum in Athens, Bronze Collection.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;Castoldi 2014, 32–41.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;Castoldi 2014, 87–94.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;FHG&lt;/em&gt; III 493, 11.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;Pliny &lt;em&gt;Historia naturalis&lt;/em&gt; 37.6.14; Eichholz 1971, 175.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;Pausanias 1.26.6–7. See also Palagia 1984; Gerding 2006, 394–97; Castoldi 2014, 81–85.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;Pliny &lt;em&gt;Historia naturalis&lt;/em&gt; 34.8.14; see also Castoldi 2014, 7.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34;&gt;Calandra 2015.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34;&gt;Calandra 2008; Calandra 2009; Calandra 2011.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:18&#34;&gt;Athenaeus 5.196a–197c.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:18&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:19&#34;&gt;Slavazzi 2015.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:19&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:20&#34;&gt;For the lampstand from Cremona (&lt;em&gt;domus&lt;/em&gt; del Ninfeo), see Castoldi 2010, 153, fig. 2.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:20&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:21&#34;&gt;For this lampstand &lt;em&gt;a canna&lt;/em&gt; (bamboo-shaped), see Bailey 1996, 94–96, plates 109–15; for northern Italy, see Giacobello 2005.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:21&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:22&#34;&gt;For Pompeii, see Pirzio Biroli Stefanelli 1990, and for the candelabrum “della Meloria”, see Beschi 1984, 54–55; Castoldi 2005, 197–98. Another lampstand modeled as tree is one found in Alba Helvorum (France): Clément and Dumoulin 2010, 336, fig. 4.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:22&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:23&#34;&gt;Gentili 2013, 267, no. 62; see also Bailey 1996, 98–99, plate 118–21.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:23&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:24&#34;&gt;Pompeii: Pirzio Biroli Stefanelli 1990, 276, no. 80, fig. 186. Ephesos: Bol 1970, 82–90, figs. 6–7. Baden: Kaufmann-Heinimann and Deschler-Erb 2013, 48, fig. 21. Kansas City: Bieber 1963. Brigetio: Gschwantler 1986, 139, no. 218, fig. 280; given its small size, this piece could have been part of a domestic shrine.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:24&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:25&#34;&gt;We may remember the statues of nude youths in the tradition of the fifth century that have become tray-bearers or lamp-holders: see &lt;em&gt;supra&lt;/em&gt; the paper of Carol Mattusch.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:25&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:26&#34;&gt;British Museum, inv. Q 3909: Bailey 1996, 99, plates 124–25.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:26&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:27&#34;&gt;See Bolla 2007, 248, figg. 3–4; the tree and the statuette have the same patina; they were found in Predelle (Gazzo Veronese) in a residential setting.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:27&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:28&#34;&gt;Beschi 1962, 102–104; Kaufmann-Heinimann 1998, 293, GF94.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:28&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:29&#34;&gt;See now Bolla 2015, 284–87.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:29&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:30&#34;&gt;Magdalensberg: Deimel 1987, 167, no. 4, plate 32. Strasbourg-Argentoratae: Forrer 1927, 495, fig. 365 C; Schnitzler 1995, 82, no. 87. Seltz: Schaeffer 1927, 38–39, no. 21, plate VIII; Kaufmann-Heinimann 1998, 262, GF45, fig. 219. Hintzerath, Kr. Bernkastel (Trier): Menzel 1966, 80, no. 192, plate 62. Zugmantel: Büttner 1962, 74 (ZM 2750), plate 7.11. Bonn, legion camp: Zieling and Leih 2004, 322, fig. 37.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:30&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:31&#34;&gt;Compare for instance the spiral trees from Brigetio, Hintzerath, and Kansas City; or the specimens from Seltz and Strasbourg-Argentoratae, which are very similar; for bibliography, see nn. 23 and 29 above.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:31&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:32&#34;&gt;Gamba 2012, fig. 4.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:32&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:33&#34;&gt;Kaufmann-Heinimann 2002, 48–53.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:33&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:34&#34;&gt;See Giacobello 2008, 99–100, figs. 2, 9, 11, 13, 18–20.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:34&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bronze Medical and Writing Cases in Classical and Hellenistic Macedonia</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artifacts/32-ignatiadou/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artifacts/32-ignatiadou/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Parexodos&lt;/em&gt; is the name ascribed in the Hippocratic Corpus to the portable medical case that a doctor must own, to facilitate work outside his premises. In it, he could store prepared medicaments and also his tools: “ἔστω δέ σοι ἑτέρη παρέξοδος ἡ λιτοτέρη πρὸς τὰς ἀποδημίας ἡ διὰ χειρῶν &amp;hellip; [Be sure to possess another portable case, simpler and hand-held for travels &amp;hellip;]” (&lt;em&gt;De decente habitu&lt;/em&gt; 8.10–11).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are familiar with the medical cases of the Roman period, which are rectangular boxes with sliding lids and rectangular compartments,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; but our knowledge of the medical cases of the Classical and Hellenistic periods remains limited. In Macedonia, older and recent finds illuminate an important production of multi- and single-compartment medical and writing cases of those periods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;type-a-cases-late-classical-period&#34;&gt;Type A Cases: Late Classical Period&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two cases, from Stavroupolis and Derveni, were found in secure Late Classical contexts and remain the only examples of the Classical period and of this particular type: a cylindrical body comprising two lidded parts, hinged lengthwise. It is very probable that both were made in the same workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first was found in Stavroupolis in Thessaloniki, on Oreokastrou Street, in a cist grave containing a burial of 350‒325 BC (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 32.1a‒b&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It is the most complete and sophisticated case, found in an elite male burial of a warrior and priest. It consists of two hinged half-cylinders with lidded compartments and a built-in inkwell. The case is fully portable as it could be latch-locked and suspended from two loops at the far right end. The upper half-cylinder has its own internal lid, which is hinged at its outer edges, a movable arched handle, and locks in three places. The lower half-cylinder is divided by transverse sheets into three compartments; the left is one-half the length of the whole, and the other two are one-quarter each. One of the dividers is made of lead, and it could be interpreted as a repair; but this practice is noticed in the Archontiko case too (see below), therefore another interpretation might apply. The first two compartments have their own hinged lids with handles and locks. The right compartment has a removable flat top with a central perforation. Underneath it are the remains of a black substance within a circle. The case is made of yellowish high-tin bronze and all the inner lids and the periphery of the hole are decorated with triple silver-gilt lines with small incisions. It is 22.5 centimeters long, and 5.5 centimeters in diameter when closed. It has been mended and restored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deceased in the Stavroupolis burial was a warrior, as we know from his grave goods; however, there are also finds that indicate a religious aspect of his status, such as a set of ritual silver vessels. The most impressive item in the burial was a unique silver-legged stool, a piece of furniture with an established association with the representation of gods, heroes, and priests. The burial had been disturbed by modern digging machinery and the finds were collected rather than excavated. It is probable that the case had been placed in the grave with some other contents that were overlooked or destroyed. As the burial can be dated after the middle of the fourth century BC, the case was probably manufactured in the first half of the same century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Stavroupolis case was interpreted as a writing case until recently, when the investigation of the Derveni find, discussed below, led scholars to suspect it was intended instead for medical purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second case of Type A was found in Derveni, near Thessaloniki, in Cist Grave B with a burial of around 320 BC (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 32.2.a‒c&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This burial contained the cremated remains of a man and another individual inside the spectacular Derveni krater. Among the numerous accompanying grave goods was a bronze case (B 35) that still preserved its contents and was interpreted as a cosmetics container. The existence of a second individual in this grave, perhaps a woman, has puzzled researchers because there were no grave goods that could be associated with a woman. In fact, the case presented here was thought to be the main indication for the cremation of a female consort. The find was displayed for more than fifty years with the lid permanently half closed. It is made of high-tin bronze and is divided in three compartments with a flat ledge and a rod fastened on the ledge with copper nails. The lid is made of a single flat sheet, fastened at its extremities with a lengthwise wire rod, and decorated with incised lines along its edges. On the front middle of the lid is an arched handle of ordinary bronze, attached by means of two strips penetrating the sheet and bent underneath. Flanking the handle are two elongated latch holes. One hole and two dents along the right edge of the lid have been patched from behind with a bronze strip. It is 13 centimeters long, and 4.9 centimeters wide. Its height when closed is 2.1 centimeters. The lid measures 12.5 by 4.7 by 0.1 centimeter, and the handle is 1.7 by 2.5 centimeters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside the compartments the original contents are preserved: three masses of “clay.” The left and the middle bits appear to have been pinched with naked fingers while the right one had been originally pressed inside a miniature pyxis. On the middle one, a mass of cellulose fibers remains. The inorganic and mineral composition of the three cakes is similar but not identical, and it seems that each one was a deliberate preparation, to be used as medication. Their main constituents are quartz, mica, and chlorite (41‒44 percent), plus 16‒31 percent of amorphous materials. Fifty-three (53) organic fatty acids were determined in traces, for the moment only chemically, and our efforts continue toward determining their origin in particular herbs, oils/fats, or condiments. The finger impressions on the two cakes show that the healer was taking small amounts to administer in the form of pills.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other bronze and copper parts related to the Derveni case were retrieved from the same grave (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 32.2c&lt;/strong&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lid B 90a (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 32.2c, top&lt;/strong&gt;) is a second, but longer, bronze lid preserving two latches and also repaired. It is 25.2 centimeters long and 4.5 centimeters wide; the bronze sheet is 0.1 centimeter thick. The handle measures 2.5 by 3.2 centimeters, with latch holes 4.5 centimeters from the corresponding short side.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lid B 90b (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 32.2c, bottom middle&lt;/strong&gt;) is a small square bronze lid with a ring handle, perhaps a replacement part. It is 5.3 centimeters long, and 4.5 centimeters wide. The bronze sheet is again 0.1 centimeter thick. The diameter of the ring (handle) is 1 centimeter, while the latch holes are 2.5 centimeters from the left side and 2.3 centimeters from the right.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The bronze top of B 90c (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 32.2c, bottom right&lt;/strong&gt;) is flat and perforated, decorated with incised lines. It was probably fitted with a small cylinder made of a single flat sheet fastened with a bronze nail; this is evidently the lid of an inbuilt inkwell. It is 5.1 centimeters long and 4.9 centimeters wide, with a sheet thickness of 0.1 centimeter. The diameter of the perforation is 1.4 centimeters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Case B 43 has two miniature, undecorated, semi-spherical bowls of hammered copper. They contained remains of a dark cake, of a nature similar to that of the “clays” in Case B 35. The dimensions of the bowls (4.4 cm in diameter, height 2.1 cm) permit the hypothesis that they could originally have fit inside the compartments of the case.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Differences in surface preservation resulted when some were mechanically cleaned, some chemically cleaned, while others are still untreated. Nevertheless, all of these non-assembled parts probably belong to the same original case as the restored Case B 35. The long lid of Case B 90a indicates the full length of the complete case, which probably looked similar to the Stavroupolis one. The wear and repairs show that it had been used for a long time before the interment, around 320 BC, and we can therefore date the manufacture of the find to the first half of the fourth century BC. It is further possible that the complete case was modified so that the now-restored part had become detachable; it might then be used independently by the healer, who may have inherited it from his father in continuation of a family tradition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companion bronze finds in the burial confirm the medical use of the case: these include a miniature pyxis that contained red hematite powder, a spatula probe, a spatula scoop, a rare catheter/clyster, and numerous stone alabastra that probably originally contained medicaments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deceased in Derveni Grave B was a high priest, entitled to be buried inside the krater associated with his cultic duties,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:6&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and also evidently a warrior, since he was buried with his armor and weapons. The inscription on the krater’s rim associates him with Larissa, the workplace of Hippocrates, who also died and was buried there, and consequently with the Hippocratic tradition of Thessalian healers.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:7&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;type-b-cases-late-classical-or-early-hellenistic-period&#34;&gt;Type B Cases: Late Classical or Early Hellenistic Period&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several other cases have been found in Macedonian burials. These cases also have a semi-cylindrical body, but their compartments may be lidded and/or topped by a flat sheet perforated to give inside access. These perforations are either rectangular or round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One such case (Case A) was found in Pydna (Kitros, Alykes), in a Macedonian tomb with burials of the third and second centuries BC. Like the others, it is bronze and a semi-cylindrical case with hinged lid,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:8&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; dating to the late fourth to early third century BC. Its parts are housed in the Archaeological Ephorate of Pieria/Archaeological Museum of Thessaloniki (inv. Py 683, Py 684, Py 686, Py 688) (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 32.3&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three cases were retrieved from this tomb in the south cemetery of ancient Pydna. It was built in the early third century BC but remained in use for successive burials for more than a century. The finds have been treated but not assembled or restored. It is not clear whether Cases A and B (discussed below) were originally used independently or were combined in one cylindrical unit like the Stavroupolis case. Additionally, two bronze lock plates, which may be associated with the cases,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:9&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; one small bronze pyxis, and one bronze probe were found in the tomb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Case A is a nearly complete lidded and latched case with three compartments made of high-tin alloy. Its top has three circular openings, outlined with incised concentric circles. The lid is undecorated and fastened by means of a flat rod. Flanking the handle are two stepped bosses covering the dowels used to turn the latches. The body (Py 684) is a semi-cylindrical curved sheet preserved in four fragments (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 32.3, bottom&lt;/strong&gt;). As preserved, it is 12 centimeters long, 4.8 centimeters wide, and 1.6 centimeters high. The sheet thickness is less than 0.1 centimeter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The body side (Py 688) consists of one semi-circular sheet; it is probably one short side of Py 684. It measures about 4.7 centimeters (est. because of broken tip) by 2 centimeters, with a thickness of 0.07 centimeter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The top (Py 686, Py 691) consists of a flat rectangular sheet with three circular openings (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 32.3, middle&lt;/strong&gt;). It was probably fastened on top of the curved sheet (Py 684). Each opening was approximately 3.6 centimeters wide and is outlined with two incised concentric circles at a distance of 0.4 centimeter from each other. From the largest fragment, preserving nearly half the length, we can estimate the total length of this element to be 15.6 centimeters and its width to be at least 4.8 centimeters. The thickness is 0.07 centimeter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lid (Py 683, &lt;strong&gt;fig. 32.3, top&lt;/strong&gt;) consists of a single flat sheet with a moving arched handle. On top of its upper surface and along the back long side is attached a flat rod with pointed ends. Both back corners of the lid are missing; it is therefore not possible to see how it was connected to the body. On the front middle of the lid is an arched moving handle with curved-back terminals. The handle was attached to the sheet by means of two strips penetrating the sheet; these survive only partly. Flanking the handle are two stepped bosses covering the dowel attachments of the latches on the other side of the lid, and probably also used to swivel the latches. The bosses are placed at a distance of 1.7 centimeters from the corresponding short sides and 0.6 centimeter from the long side. The latches are made of a contoured sheet (like two back-to-back C-shaped elements) at the end of a long strip, which survives only partly; the latches were obviously swiveling around the dowel so that the protruding strip would catch against an opposite side. The surface is corroded but from the uncorroded patches it is evident that the lid is not decorated with incisions. It was mended but not restored. The lid measures 16.3 by 5.2 centimeters; the handle is 2.9 by 2 centimeters; the bosses are 0.9 centimeter in diameter. The latches (preserved) are 1.2 by 1.2 centimeters; the rod is 16.7 by 0.3 by 0.1 centimeter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Case B is also a bronze semi-cylindrical (Py 692), preserved at the Archaeological Ephorate of Pieria/Archaeological Museum of Thessaloniki. It too comes from Pydna, from the same tomb as Case A (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 32.4&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Case B is a semi-cylindrical case with three compartments, but it is shorter than Case A. Only the body is preserved, with visible marks on the places where the compartment dividers once were. It is also possible that some of the top parts attributed to Case A belong to this case instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The body consists of one nearly complete semi-cylindrical curved sheet, mended but not restored. It was originally divided lengthwise in three compartments. Their exact original places are still visible on the concave side, as straight corrosion lines. Each of the three compartments was approximately 4.7 centimeters long. It is 14.5 centimeters long and about 4.8 centimeters wide (present but distorted width, 4.2 cm), with a height of 2.3 centimeters. The thickness is 0.05 centimeters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A third case from the Pydna tomb, Case C, is once again a bronze semi-cylindrical case with a perforated top. It is preserved in the Archaeological Ephorate of Pieria/Archaeological Museum of Thessaloniki (inv. Py 644, Py 645, Py 687, Py 689, Py 690; &lt;strong&gt;fig. 32.5&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Case C is a single compartment case with a recessed top with a square perforation. In the recess fits a bronze “palette” that can slide to cover or uncover the perforation. A lid slightly larger than the top and with a similar perforation was probably fitted on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The body of Case C consists of one nearly complete semi-cylindrical curved sheet (Py 690), mended but not restored. It is 6.7 centimeters (its present but distorted width is 4.2 cm), and it is 2.3 centimeters high. The thickness is less than 0.1 centimeter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The body side of Case C consists of one semi-circular sheet (Py 687), about 3.9 by 1.9 centimeters, with a thickness of 0.05 centimeter. Alternatively, this element could be one of the short sides or a divider of Case B.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The top of Case C is a flat rectangular sheet with a recessed rectangular area and a square perforation (Py 689). It measures 6.8 by 4.7 cm centimeters. The recessed area is 5 by 3 centimeters and about 2.4 centimeters deep. The flat rim is 0.85 centimeters wide. The thickness is 3.1 centimeters, and the thickness of the sheet is 0.7 millimeters. The perforation is 1 by 1 centimeter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “palette” of Case C is a rectangular bronze piece that fits inside the recessed area of the top and can slide to the right or left (Py 645). It is decorated with a set of parallel engraved lines visible along one short side, but these may have continued along all sides. The piece is 3.7 by 3 centimeters with a thickness of 1.5 millimeters. The “lid” of Case C is a rectangular bronze sheet with square perforation and two sets of finely engraved circles around it (Py 644). Underneath, a rough deteriorated area along the sides at the center shows a shinier (silver gilt?) area, more or less corresponding to the recessed area of the top. The piece measures 7.2 by 5.2 centimeters; the perforation is 1.3 by 1 centimeters, and the thickness is 0.1 centimeter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our next examples come from Archontiko, near Pella, Pit Grave 325 A of the fourth century BC. Two bronze semi-cylindrical cases with hinged lids&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:10&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; are preserved in the Archaeological Museum of Pella (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 32.6&lt;/strong&gt;). Two individual lidded cases and two lids were found in a late fourth-century-BC burial in the Archaic and Classical cemetery. It is possible that they all belonged to the same sophisticated case. They preserve small quantities of their contents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another bronze semi-cylindrical case and stone palette was discovered in Veroia, Building Block 305, on a side street off Ploutarchou Street, in a vaulted rock-cut tomb (Tomb III) with a burial of the third century BC.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:11&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It is preserved in the Archaeological Museum of Veroia (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 32.7&lt;/strong&gt;). This case, with three compartments and a perforated top, has a long body with two preserved dividers, making one long compartment in the middle and two short ones at the ends. The top has three perforations: two large rectangular ones left and right, and one smaller rectangular at the center right. Thus the central compartment top features two sets of concentric decoration but only one off-center perforation. A lid is not preserved. With it was found a stone palette that could be associated with one of the larger perforations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another bronze case with three compartments was unearthed during a rescue excavation at Amphipolis. The dating is uncertain but may be fourth/third century BC.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:12&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The top features one rectangular and two round perforations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, from the archaeological site at Edessa comes a small, single-compartment bronze case with feet (&lt;strong&gt;fig. 32.8&lt;/strong&gt;). It was found on a rural road, in Grave II with burial of the second century BC.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:13&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The semi-cylindrical body is supported on two contoured sheet feet. It has a flat top with a central small round perforation. There is no lid. It is thought to be an inkwell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-greek-tradition-of-medical-and-writing-cases&#34;&gt;The Greek Tradition of Medical and Writing Cases&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the pre-Roman medical cases were probably wooden and have not survived; it is therefore risky to make assumptions as to their shape. Only one, but very important, wooden find testifies to the existence of (semi-)cylindrical cases that appear to have been the forerunners of the Macedonian finds. It is a semi-cylindrical wooden case, unearthed in the “Tomb of the Poet” in Athens, the burial of a musician and author from around 430/420 BC. The case was found together with a bronze stylus, a bronze bowl, remains of five wooden writing tablets, and a papyrus roll.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:14&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Thus the construction of similar bronze cases in fourth-century BC Macedonia appears to be the evolution of an earlier Greek tradition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The semi-cylinder is an awkward and unstable shape, unless it is associated with a second semi-cylinder to form a cylinder: the perfect shape around which to roll a papyrus sheet. In addition, it is logical to imagine that some semi-cylindrical cases could have originally been incorporated in wooden cylindrical cases, similar in shape to the Stavroupolis find.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This notion of a writing substratum that is rolled around a pen case is known from historical finds. Such a writing case was in the possession of J. W. Goethe and is exhibited in his Weimar house. A similar case in gold-decorated red leather belonged to Napoleon, who gave it as a gift to his friend Marshal Lannes.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:15&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The case proper accommodates pens in the middle, while its two metal ends are an inkwell and an ink powder container. Like our Classical finds, it is a portable case, but used by army officers for writing letters and orders during military campaigns rather than for medical purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bibliography&#34;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Bessios 1985&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Bessios, M. 1985. “Der Grabhügel von Alykes bei Kitros.” In &lt;em&gt;The Archaeologists Speak about Pieria&lt;/em&gt;, 54‒58. Katerini: NELE Pierias (in Greek, German summary).&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Bessios 2010&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Bessios M. 2010. &lt;em&gt;Pieridon Stefanos: Pydna, Methone and the Antiquities of North Pieria&lt;/em&gt;. Katerini: AFE Publications (in Greek).&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Bliquez 2015&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Bliquez, L. J. 2015. &lt;em&gt;The Tools of Asclepius: Surgical Instruments in Greek and Roman Times&lt;/em&gt;. Leiden: Brill.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Boyer, Bel, and Tranoy 1990&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Boyer, R., V. Bel, and L. Tranoy. 1990. “Decouverte de la tombe d’un oculiste à Lyon (fin du IIe s. après J.-C.): Instruments et coffrets avec collyres.” &lt;em&gt;Gallia&lt;/em&gt; 47: 215‒49.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Chrysostomou 2013&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Chrysostomou A. 2013. &lt;em&gt;Ancient Edessa: The Cemeteries&lt;/em&gt;. Volos: Hellenic Ministry of Culture (in Greek).&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Descamps-Lequime 2011&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Descamps-Lequime, S., ed. 2011. &lt;em&gt;Au royaume d’Alexandre le Grand: La Macedoine antique&lt;/em&gt;. Paris: Louvre Museum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Giachi et al. 2013&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Giachi G., P. Pallechi, A. Romualdi, E. Ribechini, J. J. Luceiko, M. P. Colombini, and M. Mariotti Lippi. 2013. “Ingredients of a 2,000-y-old Medicine Revealed by Chemical, Mineralogical, and Botanical Investigation.” &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/em&gt; (January 22), 110.4: 1193–96. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1216776110/-/DCSupplemental&#34;&gt;www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1216776110/-/DCSupplemental&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Ignatiadou 2014a&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Ignatiadou, D. 2014a. “The Stavroupolis Priest-warrior.” In &lt;em&gt;The Greeks: Agamemnon to Alexander the Great,&lt;/em&gt; ed. M. Andreadaki-Vlazaki and A. Balaska, 388–401. Athens: Kapon.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Ignatiadou 2014b&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Ignatiadou, D. 2014b. “The Symbolic Krater.” In &lt;em&gt;Le cratère à volutes: Destinations d’un vase de prestige entre Grecs et non Grecs&lt;/em&gt;, 43‒59. Cahiers du Corpus Vasorum Antiquorum (France) 2.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Ignatiadou 2015&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Ignatiadou, D. 2015. “The Warrior Priest in Derveni Grave B Was a Healer Too.” &lt;em&gt;Histoire, médecine et santé&lt;/em&gt; 8: 89‒113.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Ignatiadou forthcoming&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Ignatiadou, D. Forthcoming. “Burial Practices for Élite Macedonians with Cultic Duties.” In &lt;em&gt;Constituer la tombe: Honorer les défunts en méditerranée hellénistique et romaine: Table ronde organisée par L´Écoloe française d´Athènes et le Centre d´étiudes alexandrines&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Alexandrie, 29 octobre au 1er novembre 2014&lt;/em&gt;, ed. M. D. Nenna, W. van Andringa, and S. Huber.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Katsifas et al. forthcoming&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Katsifas, C., D. Ignatiadou, N. Kantiranis, and G. A. Zachariadis. Forthcoming. “Metal Containers of the 4th century BC: Analysis of Their Composition and Contents.” In &lt;em&gt;9th Aegean Analytical Chemistry Days, 29&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;September‒3 October 2014, Chios, Greece&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Koukouvou 1996&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Koukouvou, A. 1996. “Sidestreet of Ploutarchou Street (Building Block 305).” &lt;em&gt;ADelt&lt;/em&gt; 51, B: 524 (in Greek).&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Pöhlmann 2013&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Pöhlmann, E. 2013. “Excavation, Dating and Content of Two Tombs in Daphne, Odos Olgas 53, Athens.” &lt;em&gt;Greek and Roman Musical Studies&lt;/em&gt; 1: 7‒24.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Romiopoulou 1973‒74&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Romiopoulou, K. 1973‒74. “Oreokastrou Street (Stavroupolis District).” &lt;em&gt;ADelt&lt;/em&gt; 29, B 2: 693 (in Greek).&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Romiopoulou 1989&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Romiopoulou, K. 1989. “Closed Burial Contexts of the Late Classical Period from Thessaloniki.” In &lt;em&gt;Φίλια Έπη εις Γεώργιον Ε. Μυλωνάν&lt;/em&gt; (Festschrift to George Mylonas), 3: 194‒218, plates 45‒58. Athens: Archaeologiki Etaireia (in Greek).&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Themelis and Touratsoglou 1997&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Themelis, P.G., and Y. P. Touratsoglou. 1997. &lt;em&gt;The Derveni Tombs&lt;/em&gt;. Athens: TAP (in Greek, English summary).&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Translated by the author. See also Bliquez 2015, 24.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;E.g. Boyer, Bel, and Tranoy 1990.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;On the burial and the case, Archaeological Museum of Thessaloniki, inv. MTH 7437 see Romiopoulou 1973‒74; Romiopoulou 1989, 215‒6, no. 23, plate 57; Descamps-Lequime 2011, cat. 228 (D. Ignatiadou); Ignatiadou 2014a, cat. no. 384; Ignatiadou (forthcoming).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;Full publication of the medical set in this burial, Archaeological Museum of Thessaloniki, inv. B 35 and B 90, may be found in Ignatiadou 2015. On the metal composition, see Katsifas et al. forthcoming. On the burial and the case, see Themelis and Touratsoglou 1997, 91, plate 103.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;A find of similar composition was retrieved from the second-century BC Pozzino shipwreck in Tuscany; see Giachi et al. 2013.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;Ignatiadou 2014b.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;See discussion in Ignatiadou 2015.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;Bessios 1985; Bessios 2010, 246‒55. I thank the excavator M. Bessios for the privilege of studying these cases.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;They are nearly square bronze sheets, each with two rectangular perforations perpendicular to each other. At each corner is one hole for a bronze nail; diameter 3 mm. Plate (Py 631): 4.1 x 4.2 cm. Perforations 0.8 x 1.3 and 3.6 x 1.1 cm. Thickness of sheet 0.1 cm. Preserved total thickness 1.3 cm. Mended but complete. It preserves the four nails that are attached underneath to two wooden strips; the nails are longer than the thickness of the wood and their extra length is bent along the strip they penetrate. Plate (Py 685): 3.8 x 4.1 cm. Perforations 0.7 x 1.4 and 0.3 x 1.0 cm. Thickness of sheet 0.1 cm. Mended, with missing parts.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;The finds were excavated in the summer of 2004 and are unpublished. For the opportunity to see photographic documentation of their parts and to examine the content remains, I sincerely thank the excavator Pavlos Chrysostomou and the conservator of antiquities Evangelos Chrysostomou. The two-lidded cases were displayed in the exhibition “Before the Great Capital,” in the Archaeological Museum of Pella, in 2016.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;The find is unpublished. For the opportunity to illustrate it here I thank the excavator Angeliki Koukouvou. For a brief report on the excavation, see Koukouvou 1996.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;Archaeological Museum of Amphipolis? The find is unpublished. It was shown in a past meeting of the Archaeological Work in Macedonia and Thrace.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;Chrysostomou 2013, 189, plate 72, cat. 415, 433, 434, and 435.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;Pöhlmann 2013, 12‒4, plate I 8b.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;Dated 1804–1809. 33.2 x 6.3 cm. Fondation Napoléon, Paris. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.napoleon.org/en/collectors_corner/object/files/486393.asp&#34;&gt;http://www.napoleon.org/en/collectors_corner/object/files/486393.asp&lt;/a&gt; (accessed 4-10-2015).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Group of Items from the Campana Collection as an Example of Nineteenth-Century Restoration</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artifacts/33-gulyaeva/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artifacts/33-gulyaeva/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The major part of Marquis Giovanni Pietro Campana’s famous collection came into the Department of Classical Antiquities at the Hermitage Museum in 1861. Among the items were three “shields.” There were no detailed descriptions of them, but they were included in a short list of the objects in a special catalogue.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two of the three were similar: round basins with wide flat rims. The first one was described in Campana’s catalogue as “Scudo rotondo con figura di Arpia in mezzo di bello stile”;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; the second one was described as “Scudo rotondo con chimera a basso rilievo nel mezzo.”&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The third “shield” was listed in catalogues as “Scudo grande con cerchi concentrici di borchie rotonde con in mezzo una figura di chimera in rilievo.”&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1925, some items from the Campana collection were disassembled and the parts that were deemed to be ancient were detached. Today we can only guess what the items looked like when they entered the Hermitage. We know that an appliqué relief of a winged deity was removed from the first item (inv. B. 563). This relief was once presumably attached to the wooden surface of a chariot. What the Campana catalogue described as a “harpy” most likely represented the deity Usil, the Etruscan sun god.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plaque with Usil was attached to a simple flat &lt;em&gt;kardiophylax&lt;/em&gt;, which in turn was attached to the body of the “shield.” Before the &lt;em&gt;kardiophylax&lt;/em&gt; was restored in 2011, it showed traces of the plaque fixture. The &lt;em&gt;kardiophylax&lt;/em&gt; with a figure of a fantastic creature was removed from the second “shield” (inv. B. 559), and the same was done with the third “shield” (inv. B. 535).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plaque with the sun god and the three &lt;em&gt;kardiophylakes&lt;/em&gt; were thoroughly studied and published.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; At that time, the other parts, which were thought to be fake, were left inside the cases, and no attempts were made to restore them. Ultimately, though, it was decided to examine them as well. The first modern examinations began in 2011 in the laboratory of ancient metal conservation at the Hermitage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this investigation, it was discovered that the surfaces of the two similar “shields” were covered with an artificial green patina. Both objects are shaped like round basins, 48 centimeters (18 7/8 in.) in diameter. The items were made up of numerous, diverse fragments soldered on tin and blocked on all surfaces by a thick layer of mastic, which began to burst, flake off, and lose its adhesive properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the conservation of the “shield” with Usil (B. 563), the layers of mastic and a fragment of a bronze leaf, which was fixed on a fabric layer and also covered by mastic, were removed. Places where the rim was soldered to the basin were cleaned and the lead-tin solder that nineteenth-century restorers had used to fill losses in the metal was removed. Loops of a copper alloy, holding two rings of different diameters (2 and 5 cm) inside the shield, were also soldered on with a lead-tin alloy. On the exterior of the object, traces of soldering the &lt;em&gt;kardiophylax&lt;/em&gt; remain. There is a spiral ornament, two round holes in the center, and five small holes on the rim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the center of the next “shield” (B. 559), a small metal detail was mounted with a screw and nut. The rim was fastened to the basin with a tin spot-solder. The considerable difference in the diameters of the basin and the rim was concealed by means of rags and ropes, which were filled in with a thick layer of mastic and sealing wax. To investigate the object properly, layers of mastics were completely removed from the metal surface. The lead-tin solder from the nineteenth century was removed, and small details and fragments were detached. After this conservation treatment, the “shield” practically broke up into two parts: a basin and a rim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nineteenth-century restorers faced a very difficult problem. A lot of fragmentary items found together during excavations were waiting for somebody to understand how to reconstruct them into whole objects. It was as challenging as reassembling mosaics. It was a fascinating but difficult task, considering that sometimes the restorers had only a very vague idea of what kind of objects they were and what exactly they were supposed to look like. Ultimately it was decided to restore our items as shields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relief decorations of recently found Etruscan tombs in Cerveteri may have guided the restorers in their decision. Or perhaps, knowing such items as the Certosa situla or the warrior frescoes, the restorers or their clients thought that they were dealing with parts of shields.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:6&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In any case, they created two round shields with brims, made like broad bands with bent edges and decorated with a number of double-spiral ornaments. They attached &lt;em&gt;kardiophylakes&lt;/em&gt; of the eighth to seventh centuries BC, which at that time were perhaps believed to be originally shield decorations. In the internal part of one shield, newly made bronze loops with rings were affixed, possibly for hanging the shield on a wall or just to imitate rings for fastening belts to the inner part of the shield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, on the outer side of a vessel under the rim, Hermitage conservators detected traces of tin soldering. It looks as though this object was first intended to be a dish or a basin, and that the nineteenth-century restorers soldered handles to it. This idea was not far off the mark, because such basins existed in ancient Italy; only they had no handles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, a basin with a flat rim (now in the Römisch-Germanisches Zentralmuseum in Mainz) has a similar shape and its rim is decorated with the same double-spiral ornament.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:7&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In the Metropolitan Museum of Art, there are twenty-one large shallow bowls coming from an Etruscan tomb.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:8&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; All of them have the same decorations of the rim: three bands of plait pattern. As we can see, the band of our item was attached correctly, with an ornament inside, as if it were a bowl. For the object to be properly restored as a shield, the ornament should have been on the outside, facing the opponent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third object can rightfully be called a shield (inv. 535). It consists of a round copper base with a diameter of 89 centimeters, divided into four parts by concentric circles. Each part is decorated with ranks of hemispheres covering the surface. In total there were eighty-five hemispheres, some of which are missing. In the middle of the shield can be seen solder traces where the &lt;em&gt;kardiophylax&lt;/em&gt; had been removed. On the reverse side of the shield are located two rings and a handle. The shield was previously considered to be entirely fake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is now clear that 61 of the 85 bosses are ancient. The remaining 24 hemispheres, the handle, and two rings, as well as the base were made in brass in the nineteenth century. The ancient hemispheres in the center had tetrahedral spikes, which were sawn off in the nineteenth century, in order to be attached to the base of the shield. Pairs of brass wires with bent ends were soldered with tin to the places where the hemispheres were fastened. Bosses were put on the wires and then fixed by wax gloss oil mastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may suppose that when the nineteenth-century restorers decided to make this shield they had in mind large Villanovan embossed shields of a central-handgrip type.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:9&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In order to carry out this plan, they hammered a bronze sheet and attached various bosses to the body of the shield. Inside they put a crudely-made handle and two rings, which had the same functions as in the “shield” with Usil described above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The walls of Etruscan tombs were sometimes decorated with shields. The walls of the Tomb of Shields and Chairs in the Banditaccha necropolis near Cerveteri, for example, were decorated with cut-out stone shields in relief about a meter in diameter. Under the shields, also carved from stone, stand chairs or thrones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A throne of the same form was found at the Lippi necropolis near Verucchio.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:10&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It is decorated with figurative scenes separated by lines of bronze studs. These studs look very much like the ancient bosses on the Hermitage shield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of our research, it became clear that the items are not entirely fake as was assumed before. Two similar objects in the form of shields most likely are parts of Etruscan paterae or large bowls. It is highly probable that the hemispheres detached from a shield may have been decorations on a wooden item, such as an Etruscan chair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bibliography&#34;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Boriskovskaya 1973&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Boriskovskaya, S. P. 1973. “Bronzovije plastini ot drevneitalijskogo pantzirnogo nabora.” In &lt;em&gt;Pamjatniki antičnogo&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;prikladnogo iskusstva&lt;/em&gt;, ed. X. S. Gorbunova, 5‒15. Leningrad: Avrora.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Cataloghi del Museo Campana 1858&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Cataloghi del Museo Campana, 1858. Classe II. &lt;em&gt;Bronzi Etruschi e Romani&lt;/em&gt;. Rome.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Connolly 1981&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Connolly, P. 1981. &lt;em&gt;Greece and Rome at War&lt;/em&gt;. London: Macdonald Phoebus.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Eles 2000&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Eles, P. von. 2000. &lt;em&gt;Museo Civico Archeologico Verucchio&lt;/em&gt;. Rimini: Province of Rimini.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Guédéonow 1861&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Guédéonow, E. 1861. &lt;em&gt;Notice sur les objects d’art de la Galerie Campana à Rome acquis pour le Musée Impérial de l’Ermitage&lt;/em&gt;. Paris: Raçon.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Haynes 1985&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Haynes, S. 1985. &lt;em&gt;Etruscan Bronzes&lt;/em&gt;. London and New York: Sotheby’s Publications.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Nazo 2003&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Nazo, A. 2003. &lt;em&gt;I bronzi Etruschi e Italici del Römisch-Germanisches Zentralmuseum&lt;/em&gt;. Mainz: Römisch-Germanisches Zentralmuseum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Guédéonow 1861, 41.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;Cataloghi del Museo Campana 1858, 2, VIII: 5.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;Cataloghi del Museo Campana 1858, 2, IX: 2.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;Cataloghi del Museo Campana 1858, 2, VII: 2.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;Boriskovskaya 1973, 5‒15; Haynes 1985, 173, 275‒76 n. 81.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;Connolly 1981, 81, fig. 5; 96.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;Nazo 2003, 89‒91, no. 138, plate 47.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.metmuseum.org/Collections/search-the-collections/247024&#34;&gt;http://www.metmuseum.org/Collections/search-the-collections/247024&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.metmuseum.org/Collections/search-the-collections/247025&#34;&gt;http://www.metmuseum.org/Collections/search-the-collections/247025&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;Connolly 1981, 94.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;Eles 2000, 80‒81, figs. 81, 82.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roman Silhouette Figures</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artifacts/34-franken/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artifacts/34-franken/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The question of original function is of great importance in our attempts to understand any archaeological object. For many ancient bronzes, this question is not easy to answer. Technical features, context of the discovery, or figural parallels can often provide valuable information. First of all, however, one must search for comparable bronzes. Only when one expands one’s view from the individual object to all similar artifacts does it become possible to better understand and assess their shared characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following examples provide a useful illustration of this methodological approach. Under consideration here are sheet-metal silhouette figures dating to the Hellenistic and Roman periods. The figures are cut from flat bronze sheets about 1 to 3 millimeters in thickness; internal details are incised. Sheet-metal silhouettes with similar features can also be found in the Archaic,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Classical,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and early medieval&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; periods, but these sheets and all questionable pieces&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; are only touched upon here for technical and aesthetic comparisons to the silhouettes of individual figures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I begin my analysis with the silhouette of a dancing warrior in Berlin’s Antikensammlung (cat. 1; &lt;strong&gt;fig. 34.1&lt;/strong&gt;). The helmeted warrior (H 10.5 cm) wears a short cloak slung around his waist, and appears to be holding a short knife in the right hand. Spread across his torso is a row of short, mostly parallel incisions, which, to judge from two similar examples, represents either a tightly fitting vest or body hair.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also in Berlin is a long vine leaf sheet with richly incised detail (cat. 2). In the middle, one of two tendrils is framed by an Apollonian cult-statue (a Baitylos); on the edges of the leaf there are masks and ritual objects, including baskets and tympana.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For comparison, I cite nine individual silhouette figures and a group from Tajikistan. The nine are: a Mercury from Chur in Switzerland (cat. 3; &lt;strong&gt;fig. 34.2&lt;/strong&gt;); a dancing girl from the excavations in Tel Dor (Israel) (cat. 4; &lt;strong&gt;fig. 34.3&lt;/strong&gt;); an Apollo with kithara and griffin in Lyon (cat. 6; &lt;strong&gt;fig. 34.4&lt;/strong&gt;); a seated griffin facing right (H 3.9 cm) on the art market (cat. 13); a pantheistic goddess with torch and polos in Munich (so far the only silhouette figure with a border) (cat. 7; &lt;strong&gt;fig. 34.5&lt;/strong&gt;); a dwarf in Parma with very crudely incised interior drawing (cat. 8; &lt;strong&gt;fig. 34.6&lt;/strong&gt;); a Victoria originally shown inscribing a shield in Reggio Emilia (cat. 9; &lt;strong&gt;fig. 34.7&lt;/strong&gt;); a silhouette of a dancing satyr in the Santa Barbara Museum of Art (cat. 11); a satyr with wineskin and kantharos in the Museo Gregoriano Profano at the Vatican (cat. 10; &lt;strong&gt;fig. 34.8&lt;/strong&gt;); and an offering jug in Verona (cat. 12).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of particular interest is a group of silhouette figures from the so-called Oxus Temple in Tajikistan: they show Cupid with grapes, with a kithara, with Psyche, with birds, and so on (cat. 5).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The size of these silhouette figures varies greatly. Their height ranges from barely 6 centimeters (cat. 10; see fig. 34.8) to more than 18 cm (cat. 11). The subjects are equally variable. There are goddesses and gods, for example Victoria (cat. 9; see fig. 7), Apollo (cat. 6; see fig. 34.4), and Mercury (cat. 3; see fig. 2). Particularly striking are the dancing or cavorting figures: a warrior (cat. 1; see fig. 34.1); a girl (cat. 4; see fig. 34.3); and a satyr (cat. 11).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far as is known, the backs of the silhouette figures are all flat. We might therefore conclude that most of the sheets were inlaid in or otherwise attached to a wooden base. Many of the sheets are perforated, suggesting that they were nailed in place. Some of the perforations are carefully worked, whereas others are so crude as to suggest that they are the result of later repairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important features of the silhouette figures can be summarized as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Silhouette figures on sheet metal that can be dated to the Late Hellenistic and Roman periods are extremely rare. Despite an extensive search, this catalog consists of only thirteen examples.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The findspots reveal a wide geographic spread, from France (cat. 6) and Switzerland (cat. 3) to Israel (cat. 4) and Tajikistan (cat. 5). A cluster appears to be in northern Italy, as indicated by the silhouette figures in Reggio Emilia (cat. 9), Veleia (cat. 8), and Verona (cat. 12).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;So far as can be determined, the contexts are exclusively Roman, for example in Chur (cat. 3), Lyon (cat. 6), Veleia (cat. 8), and Verona (cat. 12). There are also two sanctuaries: Tel Dor (cat. 4) and the Oxus Temple (cat. 5).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In style and quality, the silhouette figures show considerable differences, pointing to several workshops. Alongside superficial or clumsy incision, as on the dwarf in Parma (cat. 8; see fig. 34.6), there are also original and expressive or routinely conventional interior drawings, as on the Vatican satyr (cat. 10; see fig. 34.8) or the dancing girl in Tel Dor (cat. 4; see fig. 34.3), and a few works of high quality, such as the Munich goddess (cat. 7; see fig. 34.5) and the Victoria in Reggio Emilia (cat. 9; see fig. 34.7).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The subjects reveal a clear preference for figures from the Apollinian and Dionysian realms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because a number of the sheets must have been affixed to small wooden boxes or other furniture (see cat. 7 and 12), it seems probable that most of the silhouette figures originally served as decoration for wooden musical instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both literary references and a few figural representations indicate that figural inlays in wooden musical instruments are distinct possibilities. Two examples are a bronze lyre from Kertsch, today in St. Petersburg, with apparently secondarily used reliefs of Victoria and Mars on the inner side,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:6&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and a kithara decorated with an image of Marsyas that belongs to a marble statue of Apollo from Bulla Regia, now in Tunis.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:7&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of particular interest is a miniature bronze kithara, which the Akademisches Kunstmuseum of the University of Bonn purchased in 2009.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:8&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The kithara, which originally must have been the attribute of a statuette of Apollo, preserves inlays in different metals on both sides, in imitation of intarsia. On the inner side is a theatrical mask and on the outer side there is a seated Eros. Similarly, we can propose that most of the silhouette-figures were used to adorn actual wooden musical instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;catalog&#34;&gt;Catalog&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cat. 1: Armed dancer. Berlin, Antikensammlung – Staatliche Museen zu Berlin, inv. 31631. H 10.5 cm. D 0.12 cm. Said to be from Etruria. Purchased ca. 1936/37 from the collection of Dr. Albert Figdor, Vienna. Published: Franken 2011 (31631). &lt;strong&gt;Fig. 34.1.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cat. 2. Vine leaf. Berlin, Antikensammlung – Staatliche Museen zu Berlin, inv. Fr. 1552 l. H 11.4 cm. W 9.8 cm. D 0.1–0.3 cm. Findspot unknown. Purchased in 1869 from the estate of Eduard Gerhard. Published: Friederichs 1871, 326, no. 1552 l; Franken 2011 (Fr. 1552 l).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cat. 3. Mercury, probably inlaid in wood. Chur, Rätisches Museum, inv. 67/112. H 6.5 cm. Found in 1967 during excavation of the marketplace in Chur. Published: Siegfried-Weiss 1991, 146, plate 55.1; 80.5. H 6.5 cm. Punched and cut decoration. Dated to the second or third century AD by stylistic similarity to a weapon with inlaid bronze and silver figures on an iron sword. &lt;strong&gt;Fig. 34.2.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cat. 4. Female dancer. Dor, Tel Dor Archaeological Expedition. H 8.2 cm. Found in 1988 in the excavations of Area F at Del Dor. Published: Stern 1994, plate 6.1; Wolff 1994, 506, fig. 30. &lt;strong&gt;Fig. 34.3.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cat. 5. Cupids. Dushanbe, National Museum of Antiquities of Tajikistan, inv. TS 264, 265, 269‒71, 807, 825, 846, 1250, 2158, 7926, o.Nr./1091. H 1.5–6.4 cm. W 1.5–5.3 cm. D 0.05–0.2 cm. From the Oxus Temple (Tajikistan). Published: Dushanbe 1985, 95, no. 225–32, fig. S. 81; Zürich 1989, 48, no. 19 with fig. (Eros; incorrectly described as gilded bronze, dated to first century AD); Rome 1993, 35‒36, no. 18 with ill. (Eros); Lindström 2009, 363, no. 258, with ill. (dated first–second century AD).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cat. 6. Apollo. Lyon, Musée gallo-romaine, inv. Br 26. H 8 cm. Said to be from Lyon, given to the museum in 1890. Published: Bazin 1891, 377, fig. 223; Reinach 1910, 50.2; Boucher 1976, 131; Boucher and Tassinari 1976, 34, no. 26, with ill. &lt;strong&gt;Fig. 34.4.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cat. 7. Goddess. Munich, Staatliche Antikensammlungen und Glyptothek, inv. NI 4536. H 11.1 cm. W 5.9 cm. D ca. 0.09 cm. Findspot unknown. Purchased in 2002 from the art market. Published: Kunstobjekte der Antike 2002, 64–65, no. 3314, fig. p. 6; Schmölder-Veit 2002, 291‒92 (with date in first century AD); Knauß 2002, 313, fig. 21.11; 585, cat. 380. &lt;strong&gt;Fig. 34.5.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cat. 8. Dwarf. Parma, Museo d’Antichità, inv. B 416. H 8.3 cm. D 0.5 cm. From Veleia (inv. 1952, no. 345). Published: D’Andria 1970, 100, no. 156, plate 32. &lt;strong&gt;Fig. 34.6.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cat. 9. Victoria. Reggio Emilia, Museo “Gaetano Chierici” di Paletnologia, inv. 15242. H 12.9 cm. From the surroundings of Reggio Emilia. Published: Bolla 2007/2011, 68–69, no. 46, with ill. &lt;strong&gt;Fig. 34.7.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cat. 10. Satyr. Rome, Vatican Museums, Museo Gregoriano Etrusco, inv. 11510. H 5.8 cm. Findspot unknown. Published: D’Andria 1970, 100, under no. 156. &lt;strong&gt;Fig. 34.8.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cat. 11. Dancing satyr. Santa Barbara, Santa Barbara Museum of Art, inv. 1981.64.18. H 18.4 cm. Findspot unknown. Unpublished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cat. 12. Offering jug. Verona, Museo Archeologico, inv. 22124. H 11.6 cm. Found in 1891 in Verona on the banks of the Adige River. Published: Bolla 1999, 210, 230, fig. 54, plate 75.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cat. 13. Seated griffin. Art market. H 3.9 cm. Findspot unknown. Published: &lt;em&gt;Antiken&lt;/em&gt; 2011, 40, no. 1095, plate 74 (there incorrectly identified as Byzantine).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;acknowledgments&#34;&gt;Acknowledgments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lively discussion followed my presentation on October 17, 2015, at the 19th International Congress on Ancient Bronzes at the Getty Center, Los Angeles. For suggestions and references, I am grateful to J. Daehner, N. Gulyaeva, D. Ignatiadou, C. Mattusch, and J. Pollini. For images, permissions, and additional information I should also like to thank R. Aleotti (Reggio Emilia), M. Bernabò Brea (Parma), M. Bolla (Verona), S. Culpepper Stroup (Washington), W. Geominy (Bonn), L. Hagel (Santa Barbara), F. Knauß (Munich), G. Lindström (Berlin), R. Macellari (Reggio Emilia), A. Paolucci (Rome), J. Rageth (Chur), M. Sannibale (Rome), E. Stern (Tel Dor Excavation), D. Tisserand (Lyon), and A. Viani (Reggio Emilia).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bibliography&#34;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;em&gt;Antiken&lt;/em&gt; 2011&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;em&gt;Antiken&lt;/em&gt;. 2011. Gerhard Hirsch Nachfolger, auction catalog 274. September 20‒21, 2011, Munich.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Arapoyianni 2007&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Arapoyianni, X. 2007. &lt;em&gt;The Temple of Apollo Epikourios at Bassae&lt;/em&gt;. Athens: Archaeological Receipts Fund, Publications Department.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Ars Antiqua 1959&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Ars Antiqua. 1959. &lt;em&gt;Antike Kunstwerke. Nachlaß Dr. Jacob Hirsch,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;II.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Teil und anderer Besitz&lt;/em&gt;. Auc­tion catalog. May 2, 1959, Lucerne.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Bazin 1891&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Bazin, H. 1891. &lt;em&gt;Vienne et Lyon gallo-romains&lt;/em&gt;. Paris: Hachette.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Behn 1954&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Behn, F. 1954. &lt;em&gt;Musikleben im Altertum und frühen Mittelalter&lt;/em&gt;. Stuttgart: Hiersemann.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Blatter 1964&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Blatter, R. 1964. “Ein spätklassisches Athenarelief aus Bronze in Basel.” &lt;em&gt;AA&lt;/em&gt; 1964: cols. 805–23.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Bolla 1999&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Bolla, M. 1999. “Bronzetti figurati romani del territorio Veronese.” &lt;em&gt;Rassegna di studi del Civico Museo Archeologico e del Civico Gabinetto Numismatico di Milano&lt;/em&gt; 63/64:193–260.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Bolla 2007/2011&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Bolla, M. 2007/2011. “Bronzi figurati romani dal territorio reggiano nel Museo Chierici di Reggio Emilia.” &lt;em&gt;Pagine di Archeologia&lt;/em&gt; 4:1–93.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Boucher 1976&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Boucher, S. 1976. &lt;em&gt;Recherches sur les bronzes figurés de Gaule préromaine et romaine&lt;/em&gt;. Rome: BÉFAR 228.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Boucher and Tassinari 1976&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Boucher, S., and S. Tassinari. 1976. &lt;em&gt;Bronzes antiques du Musée de la Civilisation Gallo-Romaine à Lyon.&lt;/em&gt; Vol. 1: &lt;em&gt;Inscriptions, statuaire, vaisselle&lt;/em&gt;. Musée de la Civilisation Gallo-Romaine Lyon. Paris: Boccard.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Brusin 1934&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Brusin, G. 1934. &lt;em&gt;Gli scavi di Aquileia&lt;/em&gt;. Udine: La Panarie.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;D’Andria 1970&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;D’Andria, F. 1970. “I bronzi romani di Veleia, Parma e del territorio parmense.” In &lt;em&gt;Contributi dell’Istituto di Archeologia&lt;/em&gt; 3: 3–144.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Dushanbe 1985&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Dushanbe. 1985. &lt;em&gt;Kunstschätze Tadschikistans&lt;/em&gt;, Exh. cat. Dushanbe, National Museum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Faider-Feytmans 1957&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Faider-Feytmans, G. 1957. &lt;em&gt;Recueil des bronzes de Bavai&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Gallia&lt;/em&gt;, suppl. 8. Paris: Centre national de la recherche scientifique.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Franken 2011&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Franken, N. 2011. &lt;em&gt;Bilddatenbank Antike Bronzen in Berlin&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://ww2.smb.museum/antikebronzenberlin/&#34;&gt;http://ww2.smb.museum/antikebronzenberlin/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Friederichs 1871&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Friederichs, C. 1871. &lt;em&gt;Berlins antike Bildwerke.&lt;/em&gt; Vol. 2: &lt;em&gt;Antike Geräthe und Broncen im Alten Museum.&lt;/em&gt; Düsseldorf: J. Buddens.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Fuchs 1940&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Fuchs, S. 1940. “Figürliche Bronzebeschläge der Langobardenzeit aus Italien.” &lt;em&gt;RM&lt;/em&gt; 55:100–113.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Knauß 2012&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Knauß, F. S., ed. 2012. &lt;em&gt;Die Unsterblichen Götter Griechenlands&lt;/em&gt;. Exh. cat. Munich: Staatliche Antikensammlungen und Glyptothek.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Kunstobjekte der Antike 2002&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kunstobjekte der Antike&lt;/em&gt;. 2002. Gorny &amp;amp; Mosch, auction catalog 119. October 16, 2002, Munich.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Lindström 2009&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Lindström, G. 2009. “Silhouettenbleche: Eroten, ungeflügelte Knabenfiguren, Psychen.” In &lt;em&gt;Alexander der Grosse und die Öffnung der Welt: Asiens Kulturen im Wandel&lt;/em&gt;, edited by. S. Hansen, A. Wieczorek, and M. Tellenbach, 363, cat. no. 258. Exh. cat. Mannheim: Reiss-Engelhorn-Museen.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Massow 1916&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Massow, W. von. 1916. “Die Kypseloslade.” &lt;em&gt;AM&lt;/em&gt; 41: 1–117.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Menzel 1986&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Menzel, H. 1986. &lt;em&gt;Die römischen Bronzen aus Deutschland&lt;/em&gt;.” Vol. 3: &lt;em&gt;Bonn&lt;/em&gt;. Mainz: Römisch-Germanisches Zentralmuseum.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Reinach 1910&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Reinach, S. 1910. &lt;em&gt;Répertoire de la statuaire grecque et romaine&lt;/em&gt;. Vol. 4. Paris: Leroux.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Rome 1993&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Rome. 1993. &lt;em&gt;Oxus: Tesori dell’Asia Centrale.&lt;/em&gt; Exh. cat. Rome, Palazzo Venezia.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Schmölder-Veit 2002&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Schmölder-Veit, A. 2002. “Bronzenes Beschlagblech mit dem Tierkreiszeichen der Jungfrau (Virgo).” &lt;em&gt;MüJb&lt;/em&gt; 53: 291–92.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Siegfried-Weiss 1991&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Siegfried-Weiss, A. 1991. “Figürliche Bronzeobjekte.” In &lt;em&gt;Chur in römischer Zeit&lt;/em&gt;. Vol. 2: A. &lt;em&gt;Ausgrabungen Areal Markthallenplatz&lt;/em&gt;; B. &lt;em&gt;Historischer Überblick&lt;/em&gt;. Basel: Schweizer Gesellschaft für Ur- und Frühgeschichte.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Stern 1994&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Stern, E. 1994. &lt;em&gt;Dor: The Ruler of the Seas&lt;/em&gt;. Jerusalem: Israel Exploration Society.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Vendries 1999&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Vendries, C. 1999. &lt;em&gt;Instruments à cordes et musiciens dans l’empire romain.&lt;/em&gt; Paris: L’Harmattan.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Wolff 1994&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Wolff, S. R. 1994. “Archaeology in Israel.” &lt;em&gt;AJA&lt;/em&gt; 98: 481‒519.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Zürich 1989&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Zürich. 1989. &lt;em&gt;Oxus: 2000 Jahre Kunst am Oxus-Fluss in Mittelasien: Neue Funde aus der Sowjetrepublik Tadschikistan.&lt;/em&gt; Exh. cat. Zürich, Museum Rietberg.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Massow 1916, 21–22, fig. 4 (boar and bull walking toward the left; said to be from Thebes; formerly in Leipzig, Archäologisches Institut der Universität); Arapoyianni 2007, 25, fig. 24 (two large nude men facing left).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;Blatter 1964, cols. 811–12, fig. 4 (woman toward the right; from Athens, Pnyx).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;Fuchs 1940, 110–13, plates 13–16 (sheets serving as shield devices).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;Among them is a victorious charioteer in a broad frame from Aquileia: Brusin 1934, 137, 139, no. 4, fig. 77; a pigeon on a globe from a tomb in Bavai: Faider-Feytmans 1957, 85, no. 163, plate 32; also a dolphin said to be incised on both sides in Bonn: Menzel 1986, 72, no. 166, plate 83.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;For instance on the silhouette figure of a griffin (cat. 13; art market).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;Behn 1954, 85, plate 51, 117 b; Vendries 1999, 50–52, plate 1. A date in the second to third centuries AD, suggested by Vendries on the basis of style can in the case of the lyre’s secondary use provide only a &lt;em&gt;terminus post quem&lt;/em&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;Vendries 1999, 88–95, plate 8c (other examples are at least in part the result of modern restorations).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;Bonn, Akademisches Kunstmuseum. H 7.8 cm. W 6.2 cm: Ars Antiqua 1959, 35, no. 90, plate 43.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34;&gt;↥&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Balancing Artifacts</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artifacts/abstract-de-angelis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artifacts/abstract-de-angelis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Figures on Fire</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artifacts/abstract-bielfeldt/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artifacts/abstract-bielfeldt/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Standspiegel, Figured Appliqués, and Other Bronze Items at Locri Epizefiri (Magna Graecia)</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artifacts/abstract-elia-meriano/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artifacts/abstract-elia-meriano/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bibliography&#34;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Cameron 1979&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Cameron, F. 1979. &lt;em&gt;Greek Bronze Hand-Mirrors in South Italy&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford: British Archaeological Reports.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Elia 2010&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Elia, D. 2010. &lt;em&gt;Locri Epizefiri&lt;/em&gt; 6. Alessandria: Edizioni dell’Orso.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Meirano 2002&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Meirano, V. 2002. “Utensil Stands da Locri Epizefiri.” In &lt;em&gt;I bronzi antichi: produzione e tecnologia: Atti XV Congresso Internazionale sui Bronzi Antichi&lt;/em&gt;, ed. A. Giumlia-Mair, 117–26. Montagnac: Editions Monique Mergoil.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Multidisciplinary Study of Hellenistic and Roman Bronze Mirrors from the Archaeological Collection of Ancient Messene, Greece</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artifacts/abstract-giannoulaki/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artifacts/abstract-giannoulaki/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Gréau Mirror and the Phenomenon of Fakes in Nineteenth-Century Paris</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artifacts/abstract-lee/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artifacts/abstract-lee/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Ancient Chariot from Serbia</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artifacts/abstract-milanovic-ratkovic-petelin-colovic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artifacts/abstract-milanovic-ratkovic-petelin-colovic/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bronze Warfare from the Hellenistic Period</title>
      <link>https://gettypubs.github.io/artifacts/abstract-tisseyre/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gettypubs.github.io/artifacts/abstract-tisseyre/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>