<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Artifacts on </title>
    <link>/artifacts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Artifacts on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    
	<atom:link href="/artifacts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Artifacts</title>
      <link>/artifacts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/artifacts/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Minoan Status Symbols</title>
      <link>/artifacts/30-ferrence-giumlia-mair/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/artifacts/30-ferrence-giumlia-mair/</guid>
      <description>Introduction For our project on Minoan metallurgy, many objects of various sizes, belonging to several classes, and made of different metals were analyzed by X-ray fluorescence (XRF). The items come from different sites in eastern Crete, one of which is the Minoan town of Gournia, which was excavated in the early twentieth century.1 With the support of the University of Pennsylvania Museum of Archaeology and Anthropology (hereafter, Penn Museum) in Philadelphia and private donors, Harriet Boyd Hawes and her collaborators, Richard Seager and Edith Hall, excavated the settlement of Gournia in three campaigns in 1901, 1903, and 1904 and published the discoveries in 1908.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bronze Trees from the Greek to the Roman World</title>
      <link>/artifacts/31-castoldi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/artifacts/31-castoldi/</guid>
      <description>It is well known that trees, gardens, and landscapes are not commonly represented in Greek art until the Hellenistic period. In vase painting, the focus is on men, gods, and heroes; war, hunting, labor, rituals, weddings, death, and festivals offer the opportunity to represent humans, who are at the center of philosophy and art in ancient Greece. Nature and landscapes, by contrast, rarely appear in vase painting; floral patterns, tendrils, and leaves only appear as subsidiary decoration.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bronze Medical and Writing Cases in Classical and Hellenistic Macedonia</title>
      <link>/artifacts/32-ignatiadou/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/artifacts/32-ignatiadou/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Parexodos is the name ascribed in the Hippocratic Corpus to the portable medical case that a doctor must own to facilitate work outside his premises. In it, he could store prepared medicaments and also his tools: “ἔστω δέ σοι ἑτέρη παρέξοδος ἡ λιτοτέρη πρὸς τὰς ἀποδημίας ἡ διὰ χειρῶν … [Be sure to possess another portable case, simpler and hand-held for travels … ]” (De decente habitu 8.10–11).1</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Group of Items from the Campana Collection as an Example of Nineteenth-Century Restoration</title>
      <link>/artifacts/33-gulyaeva/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/artifacts/33-gulyaeva/</guid>
      <description>The major part of Marquis Giovanni Pietro Campana’s famous collection came into the Department of Classical Antiquities at the Hermitage Museum in 1861. Among the items were three “shields.” There were no detailed descriptions of them, but they were included in a short list of the objects in a special catalogue.1
Two of the three were similar: round basins with wide flat rims. The first one was described in Campana’s catalogue as “Scudo rotondo con figura di Arpia in mezzo di bello stile”;2 the second one was described as “Scudo rotondo con chimera a basso rilievo nel mezzo.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roman Silhouette Figures</title>
      <link>/artifacts/34-franken/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/artifacts/34-franken/</guid>
      <description>The question of original function is of great importance in our attempts to understand any archaeological object. For many ancient bronzes, this question is not easy to answer. Technical features, context of the discovery, or figural parallels can often provide valuable information. First of all, however, one must search for comparable bronzes. Only when one expands one’s view from the individual object to all similar artifacts does it become possible to better understand and assess their shared characteristics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Balancing Artifacts</title>
      <link>/artifacts/abstract-de-angelis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/artifacts/abstract-de-angelis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Figures on Fire</title>
      <link>/artifacts/abstract-bielfeldt/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/artifacts/abstract-bielfeldt/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Standspiegel, Figured Appliqués, and Other Bronze Items at Locri Epizefiri (Magna Graecia)</title>
      <link>/artifacts/abstract-elia-meriano/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/artifacts/abstract-elia-meriano/</guid>
      <description> Bibliography  Cameron 1979 Cameron, F. 1979. Greek Bronze Hand-Mirrors in South Italy. Oxford: British Archaeological Reports. Elia 2010 Elia, D. 2010. Locri Epizefiri 6. Alessandria: Edizioni dell’Orso. Meirano 2002 Meirano, V. 2002. “Utensil Stands da Locri Epizefiri.” In I bronzi antichi: produzione e tecnologia: Atti XV Congresso Internazionale sui Bronzi Antichi, ed. A. Giumlia-Mair, 117–26. Montagnac: Editions Monique Mergoil.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Multidisciplinary Study of Hellenistic and Roman Bronze Mirrors from the Archaeological Collection of Ancient Messene, Greece</title>
      <link>/artifacts/abstract-giannoulaki/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/artifacts/abstract-giannoulaki/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Gréau Mirror and the Phenomenon of Fakes in Nineteenth-Century Paris</title>
      <link>/artifacts/abstract-lee/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/artifacts/abstract-lee/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Ancient Chariot from Serbia</title>
      <link>/artifacts/abstract-milanovic-ratkovic-petelin-colovic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/artifacts/abstract-milanovic-ratkovic-petelin-colovic/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bronze Warfare from the Hellenistic Period</title>
      <link>/artifacts/abstract-tisseyre/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/artifacts/abstract-tisseyre/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Abstracts</title>
      <link>/artifacts/abstracts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/artifacts/abstracts/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>